<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>Faust Book</title>
&responsibility;
&fund.Tufts;
      </titleStmt>
	&Perseus.publish;
      <sourceDesc>
	<bibl>Thoms, William John, ed. <title>Early English Prose Romances</title>. London: Nattali and Bond, 1858.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
	<step refunit="chapter" delim="." from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %1)"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language id="en">English
	</language><language id="la">Latin
	</language><language id="greek">Greek
	</language><language id="it">Italian
      </language></langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>5/12/97</date>
	<respStmt><name rend="ital">HB</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: efb.xml,v $
Revision 1.2  2004/04/22 15:19:57  cwulfman
fixing log problem.

Revision 1.1  2004/04/22 13:55:23  cwulfman
Making xml files the canonical ones.

Revision 1.7  2003/07/01 22:14:53  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.6  2001/02/09 01:03:13  dasmith
Turned tabs to spaces.

Revision 1.5  2000/04/25 23:06:48  dasmith
Corrected TEI header.

Revision 1.4  1999/09/01 17:15:33  dasmith
Fixed preamble and added encodingDesc.

Revision 1.3  1997/09/01 17:24:13  textgod
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.

Revision 1.2  1997/06/30 21:54:57  textgod
Changed headers (?).

Revision 1.1  1997/06/24 17:35:10  textgod
New name. was gent.

Revision 1.4  1997/05/13 18:23:30  textgod
Fixed trailing spaces in notes.

Revision 1.3  1997/05/13 15:22:18  textgod
Added missing note SEGs.
Formatted table (perhaps it should be a two-column list).
Commented out LINKs for now.

Revision 1.2  1997/05/12 21:08:28  textgod
Fixed some note references.

Revision 1.1  1997/05/12 20:08:31  textgod
Added to repository. Passes validation.


      </item></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<titlePage>
<docTitle><titlePart type="main">The 
Historie 
of the damnable 
life, and the deserved death of 
Doctor Iohn Faustus,</titlePart></docTitle>
<titlePart type="main"><seg id="n0">Newly imprinted</seg><note target="n0" anchored="yes">This edition is the oldest extant. It was printed between May and December, 1592. Dr W. W. Greg in F. S. Boas' edition of Marlowe's Tragical History of Doctor Faustus, London, 1932, p. 7-8, believes (on the evidence in the Records of the court of the Stationers' Company) that one Abell Jaffes printed an earlier edition about MAy 1592. Our own researches tend to confirm this. From internal evidence, vid. note (70), it appears probable that the manuscript was finished before August, 1590.</note>, and i conueni-
ent places imperfect matter amended: 
according to the true Copie printed at Franckfort, and translated into English by P. F. Gent.</titlePart>
<imprimatur>Seene and allowed.</imprimatur>
<docImprint>Imprinted at London by Thomas Orwin, and are to be 
solde by Edward White, dwelling at the little North
doore of Paules, at the sign of the Gun. 1592.</docImprint>
</titlePage>
<argument><p rend="center">
<hi>A Discourse of the Most Famous Doctor</hi>
<hi rend="ital">John Faustus of VVittenberg in Germanie, Con-</hi>
<hi>iurer, and Necromancer: wherein is declared many
strange things that he himself hath seene, and done
in the earth and in the Ayre, with his bringing</hi>
<hi>vp, his trauailes, studies, and last end.</hi></p></argument>
</front>
<body>
<div1 n="1" type="part">
<div2 n="1" type="chapter" id="chap1">
<head><hi rend="ital">Of his Parentage and Birth.</hi> Chap. 1</head>
<p><name>IOhn Faustus</name>, borne in the town of <seg id="n1"><name>Rhode</name></seg><note target="n1" anchored="yes">'Rhode,' modern Roda, about thirty kilometers southeast of Weimar.</note>, lying in the
Prouince of <name>Weimer</name> in <name>Germ<seg id="n2">[anie,]</seg></name><note target="n2" anchored="yes">Illegible in the British Museum copy (hereafter referred to as B.M.).</note> his father a poore
Husbandman, and not <seg id="n3">[able]</seg><note target="n3" anchored="yes">Illegible in B.M.</note> wel to bring him vp: but hauing an Vncle at
<name>Wittenberg</name>, a rich man, &amp; without issue, took this  <name>I. Faustus</name>
from his father, &amp; made him his heire, in so much that his father was
no more troubled with him, for he remained with his Vncle at <name>Wittenberg</name>,
where he was kept at y Vniuersitie in the same citie to study diuinity.
But <name>Faustus</name> being of a naughty minde &amp; otherwise addicted, applied
not his studies, but tooke himselfe to other exercises: the which his Vncle
oftentimes hearing, rebuked him for it, as <name>Eli</name> oft times rebuked his
children for sinning against the Lord: euen so this good man laboured to haue
<name>Faustus</name> apply his study of Diuinitie, that he might come to the
knowledge of God &amp; his lawes.  But it is manifest that many vertuous
parents haue wicked children, as <name>Cayn</name>, <name>Ruben</name>, <name>Absolom</name>, and such like
haue <seg id="n4">b&eacute;en</seg> <note target="n4" anchored="yes">The reason for the accent is not clear.  It occurs in the text only where ee is printed as a ligature.</note>  to their parents: so this <name>Faustus</name> hauing godly
parents, and seeing him to be of <term id="n5">a toward wit</term><note target="n5" type="gloss" anchored="yes">an apt or willing mind</note>, were very desirous to bring him
vp in those vertuous studies, namely, of Diuinitie: but he gaue himself
secretly to study Necromancy and Coniuration, in so much that few or none could
perceiue his profession.</p><p>But to the purpose: <name>Faustus</name> continued at study in the Vniuersity, &amp;
was by the Rectors and sixteene Masters after

wards examined howe he had profited in his studies; and being found by
them, that none for his time were able to argue with him in Diuinity, or for
the excellency of his wisedome to compare with him, with one consent they made
him Doctor of Diuinitie.  But Doctor <name>Faustus</name> within short time after hee
had obtayned his degree, fell into such fantasies and deepe cogitations, that
he was marked of many, and of the most part of the Students was called the
<name>Speculator</name>; and sometime he would throw the Scriptures <milestone n="2" unit="BMP"/> <note anchored="yes">The paging of B.M. is indicated in the brackets.  There are frequent errors in pagination.</note> from
him as though he had no care of his former profession: so that hee began a
very vngodly life, as hereafter more at large may appeare; for the olde Prouerb
sayth, Who can hold that wil away? so, who can hold <name>Faustus</name> from the
diuel, that seekes after him with al his indeuour <seg id="n6">':</seg><note target="n6" anchored="yes">B.M. uses two types of interrogation point, viz., ': and ?  The difference in significance is not clear.  See McKerrow, <name>Introduction to Bibliography</name>, Oxford, 1927, p. 316.</note>  For he accompanied
himselfe with diuers that were <term id="n7">s&eacute;ene</term> <note target="n7" type="gloss" anchored="yes">versed in</note> In those diuelish Arts, and that
had the  <name>Chaldean, Persian, Hebrew, Arabian</name>, and <name>Greeke</name> tongues,
vsing Figures, characters, Coniurations, Incantations, with many other
ceremonies belonging to these infernal Arts as Necromancie, Charmes,
South-saying, Witchcraft, Inchantment, being delighted with their bookes,
words, and names so well, that he studied day and night therein: in so much
that hee could not abide to bee called Doctor of Diuinitie, but waxed a worldly
man, and named himselfe an Astrologian, and a Mathematician: &amp; <term id="n8">for a
shadow</term> <note target="n8" type="gloss" anchored="yes">as a blind</note> sometimes a Phisitian, and did great cures, namely, with hearbs,
rootes, waters, drinks, receipts, &amp; <seg id="n9">clisters</seg>.<note target="n9" type="gloss" anchored="yes">enemas</note>  And without doubt he was
passing wise, and excellent perfect in the holy scriptures: but hee that
knoweth his masters will and doth it not, is worthy to be beaten with many
stripes.  It is written, no man can serue two masters: and, thou shalt not
tempt the Lord thy God: but <name>Faustus</name> threw all this in the winde, &amp;
made his soule of no estimation, regarding more his worldly pleasure than ye
ioyes to come: therfore at ye day of iudgement there is no hope of his
redemptio.</p>
</div2>

<!-- <link targets="chap1 aa1 bb1"> -->

<div2 n="2" type="chapter" id="chap2">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus began to practise in his diuelish  Arte, and how he coniured the Diuel, making him to appeare and meete him on the morrow at his owne house.</hi> Chap. 2</head>
<p>YOu haue heard before, that all <name>Faustus</name> minde was set to study the artes
of Necromancie and Coniuration, the which exercise hee followed day and night:
and taking to him the wings of an Eagle, thought to flie ouer the whole world,
and to know the secrets of heauen and earth; for his Speculation was so
wonderfull, being expert in vsing his <seg id="n10"><name>Vocabula</name></seg><note target="n10" type="gloss" anchored="yes">magic words</note>, Figures, Characters,
Coniurations, and other Ceremoniall actions, that in all the haste hee put in
practise to bring the Diuell before him.  And taking his way to a thicke Wood
neere to <name>Wittenberg</name>, called in the Germane tongue <name>Spisser Waldt</name>:
that is in English the <name>Spissers Wood</name>, (as <name>Faustus</name> would
oftentimes boast of it among his crue being in his iolitie,) he came into the
same wood towards euening into a crosse way, where he made with a wand a Circle
in the dust, and within that many more Circles and Characters: and thus he past
away the time, vntill it was nine or ten of the clocke <milestone n="3" unit="BMP"/> in the night,
then began Doctor <name>Faustus</name> to call for <name>Mephostophiles</name> the Spirite,
and to charge him in the name of <name>Beelzebub</name> to appeare there personally
without any long stay: then presently the Diuel began so great a <term id="n11">rumor</term><note target="n11" type="gloss" anchored="yes">uproar</note> in the
Wood, as if heauen and earth would haue come together with winde, the trees
bowing their tops to the ground, then fell the Diuell to <term id="n12">bleare</term> <note target="n12" type="gloss" anchored="yes">roar</note> as if the
whole Wood had been full of Lyons, and sodainly about the Circle ranne the
Diuell as if a thousand Wagons had been running together on paued stones.
After this at the foure corners of the Wood it thundred horribly, with such
lightnings as if the whole worlde, to his seeming, had been on fire. <name>Faustus</name>
all this while halfe amazed at the Diuels so long tarrying, and doubting
whether he were best to abide any more such horrible Coniurings, thought to
leaue his Circle and depart; wherevpon the Diuel made him such musick of all
sortes, as if the Nimphes themselues had beene in place: whereat <name>Faustus</name>
was reujued and stoode stoutly
in his Circle <seg id="n13">aspecting his purpose</seg>,<note target="n13" type="gloss" anchored="yes">keeping in mind his object</note> and began againe to coniure the spirite
<name>Mephostophiles</name> in the name of the Prince of Diuels to appeare in his
likenesse: where at sodainly ouer his head hanged houering in the ayre a mighty
Dragon: then cals <name>Faustus</name> againe after his Diuelish maner, at which
there was a monstrous crie in the Wood, as if hell had been open, and all the
tormented soules crying to God for mercy; presently not three fadome aboue his
head fell a flame in manner of a lightning, and changed it selfe into a Globe:
yet <name>Faustus</name> feared it not, but did perswade himselfe that the Diuell
should giue him his request before hee would leaue: Oftentimes after to his
companions he would boast, that he had the stoutest head (vnder the cope of
heauen) at commandement: whereat they answered, they knew none stouter than the
Pope or Emperour: but Doctor <name>Faustus</name> said, the head that is my seruant
is aboue all on earth, and repeated certain wordes out of Saint <name>Paul</name> to
the <name>Ephesians</name> to make his argument good: The Prince of this world is
vpon earth and vnder heauen.  Wel, let vs come againe to his Coniuration where
we left him at his fiery Globe: <name>Faustus</name> vexed at the Spirits so long
tarying, vsed his Charmes with full purpose not to depart before he had his
intent, and crying on <name>Mephostophiles</name> the Spirit; sodainly the Globe
opened and sprang vp in height of a man: so burning a time, in the end it
conuerted to the shape of a fiery man. This pleasant beast ranne about the
circle a great while, and lastly appeared in manner of a gray Frier, asking
<name>Faustus</name> what was his request. <name>Faustus</name> commaunded that the next
morning at twelue of the clocke hee should appeare to him at his house; but the
diuel would in no wise graunt: <milestone n="5" unit="BMP"/>  <name>Faustus</name> began againe to coniure
him in the name of <name>Beelzebub</name>, that he should fulfil his request:
whereupon the Spirit agreed, and so they departed each one his way.</p></div2>

<!-- <link targets="chap2 aa2 bb2"> -->
<div2 n="3" type="chapter" id="chap3">
<head><hi rend="ital">The conference of Doctor Faustus with the Spirit Mephostophiles the morning following at his owne house.</hi> Chap. 3</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> hauing commaunded the Spirit to be with him, at his houre
appointed he came and appeared in his
chamber, demanding of <name>Faustus</name> what his desire was: then began Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> anew with him to coniure him that he should be obedient vnto
him, &amp; to answere him certaine Articles, and to fulfil them in al points.

<list type="ordered">
<label>1</label><item>That the Spirit should serue him and be obedient vnto him in all things
that he asked of him from yt houre vntil the houre of his death.</item>
<label>2</label><item>Farther, any thing that he desired of him he should bring it to him.</item>
<label>3</label><item>Also, that in all <name>Faustus</name> his demaunds or Interrogations, the spirit
should tell him nothing but that which is true.</item>
</list>
Hereupon the Spirit answered and laid his case foorth, that he had no such
power of himselfe, vntil he had first giuen his Prince (that was ruler ouer
him) to vnderstand thereof, and to know if he could obtaine so much of his
Lord: therfore speake farther that I may do thy whole desire to my Prince: for
it is not in my power to fulfill without his leaue.  Shew me the cause why
(said <name>Faustus</name>.) The Spirit answered: <name>Faustus</name>, thou shalt
vnderstand, that with vs it is euen as well a kingdome, as with you on earth:
yea, we haue our rulers and seruants, as I my selfe am one, and we name our
whole number the Legion: for although that <name>Lucifer</name> is thrust and falle
out of heauen through his pride and high minde, yet he hath notwithstanding a
Legion of Diuels at his commaundement, that we call the <name>Oriental</name>
Princes; for his power is great and infinite.  Also there is an <seg id="n14">host in
<name>Meridie</name></seg><note target="n14" anchored="yes">'Host' is a mistranslation of the German 'Herrschaft,' kingdom. 'Meridie' is south; 'Septentrio,' north; 'Occidente,' west.</note>, in <name>Septentrio</name>, in <name>Occidente</name>: and for that
<name>Lucifer</name> hath his kingdome vnder heauen, wee must change and giue our
selues vnto men to serue them at their pleasure.  It is also certaine, we haue
neuer as yet opened vnto any man the truth of our dwelling, neither of our
ruling, neither what our power is, neither haue we giuen any man any gift, or
learned him any thing, except he promise to be ours.</p><p>Doctor <name>Faustus</name> vpon this arose where he sate, &amp; said, I wil haue my
request, and yet I wil not be damned.  The spirit answered, Then shalt thou
want thy desire, &amp; yet art

thou mine notwithstanding: if any man would detaine thee it is in vain, for
thine infidelity hath confouded th&eacute;e.</p><p>
<milestone n="4" unit="BMP"/>  Hereupon spake <name>Faustus</name>: Get thee hence from me, and take <seg id="n15">Saint
<name>Valentines</name> farewell &amp; <name>Crisam</name> with thee</seg><note target="n15" anchored="yes">'Saint Valentines farewell &amp; Crisam with thee' is about equivalent to 'a pest upon you.'  Logeman, <name>English Faustbook of 159</name>2, p. 137, gives a discussion of the derivation of the phrase.</note>, yet I coniure thee
that thou be here at euening, and bethinke thy selfe on that I haue asked thee,
and aske thy Princes counsel therein. <name>Mephostophiles</name> the Spirit, thus
answered, vanished away, leauing <name>Faustus</name> in his study, where he sate
pondering with himselfe how he might obtaine his request of the diuel without
losse of his soule: yet fully he was resolued in himselfe, rather than to want
his pleasure, to doe whatsoeuer the Spirit and his Lord should condition
vpon.

<!-- <link targets="chap3 aa3 bb3"> -->
</p>
</div2>
<div2 n="4" type="chapter" id="chap4">
<head><hi rend="ital">The second time of the Spirits appearing to Faustus in his house, and of their parley.</hi> Chap. 4.</head>
<p><name>FAustus</name> continuing in his diuelish cogitations, neuer mouing out of the
place where the Spirit left him (such was his feruent loue to the diuel) the
night approching, this swift flying Spirit appeared to <name>Faustus</name>, offering
himself with al submissi&ocirc; to his seruice, with ful authority from his
Prince to doe whatsoeuer he would request, if so be <name>Faustus</name> would
promise to be his: this answere I bring thee, and an answere must thou make by
me againe, yet will I heare what is thy desire, because thou hast sworne me to
be here at this time.  Doctor <name>Faustus</name> gaue him this answere, though
faintly (for his soules sake) That his request was none other but to become a
Diuel, or at the least a limme of him, and that the Spirit should agree vnto
these Articles as followeth.
<list type="ordered">
<label>1</label><item>That he might be a Spirite in shape and qualitie.</item>
<label>2</label><item>That <name>Mephostophiles</name> should be his seruant, and at his commandement.</item>
<label>3</label><item>That <name>Mephostophiles</name> should bring him any thing, and doo for him
whatsoeuer.</item>
<label>4</label><item>That at all times he should be in his house, inuisible to all men, except
onely to himselfe, and at his commandement to shew himselfe.</item>
<label>5</label><item>Lastly, that <name>Mephostophiles</name> should at all times appeare
at his command, in what forme or shape soeuer he would.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Vpon these poynts the Spirit answered Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, that</p><p>all this should be granted him and fulfilled, and more if he would agree vnto
him vpon certaine Articles as followeth.</p><p>First, that Doctor <name>Faustus</name> should giue himselfe to his Lord <name>Lucifer</name>,
body and soule.</p><p>Secondly, for confirmation of the same, he should make him a wri- <milestone n="6" unit="BMP"/>
ting, written with his owne blood.</p><p>Thirdly, that he would be an enemie to all Christian people.</p><p>Fourthly, that he would denie his Christian beleefe.</p><p>Fiftly, that he let not any man change his opinion, if so bee any man should
goe about to disswade, or withdraw him from it.</p><p>Further, the spirit promised <name>Faustus</name> to giue him certaine yeares to liue
in health and pleasure, and when such yeares were expired, that then <name>Faustus</name>
should be fetched away, and if he should holde these Articles and
conditions, that then he should haue all whatsoeuer his heart would wish or
desire; and that <name>Faustus</name> should quickly perceiue himself to be a Spirit
in all maner of actions whatsoeuer.  Hereupon Doctor <name>Faustus</name> his minde
was so inflamed, that he forgot his soule, and promised <name>Mephostophiles</name>
to hold all things as hee had mentioned them: he thought the diuel was not
so black as they vse to paynt him, nor hell so hote as the people say,
&amp;c.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="5" type="chapter" id="chap5">
<head><hi rend="ital">The third parley between Doctor Faustus and Mephostophiles about a conclusion.</hi> Chap. 5.</head>
<p>AFter Doctor <name>Faustus</name> had made his promise to the diuell, in the morning
betimes he called the Spirit before him and commaunded him that he should
alwayes come to him like a Fryer, after the order of Saint <name>Francis</name>, with
a bell in his hande like Saint <name>Anthonie</name>, and to ring it once or twise
before he appeared, that he might know of his certaine comming:</p><p>Then <name>Faustus</name> demaunded the Spirit, what was his name? The Spirit
answered, my name is as thou sayest, <name>Mephostophiles</name>, and I am a prince,
but seruant to <name>Lucifer</name>: and all the circuit from <name>Septentrio</name> to
the <name>Meridian</name>, I rule vnder him. Euen at these words was this wicked
wretch <name>Faustus</name> inflamed, to heare himselfe to haue gotten so great a
Potentate to be his seruant, forgot the Lord his maker, and Christ his
redeemer, became an enemy vnto all man-kinde, yea, worse than the Gyants whom
the Poets fayne to climb the hilles to make warre with the Gods: not vnlike
that enemy of God and his Christ, that for his pride was cast into hell: so
likewise <name>Faustus</name> forgot that the high climbers catch the greatest
falles, and that the sweetest meate requires the sowrest sawce.</p><p>		After a while, <name>Faustus</name> promised <name>Mephostophiles</name> to write and
make his Obligation, with full assurance of the Articles in the Chapter before
rehearsed.  A pitifull case, (Christian Reader,) for certainly this Letter or
Obligation was found in his house after his most lamen- <milestone n="7" unit="BMP"/> table end,
with all the rest of his damnable practises vsed in his whole life. Therefore I
wish al Christians to take an example by this wicked <name>Faustus</name>, and to be
comforted in Christ, contenting themselues with that vocation whereunto it hath
pleased God to call them, and not to esteeme the vaine delights of this life,
as did this vnhappie <name>Faustus</name>, in giuing his Soule to the Diuell: &amp;
to confirme it the more assuredly, he tooke a small penknife, and prickt a
vaine in his left hand, &amp; for certaintie therevpon, were seene on his hand
these words written, as if they had been written with blood, <foreign lang="la">o homo
fuge</foreign>: whereat the Spirit vanished, but <name>Faustus</name> continued in his
damnable minde, &amp; made his writing as followeth.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="6" type="chapter" id="chap6">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus set his blood in a saucer on warme  ashes, and writ as followeth.</hi> Chap. 6</head>
<p>I <name>Iohannes Faustus</name>, Doctor, doe openly acknowledge with mine ownehand,
to the greater force and strengthning of this Letter, that siththence I began
to studie and speculate the course and order of the Elements, I haue not found
through the gift that is giuen mee from aboue, any such learning and wisdome,
that can bring mee to my desires: and for that I find, that men are vnable to
instruct me any farther in the matter, now haue I Doctor <name>John Faustus</name>,
vnto the hellish prince of Orient and his messenger <name>Mephostophiles</name>,
giuen both bodie &amp; soule, vpon such condition, that they shall learne
me, and fulfill my desire in all things, as they haue promised and vowed vnto
me, with due obedience vnto me, according vnto the Articles mentioned betweene
vs.</p><p>	Further, I couenant and grant with them by these presents, that at the end of 24. yeares next ensuing the date of this present Letter, they being expired,
and I in the meane time, during the said yeares be serued of them at my wil,
they accomplishing my desires to the full in al points as we are agreed, that
then I giue them full power to doe with mee at their pleasure, to rule, to
send, fetch, or carrie me or mine, be it either body, soule, flesh, blood, or
goods, into their habitation, be it wheresoeuer: and herevpon, I defie God and
his Christ, all the hoast of heauen, and all liuing creatures that beare the
shape of God, yea all that liues; and againe I say it, and it shall be so.  And
to the more strengthning of this writing, I haue written it with mine owne hand
and blood, being in perfect memory, and herevpon I subscribe to it with my name
and title, calling all the infernall, middle, and supreme powers to witnesse of
this my Letter and subscription.</p>
<p rend="right">
<!-- This entire chapter is a letter.  How do we indicate that and end it with a salutation. -->
<name>Iohn Faustus</name>, <term id="n16">approued in the Elements</term><note target="n16" type="gloss" anchored="yes">proved or tested in the elements</note>,
and the spirituall Doctor.
<!-- <link targets="chap4 chap5 chap6 chap7" id="c4"> -->
<!-- <link targets="c4 aa4 bb4"> -->

<milestone n="8" unit="BMP"/></p></div2>
<div2 n="7" type="chapter" id="chap7">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Mephostophiles came for his writing, and in what maner hee appeared, and his sights he shewed him: and how he caused him to keep a copie  of his owne writing.</hi> Chap. 7.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> sitting <seg id="n17">pensiue</seg><note target="n17" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'pensine.'</note>, hauing but one onely boy with him,
sodainely there appeared his Spirite <name>Mephostophiles</name>, in likenes of a
fierie man, from whome issued most horrible fierie flames, in so much that the
boy was afraide, but being hardned by his master, he bad him stand still and he
should haue no harme: the Spirit began to blare as in a singing manner.  This
pretie sport pleased Doctor <name>Faustus</name> well, but hee would not call his
Spirit into his Counting house, vntill bee had seene more: anon was heard a
rushing of armed men, and trampling of horsses: this ceasing, came a kennell
of hounds, and they chased a great Hart in the hall, and there the Hart was
slaine. <name>Faustus</name> tooke heart, came forth, and looked vpon the Hart, hut
presenfly before him there was a

Lyon and a Dragon together fighting, so fiercely, that <name>Faustus</name> thought
they would haue brought downe the house, but the Dragon ouercame the Lyon, and
so they vanished.</p><p>	After this, came in a Peacock, with a Peahen, the cocke <term id="n18">brusling of his
tayle</term><note target="n18" type="gloss" anchored="yes">erecting his tail stiffly</note>, and turning to the female, beate her, and so vanished.  Afterward
followed a furious Bull, that with a full fiercenes ran vpon <name>Faustus</name>,
but comming neare him, vanished away.  Afterward followed a great old Ape,
this Ape offered <name>Faustus</name> the hand, but he refused: so the Ape ran out
of the hal againe.  Herevpon fell a mist in the hal, that <name>Faustus</name> saw no
light, but it lasted not, and so soone as it was gone, there lay before
<name>Faustus</name> two great sacks, one full of gold, the other full of siluer.</p><p>Lastly, was heard by <name>Faustus</name> all maner Instruments of musick, as Organs,
<term id="n19">Clarigolds</term><note target="n19" type="gloss" anchored="yes">A corruption of clarichord, a spinet-like instrument.</note>, Lutes, Viols, <term id="n20">Citerns</term><note target="n20" type="gloss" anchored="yes">A wire-strung instrument of the guitar type.</note>, <term id="n21">Waights</term><note target="n21" type="gloss" anchored="yes">oboes</note>, Hornepipes, Fluites,
<seg id="n22">Anomes</seg><note target="n22" anchored="yes">we can find no trace of this instrument.  It is possibly a misprint.</note>, Harpes, and all maner of other Instruments, the which so rauished his
minde, that hee thought hee had been in another world, forgat both body and
soule, in so much that he was minded neuer to change his opinion concerning
that which he had done. Hereat, came <name>Mephostophiles</name> into the Hall to
<name>Faustus</name>, in apparell like vnto a Frier, to whome <name>Faustus</name> spake,
thou hast done mee a wonderfull pleasure in shewing mee this pastime, if thou
continue as thou hast begun, <seg id="n23">thou</seg> <note target="n23" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'thon.'</note> shalt win my heart and soule, yea and haue
it. <name>Mephostophiles</name> answered, this is nothing, I will please thee better
: yet that thou maist know my power and all, aske what thou wilt request of
mee, that shalt thou haue, conditionally hold thy promise, and giue me thy
hand-writing: at <milestone n="9" unit="BMP"/> which words, the wretch thrust forth his hand,
saying, hold thee, there hast thou my promise: <name>Mephostophiles</name> tooke the
writing, and willing <name>Faustus</name> to take a copie of it, with that the
peruerse <name>Faustus</name> being resolute in his damnation, wrote a copie thereof,
and gaue the Diuell the one, and kept in store

the other.  Thus the Spirit and <name>Faustus</name> were agreed, &amp; dwelt
together: no doubt there was a vertuous housekeeping.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="8" type="chapter" id="chap8">
<head><hi rend="ital">The manner how Faustus proceeded with his damnable life, and of the diligent seruice that Mephostophiles vsed towards him.</hi> Chap. 8.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> hauing giuen his soule to the diuell, renouncing all the
powers of heauen, confirming this lamentable action with his owne blood, and
hauing alreadie deliuered his writing <seg id="n24">not</seg><note target="n24" anchored="yes">A later undated edition in our possession has 'now.'  Logeman suggests 'written note' for 'writing not.'</note> into the diuels hand, the which so
puffed vp his heart, that hee had forgot the minde of a man, and thought rather
himselfe to bee a spirit.  This <name>Faustus</name> dwelt in his Vnckles house at
<name>Wirtenherg</name>, who dyed, and bequethed it in his Testament to his Cousin
<name>Faustus</name>. 

<seg id="c5">
<name>Faustus</name> kept a boy with him that was his scholler, an vnhappie
wagge, called <name>Christopher Wagner</name>, to whome this sporte and life that hee
saw his master follow seemed pleasant. <name>Faustus</name> loued the boy well,
hoping to make him as good or better seene in his diuelish exercise than
himselfe; and hee was fellow with <name>Mephostophiles</name>: otherwise <name>Faustus</name>
had no more companie in his house; but himselfe, his boy and his Spirit,
that euer was diligent at <name>Faustus</name> commaund, going about the house,
clothed like a Frier, with a little bell in his hand, seene of none but
<name>Faustus</name>.</seg>
<!-- <link targets="c5 aa5 bb5"> -->

For his victuall and other necessaries, <name>Mephostophiles</name>
brought him at his pleasure from the Duke of <name>Saxon</name>, the Duke of
<name>Bauaria</name>, and the Bishop of <name>Saltzhurg</name>: for they had many times
their best wine stolne out of their cellers by <name>Mephostophiles</name>: Likewise
their prouision for their owne table, such meate as <name>Faustus</name> wished for,
his spirite brought him in: besides that, <name>Faustus</name> himselfe was become
so cunning, that when he opened his windowe, what foule soeuer he wished for,
it came presently flying into his house, were it neuer so daintie.  Moreouer,
<name>Faustus</name> and his boy went in sumptuous apparrell, the which
<name>Mephostophiles</name> stole from the Mercers at <name>Norenberg</name>, <name>Auspurg</name>,
<name>Franckeford</name>, and <name>Liptzig</name>: for it was hard for them to find a lock
to keep out such a theefe.  All their maintenance was but stolne &amp; borrowed
ware: and thus

they liued an odious life in the sight of God, though as yet ye world were
vnacquainted with their wickednes.  It must be so, for their fruites be none
other: as Christ saith through <name>John</name>, where hee cals the diuell a
theefe, <milestone n="10" unit="BMP"/> and a murderer: and that found <name>Faustus</name>, for hee stole
him away both bodie and soule.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="9" type="chapter" id="chap9">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus would haue married, and how the Diuell had almost killed him for it.</hi> Chap. 9.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> continued thus in his Epicurish life day &amp; night, and
beleeued not that there was a God, hell, or diuel:</p><p>he thought that bodie and soule died together, and had quite forgotten
Diuinitie or the immortalitie of his soule, but stoode in his damnable heresie
day and night.  And bethinking himselfe of a wife, called <name>Mephostophiles</name>
to counsaile; which would in no wise agree: demanding of him if he would
breake the couenant made with him, or if hee had forgot it.  Hast not thou
(quoth <name>Mephostophiles</name>) sworne thy selfe an enemy to God and all
creatures': To this I answere thee, thou canst not marry; thou canst not serue
two masters, God, and my Prince: for wedlock is a chiefe institution ordained
of God, and that hast thou promised to defie, as we doe all, and that hast thou
also done: and moreouer thou hast confirmed it with thy blood: perswade thy
selfe, that what thou doost in contempt of wedlock, it is all to thine owne
delight.  Therefore <name>Faustus</name>, looke well about thee, and bethinke thy
selfe better, and I wish thee to change thy minde: for if thou keepe not what
thou hast promised in thy writing, we wil teare thee in peeces like the dust
vnder thy feete.  Therefore sweete <name>Faustus</name>, thinke with what vnquiet
life, anger, strife, &amp; debate thou shalt liue in when thou takest a wife:
therefore change thy minde.</p><p>Doctor <name>Faustus</name> was with these speeches in despaire: and as all that
haue forsaken the Lord, can build vpon no good foundation: so this wreched
<name>Faustus</name> hauing forsooke the rock, fell in despaire with himself, fearing
if he should <term id="n25">motion</term><note target="n25" type="gloss" anchored="yes">propose</note> Matrimonie any more, that the diuell would teare him in
peeces  For this time (quoth he to <name>Mephostophiles</name>)</p><p>
I am not minded to marry.  Then you doe well, answered his spirite.  But
shortly &amp; that <seg id="n26">within</seg> <note target="n26" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'wihtin.'</note> two houres after, <name>Faustus</name> called his spirit,
which came in his old maner like a Frier.  Then <name>Faustus</name> said vnto him, I
am not able to resist nor bridle my fantasie, I must and will haue a wife, and
I pray thee giue thy consent to it.  Sodainlie vpon these words came such a
whirle-winde about the place, that <name>Faustus</name> thought the whole house would
come down, all the doores in the house flew off the hookes: after all this,
his house was full of smoke, and the floore couered ouer with ashes: which
when Doctor <name>Faustus</name> perceiued, he would haue gone Vp the staires: and
flying Vp, he was taken and throwne into the hall, <milestone n="11" unit="BMP"/> that he was not
able to stir hand nor foote: then round about him ran a monstrous circle of
fire, neuer standing still, that <name>Faustus</name> fried as hee lay, and thought
there to haue been burned.  Then cried hee out to his Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name>
for help, promising him hee would liue in all things as he had vowed in his
hand-writing.  Hereupon appeared vnto him an ougly Diuell, so fearefull and
monstrous to beholde, that <name>Faustus</name> durst not looke on him.  The Diuell
said, what wouldst thou haue <name>Faustus</name>: how likest thou thy wedding? what
minde art thou in now': <name>Faustus</name> answered, he had forgot his promise,
desiring him of pardon, and he would talke no more of such things.  The diuell
answered, thou were best so to doe, and so vanished.</p><p>	After appeared vnto him his Frier <name>Mephostophiles</name> with a bel in his
hand, and spake to <name>Faustus</name>: It is no iesting with vs, holde thou that
which thou hast vowed, and wee will performe as wee haue promised: and more
than that, thou shalt haue thy hearts desire of what woman soeuer thou wilt,
bee shee aliue or dead, and so long as thou wilt, thou shalt keepe her by
thee.</p><p>These words pleased <name>Faustus</name> <seg id="n27">wonderfull</seg><note target="n27" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'wonderfnll.'</note> well, and repented himselfe that
hee was so foolish to wish himselfe married, that might haue any woman in the
whole Citie brought to him at his command; the which he practised and
perseuered in a long time.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<!-- <link targets="chap9 aa6 bb6"> -->

<div2 n="10" type="chapter" id="chap10">
<head><hi rend="ital">Questions put foorth by Doctor Faustus vnto his Spirite Mephostophiles.</hi> Chap. 10.</head>
<p>
<seg id="c7">DOctor <name>Faustus</name> liuing in all manner of pleasure that his heart could
desire, continuing in his amorous drifts, his delicate fare, and costly
apparel, called on a time his <name>Mephostophilies</name> to him: which being come,
brought with him a booke in his hand of all maner of diuelish and inchanted
artes, the which he gaue <name>Faustus</name>, saying: hold my <name>Faustus</name>, worke
now thy hearts desire:</seg>

<seg id="c15">The copie of this inchanting booke was afterward found
by his seruant <name>Christopher Wagner</name>.
</seg>
<!-- <link targets="c15 aa16 bb17 bb18"> -->

Wel (quoth <name>Faustus</name> to his
spirit) I haue called thee to know what thou canst doe if I haue neede of thy
help.  Then answered <name>Mephostophiles</name> and said, my Lord <name>Faustus</name>, I
am a flying spirit: yea, so swift as thought can think, to do whatsoeuer.
Here <name>Faustus</name> said: but how came thy Lord and master <name>Lucifer</name> to
haue so great a fal fro heaue': <name>Mephostophiles</name> answered: My Lord
<name>Lucifer</name> was a faire Angell, created of God as immortal, and being placed
in the Seraphins, which are aboue the <seg id="n28">Cherubins</seg><note target="n28" anchored="yes">According to the medieval conception, there were nine orders of heavenly beings, of which the Seraphim were the highest and the Cherubim second.</note>, hee would haue presumed vnto
the Throne of God, with intent to haue <milestone n="12" unit="BMP"/> thrust God out of his seate.
Vpon this presumption the Lord cast him downe headlong, and where before he was
an Angel of light, now dwels hee in darkenes, not able to come neere his first
place, without God send for him to appeare before him as <seg id="n29"><name>Raphael</name></seg><note target="n29" anchored="yes">According to Spies, Lucifer, before his fall, was an archangel and was named Raphael.</note>: but
vnto the lower degree of Angells that haue their conuersation with men hee was
come, but not vnto the second degree of Heauens that is kept by the
Archangells, namely, <name>Michael</name> and <name>Gabriel</name>, for these are called
Angels of Gods wonders: yet are these farre inferiour places to that from
whence my Lord and Master <name>Lucifer</name> fell.  And thus farre <name>Faustus</name>,
because thou art one of the beloued children of my Lord <name>Lucifer</name>,
following and feeding thy minde in maner as he did his, I haue shortly
resolued thy request, and more I will doe for thee at thy pleasure.  I thanke
thee <name>Mephostophiles</name> (quoth <name>Faustus</name>)

come let vs now goe rest, for it is night: vpon this they left their
communication.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="11" type="chapter" id="chap11">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus dreamed that hee had seene hell in his sleepe, and how he questioned with his Spirit of matters as concerning hell, with the Spirits answer.</hi> Chap. 11.</head>
<p>THe night following, after <name>Faustus</name> his communication had with
<name>Mephostophiles</name>, as concerning the fal of <name>Lucifer</name>, Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> dreamed that he had seene a part of hell: but in what maner it
was, or in what place he knew not: whereupon he was greatly troubled in minde,
and called vnto him <name>Mephostophiles</name> his spirit, saying to him, my
<name>Mephostophiles</name>, I pray thee resolue me in this doubt: what is hell,
what substance is it of, in what place stands it, and when was it made':
<name>Mephostophiles</name> answered: my <name>Faustus</name>, thou shalt knowe, that
before the fall of my Lord <name>Lucifer</name> there was no hell, but euen then was
hell ordained: it is of no substance, but a confused thing: for I tell thee,
that before al Elements were made, and the earth seene, the Spirit of God moued
on the waters, and darkenes was ouer all: but when God said, let it bee light,
it was so at his word, and the light was on Gods right hand, and God praised
the light.  Iudge thou further:</p><p>God stood in the middle, the darkenes was on his left hand, in the which my
Lorde was bound in chaines vntill the day of iudgement: in this confused hell
is nought to finde but a filthie, Sulphurish, firie, stinking mist or fog.
Further wee Diuels know not what substance it is of, but a confused thing.  For
as a bubble of water flieth before the wind, so doth hell before the breath of
God.  Further, we Diuels know not how God hath <milestone n="13" unit="BMP"/> laid the foundation of
our hell, nor whereof it is: but to bee short with thee <name>Faustus</name>, we
know that hell hath neither bottome nor end.</p><p></p>
</div2>

<!-- <link targets="chap11 aa8 bb8"> --> 

<div2 n="12" type="chapter" id="chap12">
<head><hi rend="ital">The second question put foorth by Doctor Faustus to his Spirite, what Kingdomes there were in hell, how many, and what were their rulers names.</hi> Chap. 12.</head>
<p>
<name>Faustus</name> spake againe to <name>Mephostophiles</name>, saying: thou speakest of
wonderfull things, I pray thee now tell mee what Kingdomes is there in your
hell, how many are there, what are they called, and who rules them: the
Spirite answered him: my <name>Faustus</name>, knowe that hell is as thou wouldst
thinke with thy selfe another world, in the which wee haue our being, vnder the
earth, and aboue the earth, euen to the Heauens; within the circumference
whereof are contained ten Kingdomes, namely:
<!-- I have no idea ag this.  See page 150 in Faust Books.-->
<table>
<row role="data"><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">1</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Lacus mortis</name>.</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">6</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Gehenna</name>.</cell></row>
<row role="data"><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">2</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Stagnum ignis</name>.</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">7</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Herebus</name>.</cell></row>
<row role="data"><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">3</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Terra tenebrosa</name>.</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">8</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Barathrum</name>.</cell></row>
<row role="data"><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">4</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Tartarus</name>.</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">9</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Styx</name>.</cell></row>
<row role="data"><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">5</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Terra obliuionis</name>.</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1">10</cell><cell role="data" cols="1" rows="1"><name>Acheron</name>.</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The which Kingdomes are gouerned by flue kings, that is, <name>Lucifer</name>
in the <name>Orient</name>, <name>Beelzebub</name> in <name>Septentrio, Belial</name> in <name>Meridie</name>,
<name>Astaroth</name> in <name>Occidente</name>, and <seg id="n30"><name>Phlegeton</name></seg><note target="n30" anchored="yes">'Phlegeton,' used here as the name of a king, is usually the name of a mythical river in the underworld.</note>
 in the middest of them
all: whose rule and dominions haue none end vntill the day of Dome.  And thus
farre <name>Faustus</name>, hast thou heard of our rule and kingdomes.</p><p></p>
</div2>

<div2 n="13" type="chapter" id="chap13">
<head><hi rend="ital">Another question put foorth by Doctor Faustus to his Spirite concerning his Lorde Lucifer, with the sorrow that Faustus fell afterwards into.</hi> Chap. 13.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> began againe to reason with <name>Mephostophiles</name>,
requiring him to tell him in what forme and shape, &amp; in what estimation
his Lord <name>Lucifer</name> was when he was in fauour with God.  Whereupon his
spirit required him of three daies respite, which <name>Faustus</name> granted.  The 3. daies being expired, <name>Mephostophiles</name> gaue him this answer:
<name>Faustus</name>, my Lord <name>Lucifer</name>, (so called now, for that he was
banished out of the cleare light of Heauen) was at the first an Angell of God,
he <term id="n31">sate on</term> <note target="n31" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Probably, 'had a place above.' According to N. E. D. a frequent expression for the Divine Being was: he sitteth or dwelleth between (or on) the Cherubim.</note> the Cherubins, and sawe all the wonderfull works of God, yea he
was so of God ordained, for shape, pompe, authority, worthines, &amp; dwelling,
that he far

exceeded all other the creatures of God, <milestone n="14" unit="BMP"/> yea our gold and precious
stones: and so illuminated, that he farre surpassed the brightnes of the Sunne
and all other Starres: wherefore God placed him on the Cherubins, where he had
a kinglie office, and was alwaies before Gods seate, to the end hee might hee
the more perfect in all his beings: but when hee began to be high minded,
proude, and so presumptuous that hee would vsurpe the seate of his Maiestie,
then was he banished out from amongst the heauenly powers, separated from their
abiding into the manner of a fierie stone, that no water is able to quench, but
continually burneth vntill the ende of the world.</p><p>

<seg id="c9">	Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, when he had heard the words of his spirit, began to
consider with himselfe, hauing diuerse and sundrie opinions in his head: and
very pensiuely (saying nothing<seg id="n32">)</seg> <note target="n32" anchored="yes">This second parenthesis mark evidently should come after 'Spirit.'</note> vnto his Spirit, hee went into his chamber,
and laid him on his bed, recording the words of <name>Mephostophiles</name>; which so
pearced his heart, that hee fell into sighing and great lamentation, crying out
: alas, ah, wo is me! what haue I done': Euen so shall it come to passe with
me: am not I also a creature of Gods making, bearing his owne Image and
similitude, into whom he hath breathed the Spirite of life and immortalitie,
vnto whome hee hath made all things liuing subiect: but woe is me, mine hautie
minde, proud aspyring stomack, and filthie flesh, hath brought my soule into
perpetuall damnation; yea, pride hath abused my vnderstanding, in so much that
I haue forgot my maker, the Spirit of God is departed from mee  I haue promised
the Diuell my Soule: and therefore it is but a folly for me to hope for grace,
but it must bee euen with mee as with <name>Lucifer</name>, throwne into perpetuall
burning fire: ah, woe is mee that euer I was borne. In this perplexitie lay
this miserable Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, hauing quite forgot his faith in Christ,
neuer falling to repentance truly, thereby to attaine the grace &amp; holy
Spirit of God againe, the which would haue been able to haue resisted the
strong assaults of Sathan: For although hee had made him a promise, yet hee
might haue remembred throught true repentance sinners come againe into the
fauour of God; which faith the faithfull firmely holde, knowing they that kill
the bodie, are

not able to hurt the soule: but he was in all his opinions doubtfull, without
faith or hope, and so he continued.</seg></p>
</div2>
<div2 n="14" type="chapter" id="chap14">
<head><hi rend="ital">Another disputation betwixt Doctor Faustus and his Spirite, of the power of the Diuell, and of his enuie to mankinde.</hi> Chap. 14.</head>
<p>AFter Doctor <name>Faustus</name> had a while pondered and sorrowed with himselfe of
his wretched estate, hee called againe <name>Mephostophiles</name> <milestone n="15" unit="BMP"/> vnto
him, commaunding him to tell him the iudgement, rule, power, attempts, tyranny
and temptation of the Diuell, &amp; why he was moued to such kinde of liuing:
whereupon the spirit answered, this question that thou demandest of me, will
turne thee to no small discontentment: therefore thou shouldst not haue desired
me of such matters, for it toucheth the secrets of our kingdome, although I
cannot denie to resolue thy request.  Therefore know thou <name>Faustus</name>, that
so soone as my Lorde <name>Lucifer</name> fell from heauen, he became a mortall
enemie both to God and man, and hath vsed (as now he doth) all manner of
tyranny to the destruction of man, as is manifest by diuers examples, one
falling sodainly dead, another hangs himselfe, another drownes himselfe, others
stabbe themselues, others vnfaithfully despayre, and so come to vtter
confusion: the first man <name>Adam</name> that was made perfect to the similitude of
God, was by my Lord his pollicie, the whole decay of man: yea, <name>Faustus</name>,
in him was the beginning and first tyranny of my Lord <name>Lucifer</name> vsed
to man: the like did he with <name>Cain</name>, the same with the children of
<name>Israel</name>, when they worshipped strange Gods, and fell to whoredome with
strange women: the like with <name>Saul</name>: so did he by the seuen husbands of
her that after was the wife of <name>Tobias</name>: likewise <name>Dagon</name> our fellow
brought to destruction 30000. men, whereupon the Arke of God was stolen: and
<name>Belial</name> made <name>Dauid</name> to number his men, whereupon were slaine 60000
also hee deceiued King <name>Salomon</name> that worshipped the Gods of the heathen:
and there are such Spirits <seg id="n33">innumerable</seg> <note target="n33" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'innmerable.'</note> that can come by men and tempt them,
driue them to sinne, weaken their beliefe: for we rule the hearts of Kings and
Princes, stirring them vp to warre and blood-shed; and to this intent doe wee
spread our selues

throughout all the world, as the vtter enemies of God and his Son [n]e Christ,
yea &amp; all those that worship them  and that thou knowest by thy selfe
<name>Faustus</name>, how we haue dealt with thee.  To this answered Faustus, why
then thou didst also beguile me.  Yea (quoth <name>Mephostophiles</name>) why should
not we help thee forwards: for so soone as we saw thy heart, how thou didst
despise thy degree taken in Diuinitie and didst study to search and know the
secrets of our kingdome; euen then did we enter into thee, giuing thee diuers
foule and filthy cogitations, pricking thee forward in thine intent and
perswading thee that thou couldst neuer attaine to thy desire, vntill thou hast
the help of some diuell: and when thou wast delighted with this, then tooke we
roote in thee &amp; so firmely, that thou gauest thy selfe vnto vs, both body
and soule the which thou (<name>Faustus</name>) canst not denie. Hereat answered
<name>Faustus</name>, Thou sayest true <name>Mephostophiles</name>, <milestone n="18" unit="BMP"/> I cannot
denie it: Ah, woe is me miserable <name>Faustus</name> how haue I beene deceiued':
had not I desired to know so' much, I had not been in this case: for hauing
studied the hues of the holy Saints and Prophets, &amp; therby thought my self
to vnderstand sufficient in heauenly matters, I thought my self not worthy to
be called doctor <name>Faustus</name>, if I should not also know the secrets of hell,
&amp; be associated with the furious Fiend thereof; now therefore must I be
rewarded accordingly.  Which speeches being vttered, <name>Faustus</name> went very
sorrowfully away from <name>Mephostophiles</name>.

<!-- <link targets="c9 chap14" id="xx9"> -->
<!-- <link targets="xx9 aa9 bb9 aa10 bb10"> -->
</p>
</div2>
<div2 n="15" type="chapter" id="chap15">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus desired againe of his Spirit to know the secrets and paines of hell; and whether those damned Diuels and their company might euer come into the fauour of God againe or not?</hi> Chap. 15.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> was euer pondering with himselfe how he might get loose
from so damnable an end as he had giuen himself vnto, both of body and soule:
but his repentance was like to that of <name>Cain</name> and <name>Iudas</name>, he thought
his sinnes greater then God could forgiue, hereupon rested his minde he looked
vp to heauen, but sawe nothing therein; for his heart was so possessed with the
Diuel, that hee could thinke of nought els but of hell, and the paynes thereof.
Wherefore in all the hast he calleth vnto him his Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name>,
desiring him to tell him some more of the secrets of hell, what paines the
damned were in, and how they were tormented, and whether the damned soules
might get againe the fauour of God, and so bee released out of their torments
or not: whereupon the Spirit answered, my <name>Faustus</name>, thou mayst wel leaue
to question any more of such matters, for they wil but disquiet thy mind, I
pray thee what meanest thou': thinkest thou through these thy fantasies to
escape vs? No, for if thou shouldest climb vp to heauen, there to hide thy
selfe, yet would I thrust thee downe agayne; for thou art mine, and thou
belongest vnto our society: therefore sweete <name>Faustus</name>, thou wilt repent
this thy foolish demaund, except thou be content that I shall tell thee
nothing.  Quoth <name>Faustus</name> ragingly, I will know, or I will not hue,
wherefore dispatch and tell me: to whom <name>Mephostophiles</name> answered,
<name>Faustus</name>, it is no trouble vnto mee at all to tell thee, and therefore
sith thou forcest mee thereto, I will tell thee things to the terror of thy
soule, if thou wilt abide the hearing. Thou wilt haue me tel thee of the
secrets of hell, and of the paynes thereof: know <name>Faustus</name>, that hell hath
many figures, semblances, and names, but it cannot be named nor figured in such
sort vnto the liuing that are damned, as it is vnto those that are dead, and
doe both see and feele the <milestone n="19" unit="BMP"/> torments thereof: for hell is sayd to bee
deadly, out of the which came neuer any to life agayne but one, but he is as
nothing for thee to reckon vpon, hell is blood-thirstie, and is neuer
satisfied: hell is a valley, into the which the damned soules fal: for so soon
as the soule is out of mans body, it would gladly goe to the place from whence
it came, and climbeth vp aboue the highest hils, euen to the heauens; where
being by the Angels of <seg id="n34">the first <name>Mobile</name></seg><note target="n34" type="gloss" anchored="yes">the outermost of the nine or ten spheres, which, according to the Ptolemaic system, were supposed to revolve around the earth from east to west, accounting for the diurnal revolution of the heavens.  Here used in the Aristotelian sense, i.e., the physical system next to God, the unmoved mover.</note> denied <seg id="n35">entertainement</seg> <note target="n35" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'eutertainement.'</note> (in
consideration of their euill life spent on the earth) they fall into the
deepest pit or valley which hath no bottome, into a perpetuall fire, which
shall neuer bee quenched: for like

as the Flint throwne into the water, looseth not his vertue, neither is his
fire extinguished; euen so the hellish fire is vnquenchable: and euen as the
Flint stone in the fire being burned is red hot, and yet consumeth not: so
likewise the damned soules in our hellish fire are euer burning, but their
paines neuer dimin[i]shing.  Therefore is hel called the euerlasting pain, in
which is neither hope nor mercy: So is it called vtter darknesse, in which we
see neither the light of Sunne, Moone, nor Starre: and were our darkenesse
like the darknes of the night, yet were there hope of mercie, but ours is
perpetuall darkenesse, deane exempt from the face of God. Hell hath also a
place within it called <name>Chasma</name>, out of the which issueth all manner of
thunders, lightnings, with such horrible shrikings and waylings, that ofttimes
the very diuels themselues stand in feare thereof: for one while it sendeth
foorth windes with exceeding snow, hayle, and raine congealing the water into
yce; with the which the damned are frozen, gnash their teeth, howle and cry,
and yet cannot die. Otherwhiles, it sendeth foorth most horrible hote mists or
fogges, with flashing flames of fire and brimstone, wherein the sorrowfull
soules of the damned lie broyling in their reiterated torments: yea
<name>Faustus</name>, hell is called a prison wherein the damned lie continually
bound; it is also called <name>Pernicies</name>, and <name>Exitium</name>, death,
destruction, hurtfulnesse, mischiefe, a mischance, a pitifull and an euill
thing worlde without end. We haue also with vs in hell a ladder, reaching of an
exceeding height, as though it would touch the heauens, on which the damned
ascend to seeke the blessing of God; but through their infidelitie, when they
are at the very highest degree, they fall downe againe into their former
miseries, complaynmg of the heate of that vnquenchable fire: yea sweete
<name>Faustus</name>, so must thou vnderstand of hell, the while thou art so desirous
to know the secrets of our kingdome.  And marke <name>Faustus</name>, hell is the
nurse of death, the heate of all fire, the shadow of heauen and earth, the
obliuion of all goodnes, the paynes vnspeakeable, the griefes vnremoueable, the
dwelling of <milestone n="18" unit="BMP"/> Diuels, Dragons, Serpents, Adders, Toades, Crocodils, and
all maner of venymous creatures, the puddle of sinne, the stinking fogge
ascending from the Stigian lake, Brimstone, Pitch, and all maner of vncleane
mettals, the perpetual and vnquenchable fire, the end of whose miseries was
neuer purposed by God: yea, yea <name>Faustus</name>, thou sayst, I shall, I must,
nay I will tell thee the secrets of our kingdome, for thou buyest it dearely,
and thou <seg id="n36">must</seg> <note target="n36" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'mnst.'</note> and shalt be partaker of our torments, that (as the Lord God
sayd) neuer shall cease: for hell, the womans belly, and the earth are neuer
satisfied; there shalt thou abide horrible torments, trembling, gnashing of
teeth, howling, crying, burning, freezing, melting, swimming in a labyrinth of
miseries, scalding, burning, smoking in thine eyes, stinking in thy nose,
horsenes of thy speech, deaffenesse of thine eares, trembling of thy handes,
biting thine owne tongue with payne, thy hart crushed as in a presse, thy bones
broken, the diuels tossing fire brands vpon thee, yea thy whole carkasse tossed
vpon muckforkes from one diuel to another, yea <name>Faustus</name>, then wilt thou
wish for death, and he will flie from thee, thine vnspeakable torments shall be
euery day augmented more and more, for the greater the sinne, the greater is
the punishment: howe likest thou this, my <name>Faustus</name>, a resolution
answerable to thy request?</p><p>	Lastly, thou wilt haue mee tell thee that which belongeth onely to God, which
is, if it be possible for the damned to come againe into the fauour of God, or
not: why <name>Faustus</name>, thou knowest that this is agaynst thy promise, for
what shouldst thou desire to know that, hauing alreadie giuen thy soule to the
Diuell to haue the pleasure of this worlde, and to know the secrets of hell':
therefore art thou damned, and howe canst thou then come agayne to the fauour
of God? Wherefore I directly answere, no; for whomsoeuer God hath forsaken and
throwne into hell, must there abide his wrath and indignation in that
vnquenchable fire, where is no hope nor mercy to bee looked for, but abiding in
perpetuall paines world without end: for euen as much it auaileth thee
<name>Faustus</name>, to hope for the fauour of GOD agayne, as <name>Lucifer</name>
himselfe, who indeede although he and we all haue a hope, yet is it to
small auaile, and taketh none effect, for out of that place GOD will neither
heare crying nor sighing; if he doe, thou shalt haue as little remorse, as
<name>Diues</name>, <name>Cain</name>, or <name>Iudas</name> had: what helpeth the Emperour, King,
Prince, Duke, Earle, Baron, Lord, Knight, Squire or Gentleman, to crie for
mercy</p><p>
being there': Nothing: for if on the earth they would not be Tyrants, and
selfe-willed, rich with couetousnesse; proud with pomp, gluttons, drunkards,
whoremongers, backbiters, robbers, <milestone n="19" unit="BMP"/> murderers, blasphemers, and such
like, then were there some hope to be looked for: therefore my <name>Faustus</name>,
as thou commest to hell with these qualities, thou must say with <name>Cain</name>,
My sinnes are greater then can be forgiuen, goe hang thy selfe with
<name>Iudas</name>: and lastly, bee content to suffer torments with <name>Diues</name>.
Therefore know <name>Faustus</name>, that the damned haue neither ende nor time
appoynted in the which they may hope to bee released, for if there were any
such hope, that they but by throwing one drop of water out of the Sea in a day,
vntill it were all drie: or if there were an heape of sand as high as from the
earth to the heauens, that a bird carying away but one come in a day, at the
end of this so long labour; that yet they might hope at the last, God would
haue mercy on them, they would be comforted: but now there is no hope that God
once thinkes vpon them, or that their howlings shall neuer bee heard; yea, so
vnpossible, as it is for thee to hide thy self from God, or vnpossible for thee
to remoue the mountaines, or to emptie the sea, or to tell the number of the
drops of raine that haue falne from Heauen vntill this day, or to tell what
there is most of in the worlde, yea and for a Camel to goe thorough the eye of
a needle: euen so vnpossible it is for thee <name>Faustus</name>, and the rest of
the damned, to come againe into the fauour of God.  And thus <name>Faustus</name>
hast thou heard my last sentence, &amp; I pray thee how doest thou like
it': But know this, that I counsell thee to let me be vnmolested hereafter with
such disputations, or els I will vexe thee euery limme, to thy small
contentment. Doctor <name>Faustus</name> departed from his Spirit very pensiue and
sorrowful, layd him on his bed, altogether doubtful of the grace and fauour of
God, wherfore he fell into f6[a]ntasticall cogitations: fame he would haue had
his soule at liberty again, but the diuel had so blinded him, &amp; taken such
deepe roote in his heart, that he could neuer think to craue Gods mercy, or if
by chance hee had any good <term id="n37">motion</term><note target="n37" type="gloss" anchored="yes">impulse</note>, straightwaies the diuel would thrust him a
fayre Lady into his chamber, which fell to kissing and dalliance with him,

through which meanes, he threw his godly motions in the wind, going forward
stil in his wicked practises, to the vtter ruine both of his body and soule.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="16" type="chapter" id="chap16">
<head><hi rend="ital">Another question put foorth by Doctor Faustus to his Spirite Mephostophiles of his owne estate.</hi> Chap. 16.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name>, beeing yet desirous to heare more straunge things,
called his Spirit vnto him, saying: My <name>Mephostophiles</name>, I haue yet
another suite vnto thee, which I pray thee denie not to resolue me of,
<name>Faustus</name> (quoth the Spirite) I am loth to <milestone n="22" unit="BMP"/> reason with thee any
further, for thou art neuer satisfied in thy minde, but aiwayes bringest me a
new. Yet I pray thee this once (quoth <name>Faustus</name>) doe me so much fauour, as
to tell me the truth in this matter, and hereafter I will be no more so earnest
with thee.  The Spirit was altogether against it, but yet once more he would
abide him: well, (said the Spirit to <name>Faustus</name>) what demaundest thou of
mee?  <name>Faustus</name> said, I would gladly know of thee, if thou wert a man in
manner and forme as I am; what wouldest thou doe to please both God and man':
Whereat the Spirit smiled saying: my <name>Faustus</name>, if I were a man as thou
art, and that God had adorned me with those gifts of nature as thou once
haddest; euen so long as the breath of God were by, &amp; within me, would I
humble my selfe vnto his Maiestie, indeuouring in all that I could to keepe his
Commaundements, prayse him, glorifie him, that I might continue in his fauour,
so were I sure to enioy the eternall ioy and felicity of his kingdome.
<name>Faustus</name> said, but that haue not I done.  No, thou sayest true (quoth
<name>Mephostophiles</name>) thou hast not done it, but thou hast denied thy Lord and
maker, which gaue thee the breath of life, speech, hearing, sight, and all
other thy reasonable senses that thou mightest vnderstand his will and
pleasure, to hue to the glory and honour of his name, and to the aduancement of
thy body and soule, him I say being thy maker hast thou denied and defied, yea
wickedly thou hast applyed that excellent gift of thine vnderstanding, and
giuen thy soule to the Diuell: therefore giue none the blame but thine owne
selfe-will, thy proude and aspiring minde, which hath brought thee into the
wrath of God and vtter damnation.  This is most true (quoth <name>Faustus</name>) but
tell me <name>Mephostophiles</name>, wouldst thou be in my case as I am nowe': Yea,
saith the Spirite (and with that fetcht a great sigh) for yet would I so humble
my selfe, that I would winne the fauour of God.  Then (said Doctor <name>Faustus</name>)
it were time enough for me if I amended.  True (said <name>Mephostophiles</name>)
if it were not for thy great sinnes, which are so odious and detestable in
the sight of God, that it is too late for thee, for the wrath of God resteth
vpon thee. Leaue off (quoth <name>Faustus</name>) and tell me my question to my
greater comfort.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 n="2" type="part">

<div2 n="17" type="chapter" id="chap17">
<head><hi rend="ital">Here followeth the second part of Doctor Faustus his life, and practises, untill his end.</hi> Chap.17.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> hauing receiued deniall of his Spirit, to be resolued any
more in such like questions propounded; forgot all good workes, and fell to be
a Kalender maker by helpe of his <milestone n="23" unit="BMP"/> Spirit; and also in short time to be
a good Astronomer or Astrologian: he had learned so perfectly of his Spirite
the course of the Sunne, Moone, and Starres, that he had the most famous name
of all the Mathematicks that liued in his time; as may well appeare by his
workes dedicated vnto sundry Dukes and Lords: for he did nothing without the
aduice of his Spirit, which learned him to presage of matters to come, which
haue come to passe since his death. The like prayse wonne he with his
Kalenders, and Almanacks making, for when he presaged vpon any change,
Operation, or alteration of the weather, or Elements; as winde, raine, fogges,
snow, hayle, moyst, dry, warme, colde, thunder, lightening:</p><p>it fell so duely out, as if an Angel of heauen had forewarned it.  He did not
like the vnskilfull Astronomers of our time, that set in Winter cold, moyst,
ayrie, frostie; and in the Dogge-dayes, hote, drye, thunder, fire, and such
like: but he set in all his works, day and houre, when, where, and how it
should happen.  If any thing wonderful were at hand, as death, famin, plague,
or warres, he would set the time and place in true and iust order, when it
should come to passe.</p></div2>

<div2 n="18" type="chapter" id="chap18">
<head><hi rend="ital">A question put foorth by Doctor Faustus to his Spirit concerning Astronomie.</hi> Chap. 18.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> falling to practise, and making his Prognostications, he
was doubtfull in many poynts: wherefore hee called vnto him <name>Mephostophiles</name>
his spirit, saying: I finde the ground of this science very difficult to
attaine vnto: for that when I <term id="n38">conferre</term><note target="n38" type="gloss" anchored="yes">compare</note> <name>Astronomie</name> and <name>Astrologia</name>,
as the Mathematicians and auncient writers haue left in memory, I finde
them to vary and very much to disagree: wherefore I pray thee to teach me the
truth in this matter.  To whome his Spirit answered, <name>Faustus</name>, thou shalt
know that the practioners or speculators, or at least the first inuentors of
these Artes, haue done nothing of themselues certaine, whereupon thou mayst
attaine to the true prognosticating or presaging of things concerning the
heauens, or of the influence of the Planets: for if by chance some one
Mathematician or Astronomer hath left behinde him any thing worthy of memorie:
they haue so blinded it with <name>&AElig;nigmaticall</name> wordes, blinde
Characters, and such obscure figures; that it is vnpossible for an earthly man
to attaine vnto the knowledge therof, without the ayde of some Spirit, or els
the special gift of God; for such are the hidden works of God from men: yet doe
we Spirits that flie and fleete in all Elements, knowe such, &amp; there is
nothing to be done, or by the Heauens pretended, but we <milestone n="22" unit="BMP"/> know it,
except onely the day of Dome.  Wherefore (<name>Faustus</name>) learne of me, I will
teach thee the course and recourse of  <seg id="n39">XXX and XX</seg> <note target="n39" anchored="yes">These are the common symbols for Saturn, Jupiter, Man, Sun, Venus, Mercury, and the Moon, in the order named.</note> the cause of winter and
summer, the exaltation and declination of the Sunne, the eclipse of the Moone,
the distance and height of the Poles, and euery fixed Starre, the nature and
operation of the elements, fire, ayre, water, and earth, and all that is
contained in them, yea herein there is nothing hidden from me, but onely the
<seg id="n40">fift essence</seg><note target="n40" anchored="yes">'the fift essence.'  In ancient or medieval philosophy the substance of which heavenly bodies were composed.  It was supposed to be latent in all things.  Here it seems to imply a divine element which Faust lost. Compare 'quintessence.'</note>, which once thou hadst <name>Faustus</name> at liberty, but now
<name>Faustus</name> thou hast lost it past recouery: wherfore leauing that which

wil not be againe had, learne now of me to make thunder, lightening, hayle,
snow, and raine: the cloudes to rent, the earth and craggie rockes to shake
and split in sunder, the Seas to swell, and rore, and <seg id="n41">ouer-run</seg><note target="n41" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'ouer-rnn.'</note> their markes.
Knowest not thou that the deeper the Sunne shines, the hotter he pearces': so,
the more thy Arte is famous whilest thou art here, the greater shall be thy
name when thou art gone.  Knowest not thou that the earth is frozen cold and
dry; the water running, colde and moyst; the ayre flying, hote and moist; the
fire consuming, hote and drie?  Yea <name>Faustus</name>, so must thy heart bee
enflamed lik the fire to mount on high: learne, <name>Faustus</name>, to flie like
my selfe, as swift as thought from one kingdome to another, to sit at princes
tables, to eate their daintiest fare, to haue thy pleasure of their fayre
Ladies, wiues, and concubines, to vse their iewels, and costly robes as things
belonging to thee, and not vnto them: learne of mee, <name>Faustus</name>, to runne
through wals, doores, and gates of stone and yron, to creepe into the earth
like a worme, to swimme in the water like a fish, to flie in the ayre like a
bird, and to hue and nourish thy selfe in the fire like a Salamander; so shalt
thou be famous, renowmed, far-spoken of, and extolled for thy skill: going on
kniues, not hurting thy feete; carying fire in thy bosome, and not burning thy
shirt; seeing through the heauens as through a Christall, wherein is placed the
Planets, with all the rest of the presaging Comets, the whole circuite of the
worlde from the East to the West, North and South: there shalt thou know,
<name>Faustus</name>, wherefore the fiery spheare aboue   and the signes of the
Zodiack doth not burne &amp; consume the whole face of the earth, being
hindered by placing the two moyst elements between them, the ayrie cloudes and
the wauering waues of water: yea, <name>Faustus</name>, I will learne thee the
secrets of na[t]ure, what the causes that the Sun in summer being at the
highest, giueth all his heate downewards on the earth; and being in winter at
the lowest, giueth all his heate vpward into the heauens: that the snow should
be of so great vertue, as the honie; <seg id="n42">and the Lady <name>Saturnia</name>  in
<name>Occulto</name>, more hotter
then the Sun in <name>Manifesto</name></seg>. <note target="n42" anchored="yes">This whole phrase is obscure.  The symbol given is the sign of Pisces in the twelve signs of the zodiac.  Its application here is not clear to us.  'In Occulto' and 'in Manifesto' mean respectively 'hidden' or 'eclipsed' and 'not hidden.'</note>Come <milestone n="23" unit="BMP"/> on my <name>Faustus</name>, I will
make thee as perfect in these things as myselfe, I will learne thee to goe
inuisible, to finde out the mines of golde and siluer, the <term id="n43">fodines</term><note target="n43" type="gloss" anchored="yes">mines</note> of
precious stones, as the Carbuncle, the Diamond, Saphir, Emerald, Rubie, Topas,
<term id="n44">Iacinct</term><note target="n44" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Hyacinth. Among the ancients a blue gem, possibly the sapphire.  In modern usage a reddish-orange gem.</note>, <term id="n45">Granat</term><note target="n45" type="gloss" anchored="yes">garnet</note>, <term id="n46">Iaspis</term><note target="n46" type="gloss" anchored="yes">jasper</note>, Amathist, vse all these at thy pleasure, take
thy hearts desire: thy time <name>Faustus</name> weareth away, then why wilt thou
not take thy pleasure of the worlde': Come vp, we wil goe visite Kings at their
owne courtes, and at their most sumptuous banquets be their guests, if
willingly they inuite vs not, then perforce wee will serue our owne turne with
their best meate and daintiest wine: Agreed quoth <name>Faustus</name>; but let mee
pause a while vpon this thou hast euen now declared vnto me.</p><p></p>
</div2>

<!-- <link targets="chap18 aa11 b11"> -->

<!-- I am drawing a questionable link between this chapter and Marlowe's Seven Deadly Sins pageant. -->

<div2 n="19" type="chapter" id="chap19">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus fell into despaire with himselfe: for hauing put foorth a question vnto his Spirit, they fell at variance, whereupon the whole route of diuels appeared vnto him, threatning him sharply.</hi> Chap. 19.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> reuoluing with himselfe the speeches of his Spirit, he
became so wofull and sorrowfull in his cogitations, that he thought himselfe
already frying in the hottest flames of hell, and lying in his muse, sodainely
there appeared vnto him his Spirit, demaunding what things so griued and
troubled his conscience, whereat Doctor <name>Faustus</name> gaue no answere: yet
the Spirite very earnestly lay vpon him to know the cause; and if it were
possible, he would finde remedie for his griefe, and ease him of his sorrowes.
To whome <name>Faustus</name> answered, I haue taken thee vnto mee as a seruant to
doe mee seruice, and thy seruice will be very deare vnto me; yet I cannot haue
any diligence of thee farther than thou list thy selfe, neither doost thou in
any thing as it becommeth thee.  The spirit replied, my <name>Faustus</name>, thou
knowest that I was neuer against thy commaundements as yet, but readie to serue
and resolue thy questions, although I am not bound vnto thee in such re
spects as concerne the hurt of our kingdome, yet was I alwaies willing to
answere thee, and so I am still: therefore my <name>Faustus</name> say on boldly,
what is thy will and pleasure': At which words, the spirit stole away the heart
of <name>Faustus</name>, who spake in this sorte, <name>Mephostophiles</name>, tell me how
and after what sorte God made the world, and all the creatures in them, and why
man was made after the Image of God': The spirit hearing this, answered,
<name>Faustus</name> thou knowest that all this is in vaine for thee to aske, I knowe
that thou art sory for that thou hast done, but it auaileth thee not, for I
will teare thee in thousands of pee-<milestone n="24" unit="BMP"/>ces, if thou change not thine
opinions, and hereat hee vanished away.  Whereat <name>Faustus</name> al sorrowful
for that he had put forth such a question, fel to weeping and to how[l]ing
bitterly, not for his sinnes towards God, but for that the Diuel was departed
from him so sodainely, and in such a rage.  And being in this perplexitie, hee
was sodainely taken in such an extreame cold, as if he should haue frozen in
the place where he sate, in which, the greatest Diuel in hell appeared vnto
him, with certaine of his hideous and infernal companie in the most ougliest
shapes that it was possible to think vpon, and trauersing the chamber round
about where <name>Faustus</name> sate, <name>Faustus</name> thought to himselfe, now are
they come for me though my time bee not come, and that because I haue asked
such questions of my seruant <name>Mephostophiles</name>:</p><p>at whose cogitations, the chiefest Diuel which was his Lord, vnto whom
he gaue his soule, that was <name>Lucifer</name>, spake in this sorte: <name>Faustus</name>,
I haue seene thy thoughtes, which are not as thou hast vowed vnto me, by
vertue of this letter, and shewed him the Obligation that hee had written with
his owne blood, wherefore I am come to visite thee and to shewe thee some of
our hellish pastimes, in hope that will drawe and confirme thy minde a little
more stedfast vnto vs.  Content quoth <name>Faustus</name>, goe too, let mee see what
pastime you can make.  At which words, the great Diuell in his likenes sate him
downe by <name>Faustus</name>, commanding the rest of the Diuels to appeare in their
forme, as if they were in hel: first entred <name>Belial</name> in forme of a Beare,
with curled black haire to the ground, his eares standing vpright: within the
eare was as red as blood, out of which issued flames of fire, his teeth were a
foote at least long, as white as snowe, with a tayle three elles long (at the
least) hauing two wings, one behinde each arme, and thus one after another they
appeared to <name>Faustus</name> in forme as they were in hell. <name>Lucifer</name>
himselfe sate in manner of a man, all hairie, but of a browne colour like a
Squirrell, curled, and his tayle turning vpwards on his back as the Squirrels
vse, I thinke hee could cracke nuts too like a Squirrel.  After him came
<name>Beelzebub</name> in curled hayre of hors flesh colour, his head like the head
of a Bull, with a mightie payre of hornes, and two long eares downe to the
grounde, and two winges on his backe, with pricking stinges like thornes: out
of his wings issued flames of fire, his tayle was like a Cowe.  Then came
<name>Astaroth</name> in forme of a worme, going vpright on his taile; he had no
feete, but a tayle like a slowe-worme: vnder his <term id="n47">chappes</term><note target="n47" type="gloss" anchored="yes">jaws</note> grew two shorte
hands, and his back was cole blacke, his belly thick in the middle, and yellow
like golde, hauing many bristles on his backe like a Hedgehog.  After him came
<name>Chamagosta</name>, being white and gray mixed, ex- <milestone n="25" unit="BMP"/> ceeding curled and
hayrie: hee had a head like the head of an Asse, the tayle like a Cat, and
<term id="n48">Cleaes</term><note target="n48" type="gloss" anchored="yes">claws</note> like an Oxe, lacking nothing of an ell broade.  Then came <name>Anobis</name>;
this Diuell had a head like a Dog, white and black hayre in shape of a
Hogge, sauing that he had but two feete, one vnder his throate, the other at
his tayle: he was foure elles long, with hanging eares like a Blood-hound.
After him came <name>Dythycan</name>, he was a short theefe in forme of a Feasant,
with shining feathers, and foure feete: his neck was greene, his bodie red,
and his feete blacke.  The last was called <name>Brachus</name>, with foure shorte
feete like an Hedgehog, yellow and greene: the vpper side of his bodie was
browne, and the bellie like blewe flames of fire; the tayle redde, like the
tayle of a Monkey.  The rest of the Diuels were in forme of vnsensible beasts,
as Swine, Harts, Beares, Woolues, Apes, Buffes, Goates, Antelopes, Elephants,
Dragons, Horsses, Asses, Lions, Cats, Snakes, Toades, and all manner of vgly
odious Serpents and Wormes: yet came in such sorte, that euery one at his
entrie into the Hall, made their reuerence vnto <name>Lucifer</name>, and so tooke
their places, standing in order as they came, vntill they had filled the whole
Hall: wherewith sodainely fell a most horrible thunder-clap,
that the house shooke as though it would haue fallen to the ground, vpon which
euerie monster had a muck-fork in his hande, holding them towards <name>Faustus</name>
as though they would haue runne a tilt at him: which when <name>Faustus</name>
perceiued, hee thought vpon the words of <name>Mephostophiles</name>, when he
tolde him how the soules in hell were tormented, being cast from Diuel to Diuel
vpon muck-forkes, he thought verely to haue been tormented there of them in
like sort.  But <name>Lucifer</name> perceiuing his thought, spake to him, my
<name>Faustus</name>, how likest thow this crewe of mine': Quoth <name>Faustus</name>, why
came you not in another manner of shape?  <name>Lucifer</name> replied, wee cannot
chaunge our hellish forme, we haue shewed our selues heere, as we are there;
yet can we blind mens eyes in such sort, that when we will repayre vnto them,
as if we were men or Angels of light, although our dwelling bee in darknesse.
Then said <name>Faustus</name>, I like not so many of you together3 whereupon
<name>Lucifer</name> commaunded them to depart, except seauen of the principall,
forthwith they presently vanished, which <name>Faustus</name> perceiuing, hee was
somewhat better comforted, and spake to <name>Lucifer</name>, where is my seruant
<name>Mephostophiles</name>, let me see if hee can doe the like, wherevpon came a
fierce Dragon, flying and spitting fire round about the house, and comming
towards <name>Lucifer</name>, made reuerence, and then changed himself to ye forme of
a Frier, saying, <name>Faustus</name>, what wilt thou': Saith <name>Faustus</name>, I will
that thou teach me to transforme my selfe in like <milestone n="26" unit="BMP"/> sort as thou and
the rest haue done: then <name>Lucifer</name> put forth his Pawe, and gaue <name>Faustus</name>
a booke, saying holde, doe what thou wilt, which hee looking vpon, straight
waies changed himselfe into a Hog, then into a Worme, then into a Dragon, and
finding this for his purpose, it liked him well.  Quoth he to <name>Lucifer</name>,
and how commeth it that all these filthy formes are in the world?
<name>Lucifer</name> answered, they are ordained of God as plagues vnto men, and so
shalt thou be plagued (quoth he) whereupon, came Scorpions, Waspes, Emits,
Bees, and Gnattes, which fell to stinging and biting him, and all the whole
house was filled with a most horrible stinking fogge, in so much, that
<name>Faustus</name> sawe nothing, but still was tormented; wherefore hee cried for
helpe saying, <name>Mephostophiles</name> my faithfull seruant where art thou, helpe,
helpe I pray thee: hereat his Spirite answered nothing, but <name>Lucifer</name>
himself said, ho ho ho <name>Faustus</name>,
how likest thou the creation of the worlde, and <term id="n49">in continent</term><note target="n49" type="gloss" anchored="yes">incontinent, forthwith.</note> it was
cleare againe, and the Diuels and all the filthy Cattell were vanished, onely
<name>Faustus</name> was left alone; seeing nothing, but hearing the sweetest musick
that euer he heard before, at which he was so rauished with delight, that he
forgat the feares hee was in before: and it repented him that he had seene no
more of their pastime.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<!-- <link targets="chap19 aa12 bb12"> -->

<div2 n="20" type="chapter" id="chap20">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus desired to see hell, and of the maner how hee was vsed therein.</hi> Chap. 20.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> bethinking how his time went away, and how he had spent
eight yeares thereof, he ment to spend the rest to his better contentment,
intending quite to forget any such motions as might offend the Diuell any more:
wherefore on a time he called his spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name>, and said vnto
him, bring thou hither vnto mee thy Lord <name>Lucifer</name>, or <name>Belial</name>:</p><p>he brought him (notwithstanding) one that was called <name>Beelzebub</name>,
the which asked <name>Faustus</name> his pleasure.  Quoth <name>Faustus</name>, I would
knowe of thee if I may see Hell and take a view thereof': That thou shalt (said
the diuell) and at midnight I will fetch thee.  Well, night being come, Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> awaited very diligently for the comming of the Diuell to fetch
him, and thinking that hee tarried all too long, he went to the window, where
hee pulled open a cazement, and looking into the Element, hee sawe a cloude in
the North more black, darke and obscure, than all the rest of the Sky, from
whence the winde blew most horrible right into <name>Faustus</name> his chamber,
filled the whole house with smoake, that <name>Faustus</name> was almost smothered:
hereat fell an exceeding thunderclap, and withall came a great rugged black
<milestone n="27" unit="BMP"/> Beare, all curled, &amp; vpon his backe a chayre of beaten golde, and
spake to <name>Faustus</name>, saying, sit vp and away with me: and Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
that had so long abode the smoake, wisht rather to be in hell than there,
got on the Diuell, and so they went together.  But marke how the Diuell blinded
him, and made him beleeue that he carried him into hell, for he caned him into
the ayre, where <name>Faustus</name> fell into a sound sleepe, as if hee had sate in
a warme water or bath: at last they came to a place which burneth continually
with flashing flames of fire and brimstone,

whereout issued an exceeding mighty clap of thunder, with so horrible a noyse,
that <name>Faustus</name> awaked, but the Diuell went forth on his way and caned
<name>Faustus</name> therinto, yet notwithstanding, howsoeuer it burnt, Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> felt no more heate, than as it were the glimps of the Sunne in
May: there heard he all manner of musicke to welcome him, but sawe none playing
on them; it pleased him well, but he durst not aske, for hee was forbidden it
before.  To meet the Diuel &amp; the guest that came with him, came three other
ougly Diuels, the which ran back againe before the Beare to make them way,
against whome there came running an exceeding great Hart, which would haue
thrust <name>Faustus</name> out of his chayre, but being defended by the other three
Diuels, the Hart was put to the repulse: thence going on their way <name>Faustus</name>
looked, and beholde there was nothing but Snakes, and all manner of
venemous beastes about him, which were exceeding great, vnto the which Snakes
came many Storks, and swallowed vp all the whole multitude of Snakes, that they
left not one: which when <name>Faustus</name> sawe, he marueiled greatly: but
proceeding further on their hellish voyage, there came forth of a hollow cliffe
an exceeding great flying Bull, the which with such a force hit <name>Faustus</name>
his chayre with his head and homes, that he turned <name>Faustus</name> and his
Beare ouer and ouer, so that the Beare vanished away, whereat <name>Faustus</name>
began to crie: oh, woe is mee that euer I came here: for hee thought there
to haue been beguiled of the Diuel, and to make his ende before his time
appointed or conditioned of the Diuel: but shortly came v[n]to him a monstrous
Ape, bidding <name>Faustus</name> bee of good cheare, and said, get vpon me; all the
fire in hel seemed to <name>Faustus</name> to haue been put out, wherevpon followed a
monstrous thick fogge, that hee sawe nothing, but shortly it seemed to him to
waxe cleare, where he saw two great Dragons fastned to a waggon, into the which
the Ape ascended and set <name>Faustus</name> therein; foorth flewe the Dragons into
an exceeding darke cloude, where <name>Faustus</name> saw neither Dragon nor Chariot
wherein he sat, and such were the cries of tormented soules, with mightie
thunder-claps and flashing light-<milestone n="28" unit="BMP"/>nings about his eares, that poore
<name>Faustus</name> shooke for feare.  Vpon this came they to a water, stinking and
filthie, thick like mudde, into the which ran the Dragons, sinking vnder with
waggon
and all; but <name>Faustus</name> felt no water but as it were a small mist, sauing
that the waues beate so sore vpon him, that hee saw nothing vnder and ouer him
but only water, in the which he lost his Dragons, Ape, and waggon; and sinking
yet deeper and deeper, hee came at last as it were vpon an high Rock, where the
waters parted and left him thereon: but when the water was gone, it seemed to
him hee should there haue ended his life, for he saw no way but death: the
Rocke was as high from the bottome as Heauen is from the earth: there sate he,
seeing nor hearing any man, and looked euer vpon the Rocke; at length hee saw a
little hole, out of the which issued fire; thought he, how shall I now doe': I
am forsaken of the Diuels, and they that brought mee hither, here must I either
fall to the bottome, or burne in the fire, or sit still in despaire: with that
in his madnesse he gaue a leape into the fierie hole, saying: holde you
infernall Hagges, take here this sacrifice as my last ende; the which I iustly
haue deserued: vpon this he was entred, and finding himselfe as yet vnburned or
touched of the fire, he was the better <term id="n50">appayed</term><note target="n50" type="gloss" anchored="yes">contented</note>, but there was so great a
noyse as he neuer heard the like before, it passed all the thunder that euer he
had heard; &amp; coming down further to the bottome of the Rocke, he sawe a
fire, wherein were many worthie and noble personages, as Emperours, Kings,
Dukes and Lords, and many thousands more of tormented soules, at the edge of
which fire ran a most pleasant, cleare, and coole water to beholde, into the
which many tormented soules sprang out of the fire to coole themselues; but
b[e]ing so freezing cold, they were constrained to returne againe into the
fire, and thus wearied themselues and spent their endles torments out of one
labyrinth into another, one while in heate, another while in colde: but
<name>Faustus</name> standing thus all this while gazing on them that were thus
tormented, hee sawe one leaping out of the fire and scriching horriblie, whome
he thought to haue knowne, wherefore he would fame haue spoken vnto him, but
remembring that hee was forbidden, hee refrained speaking.  Then this Diuel
that brought him in, came to him againe in likenes of a Beare, with the chayre
on his back, and bad him sit vp, for it was time to depart: so <name>Faustus</name>
got vp, and the Diuel caned him out into the ayre,

where he had so sweete musick that hee fell asleepe by the way.  His boy
<name>Christopher</name> being all this while at home, and missing his master so
long, thought his master would haue taried and dwelt with the Diuell for euer:
but whilest his boy was in these co-<milestone n="29" unit="BMP"/>gitations, his master came home,
for the Diuel brought him home fast a sleepe as he sate in his chayre, and so
he threw him on his bed, where (being thus left of the Diuel) he lay vntil day.
When hee awaked, bee was amazed, like a man that had been in a darke dungeon;
musing with <seg id="n51">himselfe</seg><note target="n51" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'himfelfe.'</note> if it were true or false that he had seene hel, or
whether he was blinded or not: but he rather perswaded himself that he had been
there than otherwise, because he had seene such wonderful things: wherefore he
most carefully tooke pen and incke, and wrote those thinges in order as hee had
seene: the which writing was afterwards found by his boy in his studie; which
afterwards was published to the whole citie of <name>Wittenberg</name> in open print,
for example to all Christians.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="21" type="chapter" id="chap21">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus was carried through the ayre vp to the heauens to see the world, and how the Skie and Planets ruled: after the which he wrote one letter to his friend of the same to Liptzig, how he went about the world in eight daies.</hi> Chap. 21.</head>
<p>THis letter was found by a freeman and Citizen of <name>Wittenberg</name>, written
with his own hande, and sent to his friend at <name>Liptzig</name> a Phisition, named
<name>Ioue Victori</name>, the contents of which were as followeth.</p><p>	Amongst other things (my louing friend and brother) I remember yet the former
friendship had together, when wee were schoolefellowes and students in the
Vniuersitie at <name>Wittenberg</name>, whereas you first studied Phisicke,
Astronomie, Astrologie, Geometrie, and Cosmographie; I to the contrarie (you
know) studied Diuinitie: notwithstanding now in any of your owne studies I am
seene (I am perswaded) further then your selfe: for sithence I began I haue
neuer erred, for (might I speake it without affecting my owne praise) my
Kalendars and other practises haue not onely the commenda

tions of the common sorte, but also of the chiefest Lordes and Nobles of this
our Dutch Nation: because (which is chiefly to be noted) I write and presaged
of matters to come, which all accorde and fall out so right, as if they had
been alreadie seene before.  And for that (my bebued <name>Victori</name>) you write
to know my voyage which I made into the Heauens, the which (as you certifie me
you haue had some suspition of, although you partly perswaded your selfe, that
it is a thing vnpossible) no matter for that, it is as it is, and let it be as
it will, once it was done, in such maner as now according vnto your request I
giue you here to vnderstand.</p><p>

<seg id="c12">	I being once laide on my bed, and could not sleepe for thinking on <milestone n="30" unit="BMP"/>
my Kalender and practise, I marueiled with my selfe how it were possible that
the Firmament should bee knowne and so largely written of men, or whether they
write true or false, by their owne opinions, or supposition, or by due
obseruations and true course of the heauens.  Beholde, being in these my muses,
sodainly I heard a great noyse, in so much that I thought my house would haue
been blowne downe, so that all my doores and chestes flewe open, whereat I was
not a little astonied, for withall I heard a groning voyce which said, get vp,
the desire of thy heart, minde, and thought shalt thou see: at the which I
answered, what my heart desireth, that would I fame see, and to make proofe, if
I shall see I will away with thee.  Why then (quoth he) looke out at thy
windowe, there commeth a messenger for thee, that did I, and beholde, there
stoode a Waggon, with two Dragons before it to drawe the same, and all the
Waggon was of a light burning fire, and for that the Moone shone, I was the
willinger at that time to depart: but the voyce spake againe, sit vp and let vs
away: I will, said I, goe with thee, but vppon this condition, that I may aske
after all things that I see, heare, or thinke on: the voyce answered, I am
content for this time. Hereupon I got me into the Waggon, so that the Dragons
caned me vpright into ye ayre.  The Waggon had also foure wheels the which
ratled so, and made such a noyse as if we had been all this while running on
the stones: and round about vs flew out flames of fier, and the higher that I
came, the more the earth seemed to be darkened, so that me thought I came out
of a dungeon, and looking downe from Heauen, beholde, <name>Mephostophiles</name> my
Spirit and seruant was behinde me, and when he perceiued that I saw him, he
came and sate by mee, to whome I said, I pray thee <name>Mephostophiles</name>
whether shall I goc now?  Let not that trouble thy minde, said hee, and yet
they caned vs higher vp.  And now will I tell thee good friend and
schoole-fellow, what things I haue seene and prooued; for on the Tewsday went I
out, and on Tewsday seuen-nights following I came home againe, that is, eight
dayes, in which time I slept not, no not one winke came in mine eyes, and we
went inuisible of any man: and as the daye began to appeare, after our first
nights iorney, I saide to my Spirite <name>Mephostophiles</name>, I pray thee how
farre haue wee now ridden, I am sure thou knowest: for me thinkes that we are
ridden exceeding farre, the Worlde seemeth so little: <name>Mephostophiles</name>
answered mee, my <name>Faustus</name> beleeue mee, that from the place from
whence thou camst, vnto this place where wee are now, is already 47. leagues
right in height, and as the day increased, I looked downe vpon the Worlde,
<milestone n="31" unit="BMP"/> there saw I many kingdomes and prouinces, likewise the whole world,
<name>Asia</name>, <name>Europa</name>, and <name>Africa</name>, I had a sight of: and being so high,
quoth I to my Spirit, tell me now how these kingdomes lye, and what they are
called, the which he denied not, saying, see this on our left hand is
<name>Hungaria</name>, this is also <name>Prussia</name> on our left hand, and <name>Poland</name>,
<name>Muscouia</name>, <seg id="n52"><name>Tartascelesia</name></seg><note target="n52" anchored="yes">'Tartascelesia' looks like a combination of Tartary and Silesia.</note>, <name>Bohemia</name>, <name>Saxony</name>: and here on our right hand,
<name>Spaine</name>, <name>Portugal</name>, <name>France</name>, <name>England</name>, and <name>Scotland</name>: then right out
before vs lie the kingdoms of <name>Persia</name>, <name>India</name>, <name>Arabia</name>, the king of
<seg id="n53"><name>Alchar</name></seg><note target="n53" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Cairo</note>, and the great <seg id="n54"><name>Cham</name></seg><note target="n54" anchored="yes">Khan, the ruler of Tartary.</note>: nowe are we come to
<name>Wittenberg</name>, and are right ouer the towne of <seg id="n55"><name>Weim</name></seg><note target="n55" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Probably 'Wien,' Vienna.</note> in <name>Austria</name>,
and ere long will we be at <name>Constantinople</name>, <name>Tripolie</name>, and
<name>Jerusalem</name>, and after will we pearce the frozen Zone, and shortly touch
the Horizon, and the Zenith of <name>Wittenberg</name>. There looked I on the
<name>Ocean</name> Sea, and beheld a great many of ships &amp; Gallies ready to the
battaile, one against another: and thus I spent my iourney, now cast I my eies
here, now there, toward South, North, East, and West, I haue been in one place
where it rained and hailed, and in another where the Sun shone ex
cellent fayre, and so I thinke that I saw the most things in and about the
world, with great admiration that in one place it rained, and in an other hayle
and snow, on this side the Sunne shone bright, some hils couered with snow
neuer consuming, other were so hot that grasse and trees were burned and
consumed therewith.

Then looked I vp to the heauens, and behold, they went so
swift, that I thought they would haue sprong in thousands.  Likewise it was so
cleare and so hot, that I could not long gaze into it, it so dimmed my sight:
&amp; had not my Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name> couered me as it were with a
shadowing cloude, I had been burnt with the extreame heat thereof, for the Skie
the which we beholde here when we looke vp from the earth, is so fast and
thicke as a wal, cleare and shining bright as a Christal, in the which is
placed the Sunne, which casteth foorth his rayes or beames ouer the vniuersall
worlde, to the vttermost confines of the earth.  But we thinke that the Sun is
very little: no, it is altogether as big as the world.  Indeed the body
substantiall is but little in compasse, but the rayes or streame that it
casteth forth, by reason of the thing wherein it is placed, maketh him to
extend and shew himselfe ouer the whole world: and we thinke that the Sunne
runneth his course, and that the heauens stand still: no, it is the heauens
that moue his course, and the Sun abideth perpetually in his place, he is
permanent, &amp; fixed in his place, &amp; although we see him beginning to
ascend in the Orient or East, at the highest in the Meridian or South, setting
in the Occident or West, yet is hee at <milestone n="32" unit="BMP"/> the lowest in Septentrio or
North, and yet he moueth not.  It is the axle of the heauens that moueth the
whole firmamet, being a Chaos or confused thing, and for that proofe, I will
shew thee this example, like as thou seest a bubble made of water and sope
blowne forth of a quill, is in forme of a confused masse or Chaos, &amp; being
in this forme, is moued at pleasure of the wind, which runneth round about that
Chaos, &amp; moueth him also round: euen so is the whole firmament or Chaos,
wherein are placed the sun, and the rest of the Planets turned and caned at the
pleasure of the Spirit of God, which is wind. <seg id="n56">Yea Christian Reader</seg><note target="n56" anchored="yes">The long address to the 'Christian Reader' is, of course, an interpolation of the English translator.</note>, to the
glory of God, and for the 
profite of thy soule, I wil open vnto thee the diuine opinion touching the
ruling of this confused Chaos, farre more than any rude Germane Author, being
possessed with the diuell, was able to vtter; and to prooue some of my sentence
before to be true, looke into <name>Genesis</name> vnto the workes of God, at the
creation of the world, there shalt thou finde, that the Spirit of God moued
vpon the waters before heauen and earth were made.  Marke how he made it, and
howe by his word euery element tooke his place: these were not his workes, but
his words; for all the words he vsed before, he concluded afterwards in one
worke, which was in making man: marke reader with patience for thy soules
health, see into all that was done by the word and worke of God, light and
darkenes was, the firmament stoode, and their great   &amp; little light   in
it: the moyst waters were in one place, the earth was dry, &amp; euery element
brought foorth according to the word of God: now followeth his workes he made
man like his owne image, how': out of the earth': The earth wil shape no image
without water, there was one of the elements.  But all this while where was
winde? all elements were at the word of God, man was made, and in a forme by
the worke of God, yet moued not that worke, before God breathed the Spirit of
life into his nostrils, and made him a huing soule, here was the first wind and
Spirit of God out of his owne mouth, which wee haue likewise from the same
seede which was onely planted by God in <name>Adam</name>, which winde, breath, or
spirit, when he had receiued, bee was liuing &amp; moouing on earth, for it was
ordayned of God for his habitation, but the heauens are the habita[t]ion of the
Lord: and like as I shewed before of the bubble or confused Chaos made of water
and sope, through the wind and breath of man is turned round, and carried with
euery wind; euen so the firmament wherein the Sun and the rest of the Planets
are fixed, moued, turned, and carried with the winde, breath, or Spirit of God,
for the heauens and firmament are moueable as the Chaos, but the sun is fixed
in the firmament.  And farther my good <milestone n="33" unit="BMP"/> schoolefellow, I was thus nigh
the heauens, where me thought euery Planet was but as halfe the earth, and
vnder the firmament ruled the Spirits in the ayre, and as I came downe I looked
vpon the worlde &amp; the heauens, and me thought that the earth was inclosed
in comparison within the firmament, as the yolke of an egge within the white,
and me thought that the whole length of the earth was not a span long, and the
water was as if it had been twise as broad and long as the earth, euen thus at
the eight dayes end came I home againe, &amp; fell a sleepe, and so I continued
<seg id="n57">sleeping</seg><note target="n57" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'sleepiug.'</note> three dayes and three nights together: &amp; the first houre that I
waked, I fell fresh againe to my Kalender, and haue made them in right ample
maner as you know, and to satisfie your request, for that you writ vnto me, I
haue in consideration of our olde friendship had at the Vniuersitie of
<name>Wittenberg</name>, declared vnto you my heauenly voyage, wishing no worse vnto
you, than vnto my selfe, that is, that your minde were as mine in all respects.
<hi rend="ital">Dixi. Doctor Faustus the Astrologian</hi>.
</seg></p>
</div2>

<div2 n="22" type="chapter" id="chap22">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus made his iourney thorough the principal and most famous lands in the world.</hi> Chap. 22.</head>
<p>
<seg id="c12a">DOctor <name>Faustus</name> hauing ouer-<seg id="n58">runne</seg><note target="n58" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'runue.'</note>  fifteen yeers of his appointed time,
he tooke vpon him a iourney, with ful pretencec to see the whole world: and
calling his spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name> vnto him, he sayd: thou knowest that
thou art bound vnto me vpon conditions, to performe and fulfill my desire in
all thengs, wherfore my pretence is to visite the whole face of the earth
visible &amp; inuisible when it pleaseth me: wherfore, I enioyne and command
thee to the same.  Whereupon <name>Mephostophiles</name> answered, I am ready my Lord
at thy command &amp; foorthwith the Spirit changed himselfe into the likenes of
a flying horse, saying, <name>Faustus</name> sit vp, I am ready.  Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
loftily sate vpon him, &amp; forward they went: <name>Faustus</name> came
thorough many a land &amp; Prouince; as <name id="n59">Pannonia</name><note target="n59" anchored="yes">The region of Hungary.</note>, <name>Austria</name>, <name>Germania</name>,
<name>Bohemia</name>, <name>Slesia</name>, <name>Saxony</name>, <name id="n60">Missene</name><note target="n60" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Meissen</note>, <name id="n61">During</name><note target="n61" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Thuringia</note>, <name id="n62">Francklandt</name><note target="n62" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Franconia</note>, <name id="n63">Shawblandt</name><note target="n63" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Suabia</note>,
<name id="n64">Beyerlandt</name><note target="n64" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Bavaria</note>, <name>Stiria</name>, <name>Ca
rinthia</name>, <name>Poland</name>,  <name id="n65">Litaw</name>,<note target="n65" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Lithuania</note> <name id="n66">Liefland</name>,<note target="n66" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Livonia</note> <name>Prussia</name>, <name>Denmarke</name>, <name>Muscouia</name>,
<name>Tartaria</name>, <name>Turkie</name>, <name>Persia</name>, <name>Cathai</name>, <name>Alexandria</name>, <name>Bar baria</name>, <name>Ginnie</name>, <name>Peru</name>, the
strayghts of <name>Magelanes, India</name>, all about the frozen <name>Zone</name>, and
<name id="n67">Terra Incognita</name>,<note target="n67" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Probably the unknown regions near the poles.</note> <name id="n68">Noua Hispaniola</name>,<note target="n68" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Mexico</note> the Isles of <name id="n69">Terzera</name>,<note target="n69" type="gloss" anchored="yes">One of the Azores.</note>
<name id="n70">Mederi</name>,<note target="n70" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Probably Madeira.</note> <name id="n71">S. Michaels</name>, <note target="n71" type="gloss" anchored="yes">One of the Azores.</note> the <name>Canaries</name>, and the <name id="n72">Tenorrifocie</name>,<note target="n72" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Probably Teneriffe.</note>
into <name>Spaine</name>, the <name id="n73">Mayne Land</name>,<note target="n73" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Perhaps the old province of Maine in France.</note> <name>Portugall, Italie, Campania</name>,
the Kingdome of <name>Naples</name>, the Isles of <name>Sicilia</name>, <name>Malta</name>, <name id="n74">Maioria</name>,<note target="n74" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Majorca</note>
<name id="n75">Minoriac</name><note target="n75" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Minorca</note> to the Knights of the <name>Rhodes, Candie</name>, or <milestone n="34" unit="BMP"/>
<name>Creete, Ciprus, Corinth, Switzerland, France, Freesland, Westphalia, Zeland,
Holland, Brabant</name>, and all the 17. Prouinces in <name>Netherland, England,
Scotland, Ireland</name>, all <name>America</name>, and <seg id="n76"><name>Island</name></seg>,<note target="n76" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Iceland</note> the out Isles
of <name>Scotland</name>, the <name>Orchades, Norway</name>, the Bishoprick of <seg id="n77">Breame</seg>,<note target="n77" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Bremen</note>
and so home agayne: all these Kingdomes, Prouinces and Countries he passed
in 25. dayes, in which time he saw very little that delighted his minde:
wherefore he tooke a little rest at home, and burning in desirec to see more at
large, and to beholde the secrets of each kingdome, he set forward again on his
iourney vpon his swift horse <name>Mephostophiles</name>, and came to <seg id="n78">Treir</seg>,<note target="n78" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Treves, German Trier.</note>
for that he chiefly desired to see this towne, and the monuments thereof;
but there he saw not many wonders, except one fayre Pallace that belonged vnto
the Bishop, and also a mighty large Castle that was built of bricke, with three
walles and three great trenches, so strong, that it was impossible for any
princes power to win it; then he saw a Church, wherein was buried <name>Simeon</name>,
and the Bishop <name>Popo</name>: their Tombes are of most sumptuous large Marble
stone, closed and ioyned together with great bars of yron: from whence he
departed to <name>Paris</name>, where hee liked well the Academie; and what place or
Kingdome soeuer fell in his minde, the same

he visited.  He came from <name>Paris</name> to <seg id="n79"><name>Mentz</name></seg>,<note target="n79" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Mayence</note> where the riuer of
<name>Mayne</name> fals into the <name>Rhine</name>; notwithstanding he taried not long
there, but went to <name>Campania</name> in the Kingdome of <name>Neapolis</name>, in which
he saw an <seg id="n80">innumerable</seg><note target="n80" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'innmerable.'</note> sort of Cloysters, Nunneries, and Churches, great and
high houses of stone, the streetes fayre and large, and straight foorth from
one end of the towne to the other as a line, and al the pauement of the Citie
was of brick, and the more it rayned in the towne, the fayrer the streetes were
; there saw he the Tombe of <name>Virgil</name>; &amp; the high way that bee cutte
through that mighty hill of stone in one night, the whole length of an English
mile: then he saw the number of Gallies, and Argozies that lay there at the
Citie head, the Windmil that stood in the water, the Castle in the water, and
the houses aboue the water where vnder the Gallies might ride most safely from
raine or winde; then he saw the Castle on the hil ouer the towne, and many
monuments within: also the hil called <name>Vesuvius</name>, whereon groweth all the
Greekish wine, and most pleasant sweet Oliues. From thence he came to
<name>Venice</name>, whereas he wondered not a little to see a Citie so famously
built standing in the Sea: where, through euery streete the water ranne in
such largenes, that great Ships and Barks might passe from one streete to
another, hauing yet a way on both sides the water, whereon men and horse might
passe; he maruailed also howe it was possible for so much victual to be found
in the towne and so good cheape, considering <milestone n="35" unit="BMP"/> that for a whole league
off nothing grew neere the same.  He wondred not a little at the fayrenes of
Saint <name>Markes</name> place, and the sumptuous Church standing therein called
Saint <name>Markes</name>; how all the pauement was set with coloured stones, and all
the <seg id="n81">Roode or loft</seg><note target="n81" anchored="yes">Possibly the 'roodloft.'  Logeman also suggests a second possibility, i.e. that 'roode' is a misprint for 'roofe.'</note> of the Church double gilded ouer.  Leauing this, he came to
<name>Padoa</name>, beholding the maner of their Academie, which is called the mother
or nurse of Christendome, there he heard the Doctors, and saw the most
monuments in the towne, entred his name into the Vniuersitie of the Germane
nation, and wrote himselfe Doctor <name>Faustus</name> the vnsatiable Speculator:
then saw he the worthiest monument in the world for a Church, named S.

<name>Anthonies</name> Cloyster, which for the pinacles thereof, and the contriuing
of the Church, hath not the like in Christendome. This towne is fenced about
with three mighty walles of stone and earth, betwixt the which runneth goodly
ditches of water: 
twise euery 24. houres passeth boates betwixt <name>Padoa</name> and <name>Venice</name>
with passengers, as they doe here betwixt <name>London</name> and <name>Grauesend</name>,
and euen so far they differ in distance: <name>Faustus</name> beheld likewise
the Counsaile house &amp; the Castle with no small wonder.</seg>

<!-- <link targets="c12 c12a" id="xx12"> -->
<!-- <link targets="xx12 aa13 bb13 bb14"> -->

<seg id="c13">Well, forward he
went to <name>Rome</name>, which lay, &amp; doth yet lie, on the riuer <name>Tybris</name>,
the which deuideth the Citie in two parts: ouer the riuer are foure great
stone bridges, and vpon the one bridge called <name>Ponte</name> S. <name>Angelo</name> is
the castle of S. <name>Angelo</name>, wherein are so many great cast peeces as there
are dayes in a yeare, &amp; such Pieces that will shoote seuen bullets off with
one fire, to this Castle commeth a priuie vault from the Church and Pallace of
Saint <name>Peter</name>, through the which the Pope (if any danger be) passeth from
his Pallace to the Castle for safegard; the Citie hath eleuen gates, and a hill
called <seg id="n82"><name>Vaticinium</name></seg>,<note target="n82" type="gloss" anchored="yes">'Vaticinium' should of course be Vaticanum.</note> whereon S. <name>Peters</name> Church is built: in that
Church the holie Fathers will heare no confession, without the penitent bring
mony in his hand.  Adioyning to this Church, is the <seg id="n83"><name>Campo Santo</name></seg><note target="n83" anchored="yes">'Campo Santo' is the usual Italian term for cemetery. We can find no connection between Charlemagne and this 'Campo Santo.'  The reference to the 'thirteen Pilgrims' seems to have something to do with the mandatum ceremony.</note>, the
which <seg id="n84"><name>Carolus Magnus</name></seg><note target="n84" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'Maguus.'</note> built, where euery day thirteen Pilgrims haue
their dinners serued of the best: that is to say, Christ and his twelue
Apostles. Hard by this he visited the Church yard of S. <name>Peters</name>, where he
saw the <seg id="n85"><name>Pyramide</name></seg><note target="n85" type="gloss" anchored="yes">A common term for obelisk in the sixteenth century.</note> that <seg id="n86"><name>Iulius C&aelig;sar</name></seg><note target="n86" anchored="yes">The obelisk was brought from Egypt by Caligula and placed in the center of the Gaianum, the circus of Caligula, the north side of which was used as a foundation for the south half of St. Peter's.  For centuries it was considered the tomb of Julius Caesar.</note> brought out of
<name>Africa</name>; it stood in <name>Faustus</name> his time leaning against the Church
wall of Saint <name>Peters</name>, but <seg id="n87">now <name>Papa Sixtus</name> hath erected it</seg><note target="n87" anchored="yes">This phrase may furnish a hint as to the date of the translation.  The tense used seems to indicate that Pope Sixtus was still alive at the time of writing. He died August 27, 1590. The obelisk was erected on its present site in the summer of 1586.</note> in
the middle of S. <name>Peters</name> Church yard; it is 24. fathom long and at the
lower end sixe fathom foure square, and so forth

smaller vpwards, on the top is a Crucifixe of beaten golde, the stone standeth
on foure Lyons of brasse.  Then he visited the seuen Churches of <name>Rome</name>,
that were S. <name>Peters</name>, S. <name>Pauls</name>, S. <name>Sebastians</name>, S.
<name>Iohn Lateran</name>, S. <name>Laurence</name>, S. <name>Mary Magdalen</name>, and S.
<name>Marie maiora</name>: then went he <milestone n="36" unit="BMP"/> without the towne, where he saw the
conduits of water that runne leuell through hill and dale, bringing water into
the town fifteen Italian miles off: 
</seg>
<!-- <link targets="c13 aa14 bb15"> -->
<seg id="c14">other monuments he saw, too many to recite,
but amongst the rest he was desirous to see the Popes Pallace, and his maner of
seruice at his table, wherefore he and his Spirit made themselues inuisible,
and came into the Popes Court, and priuie chamber where he was, there saw he
many seruants attendant on his holmes, with many a flattering Syco~ phant
carrying of his meate, and there hee marked the Pope and the manner of his
seruice, which hee seeing to bee so vnmeasurable and sumptuous; fie (quoth
<name>Faustus</name>) why had not the Diuel made a Pope of me?  <name>Faustus</name> saw
notwithstanding in that place those that were like to himselfe, proud, stout,
wilfull, gluttons, drunkards, whoremongers, breakers of wedlocke, and followers
of all manner of vngodly exercises:
wherefore he said to his Spirit, I thought that I had been alone a hogge, or
porke of the diuels, but he must beare with me yet a little longer, for these
hogs of <name>Rome</name> are already fatned, and fitted to make his roste-meate, the
Diuel might doe well nowe to spit them all and hane them to the fire, and <seg id="n88">let</seg><note target="n88" anchored="yes">B.M. has the e in 'let' upside down.</note>
him summon the Nunnes to turne the spits: for as none must confesse the Nunne
but the Frier, so none should turne the rosting Frier but the Nunne.  Thus
continued <name>Faustus</name> three dayes in the Popes Pallace, and yet had no lust
to his meate, but stood still in the Popes chamber, and saw euery thing
whatsoeuer it was: on a time the Pope would haue a feast prepared for the
Cardinall of <name>Pauia</name>, and for his first welcome the Cardinall was bidden
to dinner: and as he sate at meate, the Pope would euer be blessing and
crossing ouer his mouth; <name>Faustus</name> could suffer it no longer, but vp with
his fist and smote the Pope on the face, and withall he laughed that the whole
house might heare him, yet none of them sawe him nor knew where he was: the
Pope perswaded his company that it was a damned soule, commanding a Masse
presently to be said for his de

liuerie out of Purgatory, which was done: the Pope sate still at meate, but
when the latter messe came in to the Popes boord, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> laid
hands thereon saying; this is mine: 
&amp; so he took both dish &amp; meate &amp; fled vnto the Capital or
<seg id="n89">Campadolia</seg>,<note target="n89" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Probably Campidoglio.  It was on the Capitoline hill.</note> calling his spirit vnto him and said: come let vs be merry, for
thou must fetch me some wine, &amp; the cup that the Pope drinkes of, &amp;
here vpon <seg id="n90"><name>monte caual</name></seg><note target="n90" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Monte Cavallo, the Quirinal, upcon which Pope Sixtus V had built his palace.  P.F. confuses the Quirinal and the Capitoline.</note> will wee make good cheare in spight of the Pope
&amp; al his fat abbie lubbers.  His spirit hearing this, departed towards the
Popes chamber, where he found the yet sitting and quaffing: wherefore he tooke
from before the Pope the fairest peece of plate or drinking goblet, &amp; a
flaggon of wine, &amp; brought <milestone n="37" unit="BMP"/> it to <name>Faustus</name>; but when the
Pope and the rest of his crue perceiued they were robbed, and knew not after
what sort, they perswaded themselues that it was the damned soule that before
had vexed the Pope so, &amp; that smote him on the face, wherefore he sent
commandement through al the whole Citie of <name>Rome</name>, that they should say
Masse in euery Church, and ring al the bels for to lay the walking Spirit,
&amp; to curse him with Bel, Booke, and Candle, that so inuisiblie had misused
the Popes holinesse, with the Cardinall of <name>Pauia</name>, and the rest of their
company: but <name>Faustus</name> notwithstanding made good cheare with yt which he
had beguiled ye pope of, and in the middest of the order of Saint <name>Barnards</name>
bare footed Friers, as they were going on Procession through the market
place, called <name>Campa de fiore</name>, he let fall his plate dishes and cup, and
withall for a farwell he made such a thunder-clap and a storme of raine, as
though Heauen and earth should haue met together, and so he left <name>Rome</name>,
</seg>
<!-- <link targets="c14 aa15 bb16"> -->

and came to <name>Millain</name> in <name>Italie</name>, neere the Alpes or borders of
<name>Switzerland</name>, where hee praysed much to his Spirit the pleasantnesse of
the place, the Citie being founded in so braue a plaine, by the which ranne
most pleasant riuers on euery side of the same, hauing besides within the
compasse or circuit of seuen miles, seuen small Seas: he sawe also therein
many fayre Pallaces &amp; goodly buildings, the Dukes Pallace, and the mighty
strong Castle, which is in maner halfe the bignes of the towne.  Moreouer, it
liked him well to see the Hospitall of Saint <name>Maryes</name>, with diuers other
things.  He did

nothing there worthy of memorie, but hee departed backe agayne towards
<name>Bolognia</name>, and from thence to <name>Florence</name>, where hee was well pleased
to see the pleas[a]nt walke of Merchants, the goodly vaults of the citie, for
that almost the whole City is vaulted, &amp; the houses themselues are built
outwardly, in such sort that the people may go vnder them as vnder a vault:
then hee perused the sumptuous Church in the Dukes Castle called <name>Nostra
Donna</name>, our Ladies Church, in which he saw many monuments, as a Marble doore
most huge to looke vpon: the gate of the Castle was Bell mettall, wherein are
grauen the holy Patriarkes, with Christ and his twelue Apostles, and diuers
other histories out of the olde and new Testament.  Then went he to <name>Sena</name>,
where he highly praysed the church and Hospital of <name>Santa Maria formosa</name>,
with the goodly <seg id="n91">buildings</seg>,<note target="n91" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'buidings.'</note> and especially the fayrenesse and greatnesse of
the Citie, and beautifull women.  Then came he to <name>Lyons</name> in <name>France</name>,
where hee marked the scituation of the Citie, which lay betweene two
hilles, inuironed with two waters: one worthy monument in the citie pleased him
wel, that was the great Church with the Image therm; he comended ye <milestone n="38" unit="BMP"/>
Citie highly for the great resort that it had vnto it of strangers.  From
thence he went to <seg id="n92"><name>Cullin</name></seg>,<note target="n92" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Cologne</note> which lieth vpon the Riuer of <name>Rhine</name>,
wherein he saw one of the auncientest monuments of the worlde, the which
was the Tombe of the three Kings that came by the Angel of God, &amp; their
knowledge they had in the starre, to worship Christ: which when <name>Faustus</name>
saw, he spake in this manner.  Ah, alas good men how haue you erred and
lost your way, you should haue gone to <name>Palestina</name> and <name>Bethelem</name> in
<name>Judea</name>, how came you hither': or belike after your death you were throwne
into <name>Mare Mediterraneum</name> about <name>Tripolis</name> in <name>Syria</name>; and so
you <seg id="n93">fleeted</seg>,<note target="n93" type="gloss" anchored="yes">floated</note> out of the Straights of <name>Giblaterra</name> into the Ocean Sea,
and so into the bay of <name>Portugal</name>; &amp; not finding any rest you were
driuen alongst the coast of <name>Galicia, Biskay</name>, and <name>France</name>, and into
the narrow Seas, then from thence into <name>Mare Germanicum</name>, and so I think
taken vp abotit the towne of <name>Dort</name> in <name>Holland</name>, you were brought to
<name>Cullin</name> to bee buried: or else I think you came more easily with a
whirle-wind ouer the Alpes, and being

throwne into the Riuer of <name>Rhine</name>, it conuayed you to this place, where
you are kept as a monument?  There sawe he the Church of S. <name>Vrsula</name>,
where remaines a monument of the 1000. Virgins: it pleased him also to see
the beauty of the women. Not farre from <name>Cullin</name> lyeth the towne of
<seg id="n94"><name>Ach</name></seg>,<note target="n94" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Aix-la-Chapelle</note> where he saw the gorgeous Temple that the Emperour <name>Carolus
quartus</name> built of Marble stone for a remembrance of him, to the end that all
his successors should there be crowned. From <name>Cullin</name> and <name>Ach</name>, he
went to <seg id="n95"><name>Genf</name></seg>,<note target="n95" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'Geuf.'</note> a Citie in <name>Sauoy</name>, lying neere <name>Switzerland</name>:
it is a towne of great trafficke, the Lorde thereof is a Bishop, whose
Wine-celler <name>Faustus</name>, and his Spirit visited for the loue of his good
wine.  From thence he went to <name>Strasburg</name>, where he beheld the fayrest
steeple that euer he had seene in his life before, for on each side therof he
might see through it, euen from the couering of the Minister to the top of the
Pinacle, and it is named one of the wonders of the worlde: wherefore he
demaunded why it was called <name>Strasburg</name>: his Spirit answered, because it
hath so many high wayes comming to it on euery side, for <name>Stras</name> in Dutch
is a high way, and hereof came the name, yea (sayd <name>Mephostophiles</name>) the
Church which thou so wonderest at, hath more reuenues belonging to it, then the
twelue Dukes of <name>Slesia</name> are worth, for there pertaine vnto this Church
55. Townes, and 463. Villages besides many houses in the Towne.  From hence
went <name>Faustus</name> to <name>Basile</name> in <name>Switzerland</name>, whereas the Riuer
of <name>Rhine</name> runneth thorough the towne, parting the same as the Riuer of
<name>Thames</name> doth <name>London</name>: in this towne of <name>Basile</name> he saw many
rich Monuments, the towne walled with brick, and round about without it goeth a
great trench: <milestone n="39" unit="BMP"/> no Church pleased him but the Iesuites Church, which
was so sumptuouslie builded, and beset full of Alabaster pillers. <name>Faustus</name>
demanded of his Spirite, how it tooke the name of <name>Basyl</name>: his Spirite
made answere and saide, that before this Citie was founded, there vsed a
<name>Basiliscus</name>, a kinde of Serpent, this Serpent killed as many men, women,
and children, as it tooke a sight of: but there was a Knight that made himselfe
a couer of Christall to come ouer his head, and so downe to the ground, and
being first couered with a

blacke cloth, ouer that he put the Christall, and so boidlie went to see the
<name>Basiliscus</name>, and finding the place where he haunted, he expected his
coming, euen before the mouth of her caue: where standing a while, the
<name>Basylike</name> came forth, who, when shee sawe her owne venemous shadowe in
the Christall, shee split in a thousand peeces; wherefore the Knight was
richlie rewarded of the Emperour: after the which the Knight founded this Towne
vpon the place where he had slaine the Serpent, and gaue it the name of
<name>Basyl</name>, in remembrance of his deede.</p>
<p>From <name>Basyl Faustus</name> went to <seg id="n96"><name>Costuitz</name></seg><note target="n96" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Constance. The old name was Kostnitz.  The 'u' is evidently a printer's error.</note> in <name>Sweitz</name>, at the
head of the <name>Rhine</name>, where is a most sumptuous Bridge, that goeth ouer the
<name>Rhine</name>, euen from the gates of the Towne vnto the other side of the
streame: at the head of the Riuer of <name>Rhine</name>, is a small Sea, called of
the <name>Switzers</name> the black Sea, twentie thousand paces long, and fiftie
hundred paces broad. The towne <name>Costuitz</name> tooke the name of this, the
Emperour gaue it to a Clowne for expounding of his riddle, wherefore the Clowne
named the Towne <name>Costuitz</name>, that is in English, cost nothing.  From
<name>Costuitz</name> hee came to <name>Vlme</name>, where hee sawe the sumptuous
Towne-house built by two and fiftie of the ancient Senators of the Citie, it
tooke the name of <name>Vlma</name>, for that the whole land thereabout are full of
Elmes: but <name>Faustus</name> minding to depart from thence, his Spirite saide vnto
him: <name>Faustus</name> thinke on the towne as thou wilt, it hath three Dukedomes
belonging to it, the which they haue bought with readie mon [i] e.  From
<name>Vlme</name>, he came to <seg id="n97"><name>Wartzburg</name></seg><note target="n97" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Wurzburg</note> the chiefest towne in
<name>Frankelandt</name>, wherein the Bishop altogether keepeth his Court, through
the which Towne passeth the Riuer of <name>Mayne</name> that runnes into the
<name>Rhine</name>: thereabout groweth strong and pleasant wine, the which <name>Faustus</name>
wel prooued. The Castle standeth on a hill on the North side of the Towne,
at the foote whereof runneth the Riuer: this Towne is full of beggerlie Fryers,
Nunnes, Priestes, and lesuites: for there are flue sortes of begging Friers,
besides three Cloysters of Nunnes.  At the foote of the Castle stands a Church,
in the which there is an Alter, where are ingrauen all the foure Elements, and
all the orders and degrees in Heauen, that any

<milestone n="40" unit="BMP"/> man of vnderstanding whosoeuer that hath a sight thereof, will say
that it is the artificiallest thing that euer he beheld.  From thence he went
to <name>Norenberg</name>, whither as he went by the waie, his Spirite enformed him
that the Towne was named of <name>Claudius Tiberius</name> the Sonne of <name>Nero</name>
the Tyrant.  In the Towne are two famous Cathedrall Churches, the one
called Saint <name>Sabolt</name>, the other Saint <name>Laurence</name>; in which Church
hangeth al the reliques of <name>Carolus Magnus</name>, that is his cloake, his hose
and doublet, his sworde and Crowne, his Scepter, and his Apple.  It hath a very
gorgious gilden <term id="n98">Conduit</term><note target="n98" type="gloss" anchored="yes">fountain</note> in the market of Saint <name>Laurence</name>, in which
Conduit, is the speare that thrust our Sauiour into the side, and a peece of
the holy Crosse; the wall is called the fayre wall of <name>Norenberg</name>, and
hath 528. streates, 160. wells, foure great, and two small clockes, sixe great
gates, and two small doores, eleuen stone bridges, twelue small hills, ten
appoynted market places, thirteene <seg id="n99">common hothouses</seg>,<note target="n99" type="gloss" anchored="yes">public bathhouses</note> ten Churches, within the
Towne are thirtie wheeles of water-mills; it hath <seg id="n100">132. tall ships</seg>,<note target="n100" anchored="yes">This Nuremberg navy is a puzzle.  Spies has "132 Hauptmannschafft." Evidently we have either a mistranslation or a misprint.</note> two
mightie Towne walls of hewen stone and earth, with very deepe trenches.  The
walls haue 180. Towers about them, and foure faire platformes, ten
Apothecaries, ten Doctors of the common lawe, foureteene Doctors of Phisicke.
From <name>Norenberg</name>, hee went to <name>Auspurg</name>, where at the breake of the
day, he demaunded of his Spirit wherevpon the Towne tooke his name: this Towne
(saith he) hath had many names, when it was first built, it was called
<name>Vindelica</name>: secondly, it was called <name>Zizaria</name>, the yron bridge:
lastly by the Emperour <name>Octauius Augustus</name>, it was called <name>Augusta</name>,
and by corruption of language the <name>Germanes</name> haue named it <name>Auspurgi</name>
Now for because that <name>Faustus</name> had been there before, he departed
without visiting their monuments to <name>Rauenspurg</name>, where his Spirite
certified him that the Citie had had seuen names, the first <name>Tyberia</name>, the
second <name>Qadratis</name>, the third <name>Hyaspalis</name>, the fourth <name>Reginopolis</name>,
the flift <name>Imbripolis</name>, the sixt <name>Ratisbona</name>, lastly
<name>Rauenspurg</name>. The scituation of the Citie pleased <name>Faustus</name> well,
also the strong and sumptuous buildings: by the walls thereof runneth the Riuer
of <name>Danubia</name>, in Dutch called <name>Donow</name>, into

the which not farre from the compasse of the Citie, falleth nerehand threescore
other small Riuers and fresh waters. <name>Faustus</name> also liked the sumptuous
stone bridge ouer the samec water, with the Church standing thereon, the which
was founded 1115. the name whereof, is called S. <name>Remedian</name>: in this
towne <name>Faustus</name> went into the celler of an Inholder, and let out all the
Wine and Beere that was in his Celler. After the which feat he returned vnto
<seg id="n101"><name>Mentz</name></seg><note target="n101" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Munich</note> in <name>Bauaria</name>, a right prince-<milestone n="41" unit="BMP"/>ly Towne, the Towne
appeared as if it were newe, with great streates therein, both of breadth and
length: from <name>Mentz</name> to <name>Saltzburg</name>, where the Bishop is alwaies
resident: here sawe he all the commodities that were possible to be seene, for
at the hill he sawe the forme of <seg id="n102"><name>Abel</name></seg><note target="n102" anchored="yes">A later text in our possession has "a Bell."</note> made in Christall, an huge
thing to looke vpon, that euery yeare groweth bigger and bigger, by reason of
the freezing colde.  From hence, hee went to <name>Vienna</name>, in <name>Austria</name>:
this towne is of so great antiquitie, that it is not possible to finde the
like in this towne (said the Spirite) is more Wine then water, for all vnder
the towne are wells, the which are filled euery yeare with wine, and all the
water that they haue, runneth by the towne, that is the Riuer <name>Danubia</name>.
From hence, hee went vnto <name>Prage</name>, the chiefe Citie in <name>Bohemia</name>,
this is deuided into three partes, that is, olde <name>Prage</name>, new
<name>Prage</name>, and little <name>Prage</name>. Little <name>Prage</name> is the place where
the Emperours Court is placed vpon an exceeding high mountaine: there is a
Castle, wherein are two fayre Churches, in the one he found a monument, which
might well haue been a mirror to himselfe, and that was the Sepulchre of a
notable Coniurer, which by his Magick had so inchanted his Sepulchre, that who
so euer set foote thereon, should be sure neuer to dye in their beds.  From the
Castell he came downe, and went ouer the Bridge.  This Bridge hath twentie and
foure Arches. In the middle of this Bridge stands a very fayre monument, being
a Crosse builded of stone, and most artificially carued. From thence, he came
into the olde <name>Prage</name>, the which is separated from the new <name>Prage</name>,
with an exceeding deepe ditch, and round about inclosed with a wall of
Bricke<seg id="n103">.</seg><note target="n103" anchored="yes">B.M. has no period.</note>  Vnto this is adioyning the lewes Towne, wherein are thirteene
thousand

men, women, and Children, all lewes.  There he viewed the Colledge and the
Garden, where all manner of sauage Beasts are kept; and from thence, he <term id="n104">fet</term><note target="n104" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Made or fetched.</note> a
compasse rounde about the three townes, whereat he wondred greatly, to see so
mighty a Citie to stand all within the walles.  From <name>Prage</name>, hee flewe
into the ayre and bethought himselfe what hee might doe, or which way to take,
so hee looked round about and beholde, he had espied a passing faire City which
lay not farre from <name>Prage</name>, about some foure &amp; twentie miles, and that
was <name>Breslaw</name> in <name>Sclesia</name>; into which when he was entred, it seemed
to him that hee had been in Paradise, so neate and deane was the streates, and
so sumptuous was their buildings.  In this Citie he sawe not many wonders,
except the Brasen Virgin that standeth on a Bridge ouer the water, &amp; vnder
ye which standeth a mil like a powder mil, which Virgin is made to do executio
vpon those disobedient town-borne children yt be so wilde, yt their parents
canot <milestone n="42" unit="BMP"/> bridle them; which when any such are found with some hainous
offence, turning to the shame of their parents and kindred, they are brought to
kisse this Virgin, which openeth her armes, the person then to bee executed,
kisseth her, then doth she close her armes together with such violence, that
she crusheth out the breath of the person, breaketh his bulke, and so dieth:
but being dead, she openeth her armes againe, and letteth the partie fall into
the Mil, where he is stamped in smal morsels, which the water carrieth away, so
that not any parte of him is found againe. From <name>Breslaw</name> he went toward
<name>Cracouia</name>, in the Kingdome of <name>Polonia</name>, where he beheld the
<name>Academie</name>, the which pleased him wonderful well.  In this Citie the King
most commonly holdeth his Court at a Castel, in which Castell are many famous
monuments.  There is a most sumptuous Church in the same, in which standeth a
siluer alter gilded, and set with rich stones, and ouer it is a conueiance full
of all maner siluer ornaments belonging to the Masse.  In the Church hangeth
the iawe bones of an huge Dragon that kept the Rocke before the Castel was
edified thereon.  It is full of all maner munition, and hath alwaies victual
for three yeare to serue 2000. men.  Through the towne runneth a riuer called
the <name>Vistula</name> or <name>Wissel</name>, where ouer is a faire woodden bridge.
This water

deuideth the towne and <name>Casmere</name>, in this <name>Casmere</name> dwelleth the
Iewes being a small walled towne by themselues, to the number of 25000. men,
women, and Children.  Within one mile of the towne there is a salte mine, where
they finde stones of pure salte of a 1000. pound, or 900. pound, or more in
waight, and that in great quantitie. This salte is as black as the <name>Newcastle</name>
coales when it comes out of the mines, but being beaten to powder, it is as
white as snowe. The like they haue foure mile from thence, at a towne called
<name>Buchnia</name>. From thence, <name>Faustus</name> went to <name>Sandetz</name>, the
Captaine thereof was called <name>Don Spiket Jordan</name>, in this towne are many
monuments as the tombe or sepulchre of Christ, in as ample maner as that is at
<name>Ierusalem</name>) at the proper costs of a Gentleman that went thrice to
<name>Ierusalem</name> from that place, and returned againe. Not far from that towne
is a new towne, wherein is a Nunrie of the order of Saint <name>Dioclesian</name>,
into which order may none come, except they be Gentlewomen, and well formed
and faire to looke vpon, the which pleased <name>Faustus</name> well: but hauing a
desire to trauaile farther, and to see more wonders, mounting vp towards the
East, ouer many lands and prouinces, as into <name>Hungaria</name>, <name>Transiluania</name>, <name id="n105">Shede,
Ingratz</name>,<note target="n105" anchored="yes">'Shede' and 'Ingratz.'  Our search for these places on old maps has yielded nothing positive.  Strabo has a Schedia, a village port in Lower Egypt.</note> <name>Sardinia</name>, and so into <name>Constantinople</name>, where the Turkish
Emperor kept his Court.  This Citie was surnamed by <name>Constantine</name> the
founder thereof, being builded of very faire stone.  In the same <milestone n="43" unit="BMP"/> the
great Turke hath three faire Pallaces, the wals are strong, the pinnacles are
very huge, and the streetes large: but this liked not <name>Faustus</name>, that one
man mightc haue so many wiues as he would. The Sea runneth hard by the Citie,
the wall hath eleuen Gates: <name>Faustus</name> abode there a certaine time to see
the manner of the Turkish Emperours seruice at his table, where hee saw his
royall seruice to bee such, that bee thought if all the Christian Princes
should banquet together, and euery one adorne the feast to the vttermost, they
were not able to compare with the Turke for his table, and the rest of his
Countrey seruice, wherefore it so spighted <name>Faustus</name>, that hee vowed to
bee reuenged of him, for his pompe he thought was more fit for himselfe:
wherefore as the Turke sate and eate, <name>Faustus</name> shewed him a little apish
play: for rounde about

the priuie Chamber, he sent foorth flashing flames of fire, in so much, that the whole company forsooke their meate and fled, except onely the great Turke himselfe, him <name>Faustus</name> had charmed in such sorte, that hee could neither rise nor fall, neither could any man pull him vp.  With this was the Hall so
light, as if the Sunne had shined in the house, then came <name>Faustus</name> in
forme of a Pope to the great Turke, saying, all haile Emperour, now art thou
honoured that I so worthily appeare vnto thee as thy <name>Mahumet</name> was wont to
doe, herevpon he vanished, and forthwith it so thundred, that the whole Pallace
shooke: the Turke greatly merueiled what this should bee that so vexed him,
and was perswaded by his chiefest counsailers, that it was <name>Mahumet</name> his
Prophet, the which had so appeared vnto them, wherevpon the Turke commaunded
them to fal downe on their knees, and to giue him thankes for dooing them so
great honor, as to shew himselfe vnto them; but the next day <name>Faustus</name>
went into the Castell where hee kept his Wiues and Concubines, in the which
Castel might no man vpon paine of death come, except those that were appointed
by the great Turke to doo them seruice, and they were all gelded, Which when
<name>Faustus</name> perceiued, he said to his Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name>, how
likest thou this sport, are not these faire Ladies greatly to be pitied, that
thus consume their youth at the pleasure of one onely man?  Why (quoth the
Spirit) maiest not thou instead of the Emperor, imbrace his fairest Ladies, doe
what thy heart desireth herein, and I will aide thee, and what thou wishest,
thou shalt haue it performed: wherefore <name>Faustus</name> (being before this
counsaile apt enough to put such matters in practize) caused a great fogge to
bee round about the Castell, both within and without, and he himselfe appeared
amongst the Ladies in all things as they vse to paint their <name>Mahumet</name>, at
which sight, the Ladies fell on their knees, and <milestone n="44" unit="BMP"/> worshipped him, then
<name>Faustus</name> tooke the fairest by the hand, and led her into a chamber, where
after his maner hee fell to dalliance, and thus he continued a whole day and
night: and when hee had delighted himselfe sufficiently with her, hee put her
away, and made his spirite bring him another, so likewise hee kept with her 24.
houres play, causing his spirit to fetch him most dainty fare, and so bee
passed way sixe daies, hauing each day his pleasure of a sundry Lady, and that
of the fairest, all which time, the fog was so thick, and so stinking, that
they within the house thought they had been in hell, for the time, and they
without wondred thereat, in such sort, that they went to their praiers calling
on their God <name>Mahumet</name>, and worshipping of his Image.  Wherfore the sixt
day <name>Faustus</name> exalted himselfe in the ayre, like to a Pope, in the sight
of the great Turke and his people, and hee had no sooner departed the Castell,
but the fogge vanished away, whence presently the Turke sent for his Wiues and
Concubines, demanding of them if they knew the cause why the Castell was beset
with a mist so long': they said, that it was the God <name>Mahumet</name> himselfe
that caused it, and how he was in the Castell personally full sixe daies, and
for more certaintie, he hath lien with sixe of vs these sixe nights one after
another.  Wherefore the Turke hearing this fell on his knees, and gaue
<name>Mahumet</name> thanks, desiring him to forgiue him for being offended with his
visiting his Castel and wiues those sixe dayes: but the Turke commanded that
those whome <name>Mahumet</name> had laine by, should bee most carefully looked vnto,
perswading himselfe (and so did the whole people that knewe of it) that out of
their <name>Mahumet</name> should be raised a mighty generation, but first he
demaunded of the sixe Ladies if <name>Mahumet</name> had had actuall copulation with
them, according as earthly men haue, yea my Lorde quoth one, as if you had been
there your selfe, you could not haue mended it, for hee lay with vs starke
naked, kissed and colled vs, and so delighted me, yt for my part, I would hee
came two or three times a week to serue me in such sort againe.  From hence,
<name>Faustus</name> went to <name>Alkar</name>, the which before time was called
<seg id="n106"><name>Chairam</name> or <name>Memphis</name></seg>,<note target="n106" anchored="yes">'Chairam, or Memphis.'  The confusion in names goes back to Schedel's <name>Chroisik</name>, where there is a picture (fol. XXII) labeled Memphis vel Chayrum. The descriptive paragraph identifies the two places.</note> in this Citie the Egiptian Souldane holdeth
his Court.  From hence the riuer <name>Nilus</name> hath his first head and spring,
it is the greatest fresh-water riuer that is in the whole world, and alwaies
when the Sunne is in <name>Cancer</name>, it ouerfloweth the whole land of <name>Egypt</name>:
then hee returned againe towards the North-east, and to the towne of
<seg id="n107"><name>Ofen</name></seg><note target="n107" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Budapest</note> and <seg id="n108"><name>Sabatz</name></seg> <note target="n108" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Possibly Sabac in Jugoslavia, 39 miles west of Belgrade.</note> in <name>Hungaria</name>. This <name>Ofen</name> is the
chiefest Citie in <name>Hungaria</name>, and

standeth in a fertile soyle, wherein groweth most excellent wine, and not farre
from the Towne there is a wel, called <seg id="n109"><name>Zipzar</name></seg>,<note target="n109" anchored="yes">Logeman suggests that this name is erroneously derived from the German adjective "Zipser," i.e., of Zips, a district north of Budapest.</note> the water whereof
changeth yron <milestone n="45" unit="BMP"/> into Copper: here are mines of gold and siluer, and all
maner of mettall, we <name>Germains</name> call this towne <name>Ofen</name>, but in the
<name>Hungarian</name> speech it is <seg id="n110"><name>Start</name></seg><note target="n110" anchored="yes">'start.'  An error copied by P.F. from Spies.  The error goes back to Schedel's <name>Chronik</name> where 'start' is a misprint for 'statt,' city.</note> In the towne standeth a very
faire Castell, and very well fortified.  From hence he went to <name>Austria</name>,
and through <name>Slesia</name> into <name>Saxony</name>, vnto the townes of
<name>Magdeburg</name> and <name>Liptzig</name>, and <name>Lubeck. Magdeburg</name> is a
Bishoprick: in this Citie is one of the pitchers wherein Christ changed the
water into wine at <name>Cana</name> in <name>Galile</name>. At <name>Liptzig</name> nothing
pleased <name>Faustus</name> so well as the great vessell in the Castell made of
wood, the which is bounde about with 24. yron hoopes, and euery hoope waieth 200. pound waight, they must goe vpon a ladder of 30. steps high before they
can looke into it: hee saw also the new church-yard, where it is walled, and
standeth vpon a faire plaine, the yard is 200. paces long, and round about in
the inside of the wall, are goodly places seperated one from each other to see
sepulchers in, which in the middle of the yard standeth very sumptuous: therein
standeth a pulpit of white worke and golde.  From hence hee came to <name>Lubeck</name>
and <name>Hamburg</name>, where he made no abode, but away againe to <name>Erfort</name>
in <name>Duringen</name>, where he visited the <seg id="n111"><name>Freskold</name></seg>,<note target="n111" anchored="yes">Possibly 'frescade,' according to N.E.D. 'a cool walk; a shady alley.' Logeman suggests 'fresco' but neither conjecture explains the reference.</note> and from
<name>Erfort</name> hee went home to <name>Wittenberg</name>, when he had seene and visited
many a strange place, being from home one yeare and a halfe, in which time he
wrought more wonders than are here declared.</p><p></p>
</div2>

<div2 n="23" type="chapter" id="chap23">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Faustus had a sight of Paradise.</hi> Chap. 23.</head>
<p>AFter this, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> set forth againe, visited these countries of
<name>Spaine</name>, <name>Portugal</name>, <name>France</name>, <name>England</name>, <name>Scotland</name>, <name>Denmark</name>, <name>Sweden</name>, <name>Poland</name>,
<name>Muscouy</name>, <name>India</name>, <name id="n112">Cataia</name>,<note target="n112" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Cathay.</note> <name>Africa</name>, <name>Persia</name>, and lastly into <name>Barbaria</name>
amongst the <name>Blacke mores</name>, and

The belief in the extraordinary virtues of Hungarian springs was widespread.</p><p>The springs actually contained copper which was precipitated by the iron.</p><p>
in all his wandring he was desirous to visit the auncient monuments and mighty
hils, amongst the rest beholding the high hill called the <name>Treno Riefe</name>,
was desirous to rest vpon it: from thence hee went into the Isle of
<name>Brittany</name>, wherein hee was greatly delighted to see the faire water and
warme Bathes, the diuers sorts of mettall, with many pretious stones, and
diuers other commodities the which <name>Faustus</name> brought thence with him, hee
was also at the <name>Orchades</name> behinde <name>Scotland</name>, where hee saw the tree
that bringeth forth fruite, that when it is ripe, openeth and falleth into the
water, whereof ingendreth a certaine kinde of Fowle or Birde: these Islands
are in number 23. but 10. of them are not habitable, the other 13. are
inhabited: from hence, he went to the hill of <name>Caucasus</name>, which is the
highest in all that <name>Tropek</name>, it lieth nere y borders <milestone n="46" unit="BMP"/> of
<name>Scythia</name>, hereon <name>Faustus</name> stoode and beheld many lands and
kingdomes. <name>Faustus</name> being on such an high hill, thought to looke ouer all
the world and beyond, for he ment to see Paradise, but he durst not commune
with his Spirit thereof: and being on the hill of <name>Caucasus</name>, hee sawe
the whole lande of <name>India</name> and <name>Scythia</name>, and towards the East as hee
looked he sawe a mightie cleare <term id="n113">strike</term><note target="n113" type="gloss" anchored="yes">streak</note> of fire comming from heauen vpon the
earth, euen as it had been one of the beames of the Sunne, he sawe in the
valley foure mighty waters springing, one had his course towards <name>India</name>,
the second towards <name>Egypt</name>, the third &amp; fourth towards <name>Armenia</name>.
When he saw these, he would needes knowe of his Spirit what waters they
were, and from whence they came.  His Spirite gaue him gently an answere,
saying; it is Paradise that lieth so farre in the East, the garden that God
himselfe hath planted with all maner of pleasure, and the fine streame that
thou seest, is the walles or defence of the garden, but that cleare light that
thou seest so farre off, is the Angell that hath the custodie thereof, with a
fierie sworde: and although that thou thinkest thy selfe to bee hard by, thou
hast yet farther thither from hence, then thou hast euer been:  the water that
thou seest deuided in foure partes, is the water that issueth out of the Well
in the middle of Paradise.  The first is called <name>Ganges</name> or <name>Phison</name>,
the second, <name>Gihon</name> or <name>Nilus</name>, the third <name>Tigris</name>, and the
fourth <name>Euphrates</name>, also thou seest that.. hee standeth vnder <name>Libra</name>
and <name>Aries</name> right vp towards the

<name>Zenith</name>, and vpon this fine wall standeth the Angell <name>Michael</name> with
his flaming sword to keep the tree of life the which he hath in charge; but the
Spirite said vnto <name>Faustus</name>, neither thou, nor I, nor any after vs, yea
all men whosoeuer are denied to visite it, or to come any nearer then we be.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="24" type="chapter" id="chap24">
<head><hi rend="ital">Of a certaine Comet that appeared in Germanie, and how Doctor Faustus was desired by certaine friends of his to knowe the meaning thereof.</hi> Chap. 24.</head>
<p>IN <name>Germanie</name> ouer the Towne of <seg id="n114"><name>S. Eizleben</name></seg>.<note target="n114" anchored="yes">The S., usual abbreviation for 'Saint,' is probably a misprint.</note> was seene a mightie
great Comet, whereat the people wondered; but Doctor <name>Faustus</name> being
there, was asked of certaine of his friends his iudgement or opinion in the
matter.  Wherevpon hee answered, it falleth out often by the course and change
of the Sunne and Moone, that the Sunne is vnder the earth, and the Moone aboue;
but when the Moone draweth neere the change, then is the Sunne so strong that
bee taketh away all the light of the Moone, in such sorte that he is as red as
blood: <milestone n="47" unit="BMP"/> and to the contrary, after they haue been together, the Moone
taketh her light againe from him, and so increasing in light to the full, shee
will be as red as the Sun was before, and changeth herselfe into diuers and
sundry colours, of the which springeth a prodygious monster, or as you call it,
a Comet, which is a figure or token appoynted of God as a forewarning of his
displeasure: as at one time hee sendeth hunger, plague, sword, or such like:
being all tokens of his iudgement: the which Comet commeth through the
coniunction of the Sun &amp; Moone begetting a monster, whose father is the
Sunne, and whose mother is the Moone,   and.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="25" type="chapter" id="chap25">
<head><hi rend="ital">A question put foorth to Doctor Faustus, concerning the Starres.</hi> Chap. 25.</head>
<p>THere was a learned man of the towne of <name>Halberstat</name>, named <name>N. V. W</name>.
inuited Doctor <name>Faustus</name> to his table, but falling into communication
before supper was ready, they looked out of the windowe, and seeing many
starres in the firmament, this man being a Doctor of Phisick and a good
Astrologian, sayd:

Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, I haue inuited you as my guest, hoping that you will
take it in good part with me, and withall I request you to impart vnto me some
of your experience in the Starres and Planets.  And seeing a Starre fall, hee
said: I pray you <name>Faustus</name>, what is the condition, qualitie, or greatnes
of the Starres in the firmament': <name>Faustus</name> answered him: My friend and
Brother, you see that the Starres that fal from heauen when they come on y
earth they be very smal to our thinking as cadles, but being fixed in the
firmament there are many as great as this Citie, some as great as a Prouince or
Dukedome, other as great as the whole earth, other some farre greater then the
earth: for the length &amp; breadth of the heauens is greater than the earth
twelue times, and from the height of the Heauens there is scarce any earth to
be seene, yea the Planets in the heauens are some so great as this land, some
so great as the whole Empire of <name>Rome</name>, some as <name>Turkie</name>, yea one so
great as the whole world.</p><p>
<milestone n="48" unit="BMP"/> </p>
</div2>

<div2 n="26" type="chapter" id="chap26">
<head><hi rend="ital">Howe Faustus was asked a question concernmg the Spirites that vexe men.</hi> Chap. 26.</head>
<p>THat is most true (sayth hee to <name>Faustus</name>) concerning the starres and
planets: but I pray you in what kinde or maner doe the spirites vse or vexe men
so little by day, and so greatly by night': Doctor <name>Faustus</name> answered:
because the spirits are by GOD forbidden the light, their dwelling is in
darknesse, and the clearer the Sunne shineth, the further the Spirits haue
their abiding from it, but in the night when it is darke, they haue their
familiaritie and abiding neere vnto vs men.  For although in the night we see
not the Sunne, yet the brightnes thereof so lightneth the first mouing of the
firmament as it doth yt on earth in the day, by which reason we are able to see
the stars and Planets in the night, euen so the rayes of the Sunne pearcing
vpwards into the firmament, the Spirits abandon the place, and so come neere vs
on earth in the darknes, filling our heads with heauy dreames and fond
fantasies, with schriching94 and crying in many deformed shapes: as sometimes
when men go forth without light, there falleth to them a feare, that their
hayre standeth an end, so many start in their sleepe thinking there is a Spirit
by him, gropeth or feeleth for</p><p>94 screaching</p><p>him, going round about the house in his sleep, &amp; many such like fantasies:
and all this is for because that in the night the Spirits are more familiarly
by vs than we are desirous of their company, and so they cary vs, blinding vs
and plaguing vs more than we are able to perceiue.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="27" type="chapter" id="chap27">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus was asked a question concerning the Starres that fall from Heauen,</hi> Chap. 27.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> being demanded the cause why the Starres fell from
Heauen, he answered: that is but our opinion; for if one Starre fall, it is
the great iudgement of God vpon vs, as aforewarning of some great thing to come
: for when we thinke that a Star falleth, it is but as a sparke that issueth
from a candle or a flame of fire, for if it were a substantiall thing, we
should not so soone loose the sight of them as we doo. And likewise, if so be
that we see as it were a streame of fire fall from the firmament, as oft it
happeneth, yet are they no Starres, but as it were a flame of fire vanishing,
but the Starres are substantiall, therefore are they firme and not falling: if
<milestone n="49" unit="BMP"/> there fall any, it is a signe of some great matter to come, as a
scourge to a people or countrey, and then such Starre falling, the gates of
heauen are opened, and the cloudes send foorth floods, or other plagues, to the
dammage of the whole land and people.</p><p></p>
</div2>

<div2 n="28" type="chapter" id="chap28">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Faustus was asked a question as concerning thunder.</hi> Chap. 28.</head>
<p>IN the moneth of August, there was ouer <name>Wittenberg</name> a mighty great
lightning and thunder, and as Doctor <name>Faustus</name> was iesting merily in the
market place with certaine of his friends and companions being Phisitc[i]os,
they desired him to tel them the cause of that weather. <name>Faustus</name> answered
: it hath beene commonly seene heretofore, that before a thunderclap fell a
showre of raine or a gale of winde, for commonly after a winde followeth a
raine, and after a rayne a thunderclap: such things come to passe when the
foure windes meete together in the heauens, the ayrie cloudes are by force
beate against the fixed chrystallin firmament, but when the ayrie cloudes meet
with the firmament they are congealed, and so strike &amp; rush against the
firmament, as great peeces of yce when they meet on the water, the eccho
thereof soundeth in our eares, and that we call thunder, which indeede is none
other than you haue heard.</p><p></p></div2>
</div1>
<div1 n="3" type="part">
<head>The third and last part, of Doctor Faustus his mery conceits, shewing after
what sort he practised Nicromancie in the Courts of great Princes, and lastly of his fearfull and pitifull ende.</head>

<div2 n="29" type="chapter" id="chap29">
<head><hi rend="ital">How the Emperour Carolus quintus requested of Faustus to see some of his cunning, whereunto he agreed.</hi> Chap. 29.</head>
<p>THe Emperour <name>Carolus</name> the fifth of that name was personally with the rest
of his Nobles and gentlemen at the towne of <name>Inszbruck</name> where he kept his
court, vnto the which also Doctor <name>Faustus</name> resorted, and being there well
knowne of diuers Nobles &amp; gentlemen, he was inuited into the court to meat,
euen in the presence of the Emperour: whom when the Emperour saw, hee looked
earnestly on him, thinking him by his looks to be some wonderfull fellow,
wherfore he asked one of his Nobles whom he should be: who answered that he was
called Doctor <name>Faustus</name>. Whereupon the Emperour held his peace <milestone n="50" unit="BMP"/>
vntill he had taken his repast, after which hee called vnto him <name>Faustus</name>,
into the priuie chamber, whither being come, he sayd vnto him: <name>Faustus</name>,
I haue heard much of thee, that thou art excellent in the black Arte, and
none like thee in mine Empire, for men say that thou hast a familiar Spirit
with thee &amp; that thou canst do what thou list: it is therefore (saith the
Emperour) my request of thee that thou let me see a proofe of thine experience,
and I vowe vnto thee by the honour of mine Emperiall Crowne, none euill shall
happen vnto thee for so dooing.  Herevpon Doctor <name>Faustus</name> answered his
Maiestie, that vpon those conditions he was ready in any thing that he could,
to doe his highnes commaundement in what seruice he would appoynt him.  Wel,
then heare what I say (quoth the Emperour.)  Being once solitarie in my house,
I called to mind mine elders and auncesters, how it was possible for them to
attaine vnto so great a degree of authoritie, yea so high, that wee the
successors of that line are neuer able to come neere.  As for example, the
great and mighty monarch of the worlde <name>Alexander magnus</name>, was such a
lanterne &amp; spectacle to all his successors, as the Cronicles makes mention
of so great riches, conquering, and subduing so many king-domes, the which I
and those that follow me (I feare) shall neuer bee able to attaine vnto:
wherefore, <name>Faustus</name>, my hearty desire is that thou wouldst vouchsafe to
let me see that <name>Alexander</name>, and his Paramour, the which was praysed to be
so fayre, and I pray thee shew me them in such sort that I may see their
personages, shape, gesture &amp; apparel, as they vsed in their life time, and
that here before my face; to the ende that I may say I haue my long desire
fulfilled, &amp; to prayse thee to be a famous man in thine arte and
experience.  Doctor <name>Faustus</name> answered: My most excellent Lord, I am ready
to accomplish your request in all things, so farre foorth as I and my Spirit
are able to performe: yet your Maiestie shall know, that their dead bodies are
not able substantially to be brought before you, but such Spirits as haue seene
<name>Alexander</name> and his Paramour aliue, shall appeare vnto you in manner and
forme as they both hued in their most florishing time: and herewith I hope to
please your imperiall Maiestie.  Then <name>Faustus</name> went a little aside to
speake to his Spirit, but he returned againe presently, saying: now if it
please your Maiesty you shall see them, yet vpon this condition that you
demaund no question of them, nor speake vnto them, which the Emperour agreed
vnto.  Wherewith Doctor <name>Faustus</name> opened the priuy chamber doore, where
presently entred the great and mighty Emperour <name>Alexander magnus</name>, in all
things to looke vpon as if he had been a-<milestone n="51" unit="BMP"/> liue, in proportion a strong
thick set man, of a middle stature, blacke hayre, and that both thick and
curled head and beard, red cheekes, and a broade face, with eyes like a
<name>Basiliske</name>, hee had on a complet harnesse burnished and grauen exceeding
rich to looke vpon; and so passing towards the Emperour <name>Carolus</name>, he made
lowe and reuerent curtesie: whereat the Emperour <name>Carolus</name> would haue
stoode vp to receiue and greete him with the like reuerence, but <name>Faustus</name>
tooke holde of him and would not permit him to doe it. Shortly after
<name>Alexander</name> made humble reuerence and went out againe, and comming to the
doore his Paramour met him, she comming in, she made the Emperour likewise
reuerence, she was clothed in blew Veluet, wrought and embrodered with pearle
and golde, she was also excellent fayre like Milke &amp; blood mixed, tall and
slender, with a face round as an Apple) and thus shee passed certaine times vp
and downe the house, which the Emperour marking, sayd to himselfe: now haue I
seene two persons, which my heart hath long wished for to beholde, and sure it
cannot otherwise be, sayd he to himselfe, but that the Spirits haue changed
themselues into these formes, and haue not deceiued me, calling to his minde
the woman that raysed the Prophet <name>Samuel</name>: and for that the Emperour
would be the more satisfied in the matter, he thought, I haue heard say, that
behinde her necke she had a great wart or wenne, wherefore he tooke <name>Faustus</name>
by the hand without any words, and went to see if it were also to be seen
on her or not, but she perceiuing that he came to her, bowed downe her neck,
where he saw a great wart, and hereupon shee vanished, leauing the Emperour and
the rest well contented.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<!-- <link targets="chap29 aa17 bb19"> -->

<div2 n="30" type="chapter" id="chap30">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus in the sight of the Emperour coniured a payre of Harts hornes vpon a Knights head that slept out of a cazement.</hi> Chap. 30.</head>
<p>WHen Doctor <name>Faustus</name> had accomplished the Emperours desire in all things
as he was requested, he went foorth into a gallerie, and leaning ouer a rayle
to looke into the priuie garden, he saw many of the Emperours Courtiers walking
and talking together, and casting his eyes now this way, now that way, he
espyed a Knight leaning out at a window of the great hall; who was fast asleepe
(for in those dayes it was hote) but the person shall bee namelesse that slept,
for that he was a Knight, although it was done to <milestone n="52" unit="BMP"/> a little disgrace
of the Gentleman: it pleased Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, through the helpe of his
Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name>, to <term id="n115">firme</term><note target="n115" type="gloss" anchored="yes">fasten</note> vpon his head as hee slept, an huge
payre of Harts hornes, and as the Knight awaked thinking to pul in his head,
hee hit his homes against the glasse that the panes therof flew about his
eares.  Think here how this good Gentleman was vexed, for he could neither get
backward nor forward: which when the Emperour heard al the courtiers laugh, and
came forth to see what was hapened, the Emperour also whe he beheld the Knight
with so fayre

a head, laughed heartily thereat, and was therewithall well pleased: at last
<name>Faustus</name>, made him quite of his hornes agayne, but the Knight perceiued
how they came, &amp;c.
</p>
</div2>

<!-- <link targets="chap30 bb20 bb21 aa18"> -->

<div2 n="31" type="chapter" id="chap31">
<head><hi rend="ital">How the aboue mentioned Knight went about to be reuenged of Doctor Faustus.</hi> Chap. 31.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> tooke his leaue of the Emperour and the rest of the
Courtiers, at whose departure they were sory, giuing him many rewards and
gifts: but being a league and a halfe from the Citie he came into a Wood, where
he beheld the Knight that hee had iested with at the Court with other in
harnesse, mounted on fayre palfrayes, and running with full charge towards
<name>Faustus</name>, but he seeing their intent, ran towards the bushes, and before
he came amongst the bushes he returned againe, running as it were to meet them
that chased him, wherupon sodainly al the bushes were turned into horsemen,
which also ran to incouter with the Knight &amp; his company, &amp; comming to
the, they closed the Knight and the rest, &amp; told them that they must pay
their ransome before they departed. Whereupon the Knight seeing himselfe in
such distresse, besought <name>Faustus</name> to be good to them, which he denied
not, but let them lose, yet he so charmed them, that euery one, Knight &amp;
other for the space of a whole moneth did weare a payre of Goates homes on
their browes, and euery Palfray a payre of Oxe homes on their head: and this
was their penance appoynted by <name>Faustus</name>, &amp;c.</p><p>

<!-- <link targets="chap31 bb22"> -->
</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="32" type="chapter" id="chap32">
<head><hi rend="ital">How three young Dukes being together at Wittenberg to behold the Vniuersitie, requested Faustus to help them at a wish to the towne of Menchen in Bauaria, there to see the Duke of Bauaria his sonnes wedding.</hi> Chap. 32.</head>
<p>THree worthy young Dukes, the which are not here to bee named, but being
students altogether at the Vniuersitie of <name>Wittenberg</name>, <milestone n="53" unit="BMP"/> met on a
time altogether, where they fell to reasoning concerning the pompe and brauery
that would be at the Citie of <name>Menchen</name> in <name>Bauaria</name>, at the wedding
of the Dukes Sonne, wishing themselues there but one halfe houre, to see the
manner of their iollity: to whom one replied, saying to the other two
Gentlemen, if it please you to giue mee the hearing, I will giue you good
counsell that we may see the wedding, and be here againe to night, and this is
my meaning; let vs send to Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, make him a present of some
rare thing and so open our mindes vnto him, desiring him to assist vs in our
enterprise, and assure ye he will not denie to fulfill our request.  Hereupon
they al concluded, sent for <name>Faustus</name>, tolde him their minde, and gaue him
a gift, and inuited him to a sumptuous banquet, wherewith <name>Faustus</name> was
well contented, and promised to further their iourney to the vttermost. And
when the time was come that the Duke his sonne should be married, Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> called vnto him the three young Gentlemen into his house,
commaunding them that they should put on their best apparell, and adorne
themselues as richly as they could, he tooke off his owne great large cloke,
went into a garde that was adioyning vnto his house, and set the three young
Dukes on his cloke, and he himselfe sate in the middest, but hee gaue them in
charge that in any wise they should not once open their mouthes to speak, or
make answere to any man so soone as they were out, no not so much as if the
Duke of <name>Bauaria</name> or his Son should speake to them, or offer them
courtesie, they should giue no word or answere agayne, to the which they all
agreed. These conditions being made, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> began to coniure,
and on a sodayne arose a mightie winde, heauing vp the cloke, and so carried
them away in the ayre, &amp; in due time they came vnto <name>Menchen</name> to y
Dukes Court, where being entred into the outmost court, the Marshall had espied
them, who presently went to the Duke, shewing his Grace that all the Lords and
gentlemen were already set at the table, notwithstanding, there were newly come
three goodly Gentlemen with one seruant, the which stoode without in the court,
wherefore the good old Duke came out vnto them, welcomming them, requiring what
they were, &amp; whence: but they made no answere at all, whereat the Duke
wondred, thinking they were all foure dumbe; notwithstanding for his honor sake
hee tooke them into his court, and feasted them. <name>Faustus</name> notwithstanding
spake to the~, if any thing happen otherwise then wel, when I say, sit vp, the~
fal you al on the cloke, &amp; good inough: wel, the water being brought, &amp;
that they must wash, one of the three had so much maners as to desire <milestone n="54" unit="BMP"/>
his friend to wash first, which when <name>Faustus</name> heard, he said, sit vp, and
all at once they got on the cloke, but he that spake fell off againe, the other
two with Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, were againe presently at <name>Wittenberg</name>, but
he that remayned, was taken and layde in Prison: wherefore the other two
Gentlemen were very sorrowfull for their friend, but <name>Faustus</name> comforted
them, promising that on the morrow he should also be at <name>Wittenberg</name>. Now
all this while was this Duke taken in a great feare, and striken into an
exceeding dump, wondring with himselfe that his hap was so hard to be left
behinde, and not the rest, and now being locked &amp; watched with so many
keepers, there was also certaine of the guests that fell to reasoning with him
to know what hee was, and also what the other were that were vanished away, but
the poore prisoner thought with himselfe, if I open what they are, then it will
be euill also with me:</p><p>wherefore all this while he gaue no man any answere, so that he was there a
whole day, and gaue no man a word.  Wherefore the olde Duke gaue in charge,
that the next morning they should racke him vntill he had confessed: which when
the young Duke heard, bee began to sorrow and to say with himselfe, it may be
that to morrowe, if Doctor <name>Faustus</name> come not to ayde me, then shall I be
racked and grieuously tormented, in so much that I shall be constrayned by
force to tell more than willingly I would doe: but he comforted himselfe with
hope that his friends would intreat Doctor <name>Faustus</name> about his
deliuerance, as also it came to passe, for before it was day, Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
was by him, and he coniured them that watched him into such a heauy sleepe,
that he with his charmes made open all the lockes in the prison, and
therewithall brought the young Duke againe in safety to the rest of his
fellowes and friends, where they presented <name>Faustus</name> with a sumptuous
gift, and so they departed the one from the other, &amp;c.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="33" type="chapter" id="chap33">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus borrowed monie of a Jew, and layd his own legge to pawne for it.</hi> Chap. 33.</head>
<p>IT is a common prouerb in <name>Germanie</name>, that although a Coniurer haue all
things at commaundement, the day will come that hee shall not be worth a
pennie: so is it like to fall</p><p>out with Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, in promising the Diuel so largely:</p><p>and as the Diuel is the author of lies, euen so hee led <name>Faustus</name> his
minde, in practising of things to deceiue the people and blinding them, wherein
hee tooke his whole delight, thereby to bring himselfe to riches, yet
notwithstanding in the ende he <milestone n="55" unit="BMP"/> was neuer the richer.  And although
that during foure and twentie yeares of his time that the diuel set him, hee
wanted nothing; yet was he best pleased when hee might deceiue any bodie: for
out of the mightiest Potentates Courtes in all those Countries, hee would send
his Spirite to steale away their best cheare.  And on a time being in his
merriment where hee was banqueting with other Students in an Inne, whereunto
resorted many Iewes, which when Doctor <name>Faustus</name> perceiued, hee was minded
to play some merrie iest to deceiue a Iew, desiring one of them to lend him
some money for a time, the Iewe was content, and lent <name>Faustus</name> threescore
dollers for a moneth, which time being expired, the Iewe came for his money and
interest, but Doctor <name>Faustus</name> was neuer minded to pay the Iewe againe:
at length the Iewe comming home to his house, and calling importunately for his
money, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> made him this answere: Iewe, I haue no money, nor
know I how to pay thee, but notwithstanding, to the ende that thou maiest bee
contented, I will cut off a lim of my bodie, bee it arme or leg, and the same
shalt thou haue in pawne for thy money, yet with this condition, that when I
shall pay thee thy money againe, then thou also giue mee my limme. The Iewe
that was neuer friend to a Christian, thought with himself, this is a fellow
right for my purpose, that will lay his limmes to pawne for money, hee was
therewith very well content; wherefore Doctor <name>Faustus</name> tooke a sawe, and
therewith seemed to cut off his foote (being notwithstanding nothing so) well,
he gaue it to the Iewe, yet vpon this condition, that when he got money to pay,
the Iewe should deliuer him his leg, to the ende hee might set it on againe.
The Iewe was with this matter very well pleased, tooke his leg and departed:</p><p>and hauing farre home, he was somewhat wearie, and by the way hee thus
bethought him, what helpeth mee a knaues leg, if I should carrie it home, it
would stinck, and so infect my house, besides it is too hard a peece of worke
to set it on</p><p>againe, wherefore what an asse was <name>Faustus</name> to lay so deare a pawne for
so small a summe of money; and for my part, quoth the Iew to himselfe, this
will neuer profit me any thing, and with these words he cast the leg away from
him into a ditch.  All this Doctor <name>Faustus</name> knewe right wel, therefore
within three daies after he sent for the Iewe to make him payment of his 60.
Dollers, the Iewe came, and Doctor <name>Faustus</name> demaunded his pawne, there
was his money readie for him:</p><p>the Iewe answered, the pawne was not profitable or necessarie for any thing and
he had cast it away: but <name>Faustus</name> threatninglie replied, I will haue my
<milestone n="56" unit="BMP"/> leg againe, or else one of thine for it. The Iewe fell to intreating,
promising him to giue him what money he would aske, if hee would not deale
<term id="n116">straightly</term><note target="n116" type="gloss" anchored="yes">rigorously</note> with him, wherefore the Iewe was constrained to giue him 60. Dollers more to be rid of him, and yet <name>Faustus</name> had his leg on, for
he had but blinded the Iewe.</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="34" type="chapter" id="chap34">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus deceiued an Horse-courser.</hi> Chap. 34.</head>
<p>IN like manner hee serued an Horse-courser at a faire called <name>Pheiffring</name>,
for Doctor <name>Faustus</name> through his cunning had gotten an excellent fayre
Horse, wherevpon hee rid to the Fayre, where hee had many Chap-men that offered
him money: lastly, he sold him for 40. Dollers, willing him that bought him,
that in any wise he should not ride him ouer any water, but the Horsecourser
marueiled with himself that <name>Faustus</name> bad him ride him ouer no water, (but
quoth he) I will prooue, and forthwith hee rid him into the riuer, presently
the horse vanished from vnder him, and he sate on a bundell of strawe, in so
much that the man was almost drowned.  The horse-courser knewe well where hee
lay that had solde him his horse, wherefore he went angerly to his Inne, where
hee found Doctor <name>Faustus</name> fast a sleepe, and snorting on a bed, but the
horsecourser could no longer forbeare him, tooke him by the leg and began to
pull him off the bed, but he pulled him so, that he pulled his leg from his
body, in so much that the Horse-courser fel down backwardes in the place, then
began Doctor <name>Faustus</name> to crie with an open throate, he hath mur

dered me.  Hereat the Horse-courser was afraide, and gaue the flight, thinking
none other with himselfe, but that hee had pulled his leg from his bodie; by
this meanes Doctor <name>Faustus</name> kept his money.</p><p>

<!-- <link targets="chap34 aa19 bb23"> -->
</p>
</div2>
<div2 n="35" type="chapter" id="chap35">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus eate a lode of Hay.</hi> Chap. 35.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> being in a Towne of <name>Germanie</name> called <name>Zwicikaw</name>,
where hee was accompanied with many Doctors and Masters, and going foorth
to walke after supper, they met with a <term id="n117">Clowne</term><note target="n117" type="gloss" anchored="yes">A boor, rustic.  A  translation of the German 'Bauer'</note> that droue a bade of Hay.  Good
euen good fellowe said <name>Faustus</name> to the Clowne, what shall I giue thee to
let mee eate my bellie full of Hay? the Clowne thought with himselfe, what a
<milestone n="57" unit="BMP"/> mad man is this to eate Hay, thought he with himselfe, thou wilt not
eate much, they agreed for three farthings he should eate as much as he could:
wherefore Doctor <name>Faustus</name> began to eat, and that so rauenously, that all
the rest of his company fell a laughing, blinding so the poore clowne, that he
was sory at his heart, for he seemed to haue eaten more than the halfe of his
Hay, wherefore the clowne began to speake him faire, for feare he should haue
eaten the other halfe also. <name>Faustus</name> made as though he had had pitie on
the Clowne, and went his way. When the Clowne came in place where he would be,
he had his Hay againe as he had before, a full bade.</p><p>

<!-- <link targets="chap35 bb24"> -->
</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="36" type="chapter" id="chap36">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus serued the twelue Students.</hi> Chap. 36.</head>
<p>AT <name>Wittenberg</name> before <name>Faustus</name> his house, there was a quarrell
betweene seuen Students, and flue that came to part the rest, one part being
stronger than the other.  Wherefore <name>Faustus</name> seeing them to bee
ouermatched, coniured them all blinde, in so much that the one could not see
the other, and yet hee so dealt with them, that they fought and smote at one
another still, whereat all the beholders fell a laughmg: and thus they
continued blinde, beating one another, vntill the people parted them, and leade
each one to his owne home: where being entred into their houses, they receiued
their sight perfectly againe.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="37" type="chapter" id="chap37">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Faustus serued the dronken Clownes.</hi> Chap. 37.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> went into an Inne, wherein were many tables full of
Clownes, the which were tippling kan after kan of excellent wine, and to bee
short, they were all dronken, and as they sate, they so sung and hallowed, that
one could not heare a man speake for them; this angred Doctor <name>Faustus</name>;
wherefore hee said to those that had called him in, marke my masters, I
will shew you a merrie iest, the Clownes continuing still hallowing and
singing, he so coniured them, that their mouthes stoode as wide open as it was
possible for them to hold them, and neuer a one of them was able to close his
mouth againe: by and by the noyse was gone, the Clownes notwithstanding looked
earnestly one vpon another, and wist not what <milestone n="58" unit="BMP"/> was happened; wherefore
one by one they went out, and so soone as they came without, they were as well
as euer they were: but none of them desired to goe in any more.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="38" type="chapter" id="chap38">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus solde fiue Swine for sixce Dollers a peece.</hi> Chap. 38.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> began another iest, hee made him readie fiue fat Swine,
the which hee solde to one for sixe Dollers a peece, vpon this condition, that
the Swine-driuer should not driue them into the water.  Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
went home againe, and as the Swine had <term id="n118">filed</term><note target="n118" type="gloss" anchored="yes">defiled</note> themselues in the mudde, the
Swine-driuer droue them into a water, where presently they were changed into so
many bundels of straw swimming vpright in the water: the buier looked <term id="n119">wishly</term><note target="n119" type="gloss" anchored="yes">longingly, wistfully</note>
about him, and was sorrie in his heart, but he knewe not where to finde
<name>Faustus</name>, so he was content to let all goe, and to lose both money and
Hogs.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="39" type="chapter" id="chap39">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus played a merrie iest with the Duke of Anholt in his Court.</hi> Chap. 39.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> on a time came to the Duke of <name>Anholt</name>, the which
welcomed him very courteously, this was in the moneth

of Ianuary, where sitting at the table, he perceiued the Dutchesse to be with
childe, and forbearing himselfe vntill the meate was taken from the table, and
that they brought in the banquetting dishes, said Doctor <name>Faustus</name> to the
Dutchesse, Gracious Ladie, I haue alway heard, that the great bellied women doe
alwaies long for some dainties, I beseech therefore your Grace hide not your
mind from me, but tell me what you desire to eate, she answered him, Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> now truely I will not hide from you what my heart dooth most
desire, namely, that if it were now Haruest, I would eate my bellie full of
ripe Grapes, and other daintie fruite. Doctor <name>Faustus</name> answered herevpon,
Gracious Lady, this is a small thing for mee to doe, for I can doo more than
this, wherefore he tooke a plate, and made open one of the casements of the
windowe, holding it forth, where incontinent hee had his dish full of all maner
of fruites, as red and white Grapes, Peares, and Apples, the which came from
out of strange Countries, all these he presented the Dutchesse, saying: Madame,
I <milestone n="59" unit="BMP"/> pray you vouchsafe to taste of this daintie fruite, the which came
from a farre Countrey, for there the Sommer is not yet ended.  The Dutchesse
thanked <name>Faustus</name> highly, and she fell to her fruite with full appetite.
The Duke of <name>Anholt</name> notwithstanding could not with-holde to aske
<name>Faustus</name> with what reason there were such young fruite to be had at that
time of the yeare?  Doctor <name>Faustus</name> tolde him, may it please your Grace
to vnderstand, that the yere is deuided into two circles ouer the whole world,
that when with vs it is Winter, in the contrary circle it is notwithstanding
Sommer, for in <name>India</name> and <seg id="n120"><name>Saba</name></seg><note target="n120" type="gloss" anchored="yes">Sheba</note> there falleth or setteth the
Sunne, so that it is so warme, that they haue twise a yeare fruite: and
gracious Lorde, I haue a swift Spirit, the which can in the twinckling of an
eye fulfill my desire in any thing, wherefore I sent him into those Countries,
who hath brought this fruite as you see: whereat the Duke was in great
admiration.

<!-- <link targets="chap39 aa20 bb25"> -->
</p>
</div2>
<div2 n="40" type="chapter" id="chap40">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus through his Charmes made a great Castle in presence of the Duke of Anholt.</hi> Chap. 40.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> desired the Duke of <name>Anholt</name> to walke a little forth
of the Court with him, wherefore they went both together into the field where
Doctor <name>Faustus</name> through his skill had placed a mightie Castel: which when
the Duke sawe, hee wondered thereat, so did the Dutchesse, and all the
beholders, that on that hill, which was called the <name>Rohumbuel</name>, should on
the sodaine bee so fayre a Castle.  At last Doctor <name>Faustus</name> desired the
Duke and the Dutchesse to walke with him into the Castle, which they denied
not.  This Castle was so wonderfull strong, hauing about it a great and deepe
trench of water, the which was full of Fish, and all maner of water-foule, as
Swannes, Duckes, Geese, Bitters, and such like.  About the wall was flue stone
dores and two other dores: also within was a great open court, wherein were
inchaunted all maner of wilde beasts, especiallie such as were not to bee found
in <name>Germanie</name>, as Apes, Beares, Buffes, Antelopes, and such like strange
beasts.  Furthermore, there were other maner of beasts, as Hart, Hind, and
wilde Swine, Roe, and all maner of land foule that any man could thinke on, the
which fiewe from one tree to another.  After all this, he set his guestes to
the table, being the Duke and the Dutchesse with their traine, for hee had
prouided them a most sumptuous feast, both of meate and all maner of drinks,
for he set nine messe of meate vpon the boord at once, and al this <milestone n="60" unit="BMP"/>
must his <name>Wagner</name> doe, place all things on the boord, the which was
brought vnto him by the Spirit inuisiblie of all things that their heart could
desire, as wild foule, and Venison, with all maner of daintie fish that could
bee thought on, of Wine also great plentie, and of diuers sortes, as <name>French</name>
wine, <name>Cullin</name> wine, <name>Crabatsher</name> wine, <name>Rhenish</name> wine,
<name>Spanish</name> wine, <name>Hungarian</name> wine, <name>Watzburg</name> wine, Malmesie, and
Sacke: in the whole, there were an hundred kannes standing rounde about the
house.  This sumptuous banquet the Duke tooke thankfullie, and afterwards hee
departed homewards, and to their thinking they had neither eaten nor drunke, so
were they blinded the whilest</p><p>that they were in the Castle: but as they were in their Pallace they looked
towards the Castle, and behold it was all in a flame of fire, and all those
that beheld it wondred to heare so great a noyse, as if it were great Ordinance
should haue been shot off; and thus the Castle burned and consumed away deane.
Which done, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> returned to the Duke, who gaue him great
thankes for shewing them of so great courtesie, giuing him an hundred Dollers,
and libertie to depart or vse his owne discretion therein.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="41" type="chapter" id="chap41">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus with his companie visited the Bishop of Saltzburg his Wine-seller.</hi> Chap. 41.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> hauing taken his leaue of the Duke, he went to
<name>Wittenberg</name>, neere about Shrouetide, and being in companie with certaine
Students, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> was himself the God <name>Bacchus</name>, who hauing
well feasted the Students before with daintie fare, after the manner of
<name>Germanie</name>, where it is counted no feast except all the bidden guests be
drunke, which Doctor <name>Faustus</name> intending, said: Gentlemen and my guestes,
will it please you to take a cuppe of wine with me in a place or seller
whereunto I will bring you, and they all said willinglie wee will: which when
Doctor <name>Faustus</name> heard, hee tooke them foorth, set either of them vpon an
hollie wand, and so were coniured into the Bishop of <name>Saltzburg</name> his
Seller, for there about grewe excellent pleasant Wine: there fell <name>Faustus</name>
and his companie to drinking and swilling, not of the worst but of the
best, and as they were merrie in the Seller, came downe to drawe drinke the
Bishops butler: which when hee perceiued so many persons there hee cried with a
loud voyce, theeues theeues.  This spited Doctor <name>Faustus</name> wonderfullie,
wherefore hee made euery <milestone n="61" unit="BMP"/> one of his company to sit on their holly
wand and so vanished away, and in parting Doctor <name>Faustus</name> tooke the
Butler by the haire of the head and carried him away with them, vntill they
came vnto a mightie high <term id="n121">lopped</term><note target="n121" type="gloss" anchored="yes">trimmed</note> tree, and on the top of that huge tree he
set the Butler, where he remained in a most fearefull perplexitie, <seg id="n122">and</seg> <note target="n122" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'aud.'</note> Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> departed to his house, where they tooke their <foreign lang="la">valete</foreign> one
of another, drink 

ing the Wine the which they had stolne in great bottels of glasse out of the
<seg id="n123">Bishops</seg> <note target="n123" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'Bishps.'</note> seller.  The Butler that had held himselfe by the hand vpon the
lopped tree all the night, was almost frozen with cold, espying the day, and
seeing the tree of so huge great highnesse, thought with himselfe it is
vnpossible to come off this tree without perill of death:</p><p>at length he had espied certaine Clownes which were passing by, he cried for
the bue of God helpe me downe: the Clownes seeing him so high, wondered what
mad man would clime to so huge a tree, wherefore as a thing most miraculous,
they caned tidings vnto the Bishop of <name>Saltzburg</name>, then was there great
running on euery side to see a man in a huge tree, and many deuises they
practised to get him downe with ropes, and being demaunded by the Bishop how
hee came there, he said, that he was brought thither by the haire of the head
of certaine theeues that were robbing of the Wine-seller, but what they were he
knew not, for (said he) they had faces like men, but <seg id="n124">they</seg> <note target="n124" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'the.'</note>wrought like
diuells.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="42" type="chapter" id="chap42">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus kept his Shrouetide.</hi> Chap. 42.</head>
<p>THere were seuen Students, and Masters that studied Diuinitie, <name>Iuris
prudentia, &amp; Medicina</name>, all these hauing consented were agreed to visite
Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, and so to celebrate Shrouetide with him who being come
to his house hee gaue them their welcome, for they were his deare friends,
desiring them to sit downe, where hee serued them with a very good supper of
Hennes, fish, and other rost, yet were they but slightly cheared: wherefore
Doctor <name>Faustus</name> comforted his guests, excusing himselfe that they stale
vpon him so sodainely, that hee had not leisure to prouide for them so well as
they were worthie, but my good friends (quoth he) according to the vse of our
Countrie wee must drinke all this night, and so a draught of the best wine to
bedward is commendable.  For you know that in great Potentates Courts they vse
as this night great feasting, the like will I <milestone n="62" unit="BMP"/> doo for you: for I haue
three great flagons of wine, the first is full of <name>Hungarian</name> wine,
containing eight

gallons, the second of <name>Italian</name> wine, containing seauen gallons, the
third containing sixe gallons of <name>Spanish</name> wine, all the which we will
tipple out before it bee day, besides, wee haue fifteene dishes of meate, the
which my Spirite <name>Mephostophiles</name> hath fet so farre that it was cold
before hee brought it, and they are all full of the daintiest things that ones
heart can deuise, but (saith <name>Faustus</name>) I must make them hot againe:</p><p>and you may beleeue mee Gentlemen, that this is no blinding of you, whereas you
thinke that it is no naturall foode, verely it is as good and as pleasant as
euer you eate.  And hauing ended his tale, he commanded his boy to lay the
cloth, which done, he serued them with fifteene messe of meate, hauing three
dishes to a messe, the which were of all maner of Venison, and other daintie
wild foule, and for wine there was no lacke, as <name>Italian</name> wine,
<name>Hungarian</name> wine, and <name>Spanish</name> wine: and when they were all made
drunke, and that they had almost eaten all their good cheare, they began to
sing and to daunce vntill it was day, and then they departed each one to his
owne habitation: at whose parting, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> desired them to bee
his guests againe the next day following.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="43" type="chapter" id="chap43">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus feasted his guests on the Ash-wednesday.</hi> Chap. 43.</head>
<p>VPon Ashwednesday came vnto Doctor <name>Faustus</name> his bidden guests the
Students, whom hee feasted very royallie, in so much that they were all full
and lustie, singing and daunsing as the night before: and when the high glasses
and goblets were <term id="n125">caroused</term><note target="n125" type="gloss" anchored="yes">drunk or pledged</note> one to another, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> began to
play them some pretie jestes, in so much that round about the hall was heard
most pleasant musick, and that in sundrie places, in this corner a Lute, in
another a Cornet, in another a Citterne, Gitterne, Clarigolds, Harpe, Home pipe
: in fine, all maner of musicke was heard there at that instant, whereat all
the glasses and goblets, cuppes and pots, dishes, and all that stoode on the
boord began to daunce: then Doctor <name>Faustus</name> tooke ten stone pots, <seg id="n126">and</seg> <note target="n126" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'add.'</note>
set them downe on the floare, where presently they began to daunce and to smite
one against the other that the shiuers flewe round about the whole house,

whereat the whole companie fell a laughing.  Then he began another iest, hee
set an Instrument on the table, and caused a monstrous greate Ape to come in
amongst them, which Ape began to <milestone n="63" unit="BMP"/> daunce and to skip, shewing them
many mery conceipts.  In this and such like pastime they passed away the whole
day, where night being come, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> bade them al to supper,
which they lightly agreeed vnto, for Students in these cases are easily
intreated: wherefore he promised to feast them with a banquet of foule, and
afterwards they would all goe about with a Maske, then Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
put foorth a long pole out of the windowe, wherupon presently there came
innumerable of birds and wild foule, and so many as came had not any power to
flie away againe, but he tooke them and flang them to the students: who lightly
pulled off the neceks of them, and being rosted they made their supper, which
being ended they made themselues readie to the Maske.  Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
commanded euery one to put on a cleane shirt ouer his other clothes, which
being done, they began to looke one vpon another, it seemed to each one of them
they had no heads, and so they went forth vnto certaine of their neighbours, at
which sight the people were wonderfully afraide.  And as the vse of <name>Germanie</name>
is, that wheresoeuer a Maske entreth, the good man of the house must feast
them: so when these maskers were set to their banquet, they seemed againe in
their former shape with heads, in so much that they were all knowne what they
were: and hauing sat and well eate and drunke, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> made that
euery one had an Asses head on, with great and long eares, so they fell to
dansing and to driue away the time, vntill it was midnight, and then euery man
departed home, and assoone as they were out of the house each one was in his
naturall shape againe, and so they ended and went to sleepe.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="44" type="chapter" id="chap44">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus the day following was feasted of the Students, and of his merrie iestes with them while hee was in their companie.</hi> Chap. 44.</head>
<p>THe last <name>Bacchanalia</name> was held on Thursday, where insued a great Snow,
and Doctor <name>Faustus</name> was inuited vnto the students that were with him the
day before, where they had prepared an excellent banquet for him: which banquet
being ended, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> began to play his olde prankes, and
forthwith were in the place thirteene Apes, that tooke hands and danced round
in a ring together, then they fell to tumble and to vauting one ouer another,
that it was most pleasant to behold, then they leaped out of the windowe and
vanished away: then they set before Doctor <name>Faustus</name> a rosted Calues head:
which one of <milestone n="64" unit="BMP"/> the Students cut a peece off, and laid it on Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> his trencher, which peece being no sooner layd downe, but the
Calues head began to crie maynly out like a man, murther, murther, out alas
what doest thou to me!  Whereat they were all amazed, but after a while
considering of <name>Faustus</name> his iesting trickes they began to laugh, and then
they pulled in sunder the Calues head and eat it vp.  Whereupon Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> asked leaue to depart, but they would in no wise agree to let
him goe, except that he would promise to come againe: presently then
<name>Faustus</name>, through his cunning, made a sleadge, the which was drawne about
the house with foure fiery dragons: this was feareful for the students to
beholde, for they saw <name>Faustus</name> ride vp and downe as though he should haue
fiered and slayne al them in the house.  This sport continued vntill midnight
with such a noyse that they could not heare one another, and the heads of the
students were so light, that they thought themselues to be in the ayre all that
time.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="45" type="chapter" id="chap45">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus shewed the fayre Helena vnto the Students vpon the Sunday following.</hi> Chap. 45.</head>
<p>THe Sunday following came these students home to Doctor <name>Faustus</name> his owne
house, and brought their meate and drinke with them: these men were right
welcome guests vnto <name>Faustus</name>, wherfore they all fell to drinking of wine
smoothly: and being merry, they began some of them to talke of the beauty of
women, and euery one gaue foorth his verdit what he had seene and what hee had
heard.  So one among the rest said, I neuer was so desirous of any thing in
this world, as to haue a sight (if it were possible) of fayre <name>Helena</name> of
<name>Greece</name>, for whom the worthy towne of <name>Troje</name> was destroyed and
razed downe to the ground, therefore sayth hee, that in all mens iudgement shee
was more than commonly fayre, because that when she was stolne away from her
husband, there was for her recouery so great blood-shed.</p><p>	Doctor <name>Faustus</name> answered: For that you are all my friends and are so
desirous to see that famous pearle of <name>Greece</name>, fayre <name>Helena</name>, the
wife of King <name>Menelaus</name>, and daughter of <name>Tindalus</name> and
<name>L&aelig;da</name>, sister to <name>Castor</name> and <name>Pollux</name>, who was the
fayrest Lady in all <name>Greece</name>: I will therefore bring her into your
presence personally, and in the same forme of attyre as she vsed to goe when
she was in her chiefest flowres and pleasauntest prime of youth.  The like haue
I done for the Emperour <name>Carolus quintus</name>, at his desire I shewed him
<name>Alexander</name> the great, and his Pa-<milestone n="65" unit="BMP"/>ramour: but (sayd Doctor
<name>Faustus</name>) I charge you all that vpon your perils you speake not a word,
nor rise vp from the Table so long as she is in your presence.  And so he went
out of the Hall, returning presently agayne, after whome immediatly followed
the fayre and beautiful <name>Helena</name>, whose beauty was such that the students
were all amazed to see her, esteeming her rather to bee a heauenly than an
earthly creature.  This Lady appeared before the in a most sumptuous gowne of
purple Veluet, richly imbrodered, her hayre hanged downe loose as fayre as the
beaten Gold, &amp; of such length that it reached downe to her hammes, with
amorous cole-black eyes, a sweete and pleasant round face, her lips red as a
Cherry, her cheekes of rose all colour, her mouth small, her neck as white as
the Swanne, tall and slender of personage, and in summe, there was not one
imperfect part in her: shee looked round about her with a rouling Haukes eye,
a smiling &amp; wanton countenance, which neere hand inflamed the hearts of the
students, but that they perswaded themselues she was a Spirit, wherefore such
phantasies passed away lightly with them: and thus fayre <name>Helena</name> &amp;
Doctor <name>Faustus</name> went out agayne one with another.  But the Students at
Doctor <name>Faustus</name> his entring againe into the hall, requested of him to let
them see her againe the next day, for that they would bring with them a painter
and so take her counterfeit: which hee denied, affirming that hee could not
alwayes rayse vp her Spirit, but onely at certaine times: yet (sayd he) I will
giue you her</p><p>counterfeit, which shall bee alwayes as good to you as if your selues should
see the drawing thereof, which they receiued according to his promise, but
soone lost it againe.  The students departed from <name>Faustus</name> home euery one
to his house, but they were not able to sleepe the whole night for thinking on
the beauty of fayre <name>Helena</name>. Wherefore a man may see that the Diuel
blindeth and enflameth the heart with lust oftentimes, that men fall in bue
with Harlots, nay euen with Furies, which afterward cannot lightly be
remoued.</p><p>

<!-- <link targets="chap45 aa22 bb27"> -->
</p>
</div2>
<div2 n="46" type="chapter" id="chap46">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus coniured away the foure wheeles from a clownes waggon.</hi> Chap. 46.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> was sent for to the Marshall of <name>Brunswicke</name>, who
was greatly troubled with the falling sicknes.  Now <name>Faustus</name> had this
vse, neuer to ride but walke foorth on foote, for hee could <milestone n="66" unit="BMP"/> ease
himselfe when his list, and as hee came neere vnto the towne of <name>Brunswicke</name>,
there ouertooke him a Clowne with foure horses and an empty waggon, to
whome Doctor <name>Faustus</name> iestingly to trie him, sayde: I pray thee good
fellow let me ride a little to ease my weary legges; which the buzzardly asse
denied, saying: that his horses were also wearie, and he would not let him get
vp.  Doctor <name>Faustus</name> did this but to prooue the buzzard, if there were
any curtesie to bee found in him if neede were.</p><p>	&nbsp;But such churlishnes as is comonly found among clowns, was by Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> well requited, euen with the like payment: for he sayd vnto him,
Thou doltish Clown, voyde of all humanitie, seeing thou art of so currish a
disposition, I will pay thee as thou hast deserued, for the foure wheeles of
thy Waggon thou shalt haue taken from thee, let mee see then how canst thou
shift: hereupon his wheeles were gon, his horses also fell downe to the ground,
as though they had been dead: whereat the clowne was sore afright, measuring
it as a iust scourge of God for his sinnes and churlishnes: wherefore all
troubled, and wayling, he humbly besought Doctor <name>Faustus</name> to be good vnto
him, confessing hee was worthy of it, notwithstanding if it pleased him to
forgiue him, he would hereafter doo better.  Which humilitie made <name>Faustus</name>
his heart to relent, answering him on this maner, well, doe so no more, but
when a poore weary man desireth thee, see that thou let him ride, but yet thou
shalt not goe altogether cleare, for although thou haue agayne thy foure
wheeles, yet shalt thou fetch them at the foure Gates of the Citie, so he threw
dust on the horses, and reuiued them agayne, and the Clowne for his churlishnes
was fame to fetch his wheeles, spending his time with wearinesse, where as
before he might haue done a good deede, and gone about his busines quietly.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="47" type="chapter" id="chap47">
<head><hi rend="ital">How foure Iuglers cut one anothers head off, and set them on agayne; and how Doctor Faustus deceiued them.</hi> Chap. 47.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> came in the Lent vnto <name>Franckfort</name> Fayre, where his
Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name> gane him to vnderstand that in an Inne were foure
Iuglers that cut one anothers head off, and after their cutting off, sent them
to the Barber to bee trimmed, which many people saw.  This angred <name>Faustus</name>,
(for he meant to haue himselfe the only Cocke in the diuels basket) &amp;
hee went to the place where they <milestone n="67" unit="BMP"/> were, to behold them.  And as these
luglers were together, ready one to cut off the others head, there stoode also
the Barbers ready to trim them, and by them vpon the table stoode likewise a
glasse full of distilled water, and he that was the chiefest among them stood
by it.  Thus they began, they smote off the head of the first, and presently
there was a Lilly in the glasse of distilled water, where <name>Faustus</name>
perceiued this Lilly as it were springing, &amp; the chiefe Iugler named it
the tree of life, thus dealt he with the first, making the Barber wash and
combe his head, &amp; then he set it on againe, presently the Lilly vanished
away out of the water, hereat the man had his head whole and sound againe; the
like did they with the other two: and as the turne &amp; lot came to the chiefe
lugler that he also should be beheaded, &amp; that his Lilly was most pleasant,
fayre, and fiorishing greene, they smote his head off, &amp; when it came to be
barbed, it troubled <name>Faustus</name> his conscience, in so much that he could not
abide to see another doe any thing, for he thought himselfe to bee the
principal coniurer in the world, wherfore Doctor <name>Faustus</name> went to ye
table where as the other Iuglers kept that Lilly, &amp; so he took a smal knife
&amp; cut off the stalke of the Lilly, saying to himself, none of the should
blind <name>Faustus</name>: yet no man saw <name>Faustus</name> to cut the Lilly, but when
the rest of the Iuglers thought to haue set on their masters head, they could
not, wherefore they looked on the Lilly, and found it a bleeding: by this
meanes the Iugler was beguiled, and so died in his wickednes, yet not one
thought that Doctor <name>Faustus</name> had done it.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="48" type="chapter" id="chap48">
<head><hi rend="ital">How an old man the neighbour of Faustus, sought to perswade him to amend his euill life, and to fall vnto repentance.</hi> Chap. 48.</head>
<p>A Good Christian an honest and vertuous olde man, a louer of the holy
scriptures, who was neighbour vnto Doctor <name>Faustus</name>: whe he perceiued that
many students had their recourse in and out vnto Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, he
suspected his euill life, wherefore like a friend he inuited Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
to supper vnto his house, vnto the which hee agreed; and hauing ended their
banquet, the olde man began with these words.  My louing friend and neighbour
Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, I haue to desire of you a friendly and Christian
request, beseeching you that you wil vouchsafe not to be angry with me, but
friendly resolue mee in my doubt, and take my poore inuiting in good part.  To
whome Doctor <name>Faustus</name> answered: My louing neighbour, I pray you say your
minde.  The began the old Patron to say: My good neighbour, you know in the
<milestone n="68" unit="BMP"/> beginning how that you haue defied God, &amp; all the hoast heauen,
&amp; giuen your soule to the Diuel, wherewith you haue incurred Gods high
displeasure, and are become from a Christian farre worse than a heathen person:
oh consider what you haue done, it is not onely the pleasure of the body, but
the safety of the soule that you must haue respect vnto: of which if you be
carelesse, then are you cast away, and shall remaine in the anger of almighty
God.  But yet is it time enough Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, if you repent and call
vnto the Lord for mercy, as wee haue example in the <name>Acts</name> of the
Apostles, the eight Chap. of <name>Simon</name> in <name>Samaria</name>, who was led out of
the way, affirming that he was <name>Simon homo sanctus</name>. This man was
notwithstanding in the end conuerted, after that he had heard the Sermon of
<name>Philip</name>, for</p><p>he was baptized, and sawe his sinnes, and repented. Likewise I beseech you good
brother Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, let my rude Sermon be vnto you a conuersion; and
forget the filthy life that you haue led, repent, aske mercy, &amp; liue: for
Christ saith, <q direct="unspecified">Come vnto me all ye that are weary &amp; heauy loden,
&amp; J wil refresh you. And in <name>Ezechiel</name>: I desire not the death of a
sinner, but rather that hee conuert and liue. Let my words good brother
<name>Faustus</name>, pearce into your adamant heart, and desire God for his Sonne
Christ his sake, to forgiue you. Wherefore haue you so long liued in your
Diuelish practises, knowing that in the olde and newe Testament you are
forbidden, and that men should not suffer any such to hue, neither haue any
conuersation with them, for it is an abomination vnto the Lord; and that such
persons haue no part in the Kingdome of God.</q> All this while Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
heard him very attentiuely, and replyed.  Father, your perswasions like me
wonderous well, and I thanke you with all my heart for your good will and
counsell, promising you so farre as I may to follow your discipline: whereupon
he tooke his leaue. And being come home, he layd him very pensiue on his bed,
bethinking himselfe of the wordes of the good olde man, and in a maner began to
repent that he had giuen his Soule to the Diuell, intending to denie all that
hee had promised vnto <name>Lucifer</name>. Continuing in these cogitations,
sodainly his Spirit appeared vnto him clapping him vpon the head, and wrung it
as though he would haue pulled the head from the shoulders, saying vnto him.
Thou knowest <name>Faustus</name>, that thou hast giuen thy selfe body and soule vnto
my Lord <name>Lucifer</name>, and hast vowed thy selfe an enemy vnto God and vnto all
men; and now thou beginnest to harken to an olde doting foole which perswadeth
thee as it were vnto God, when indeed it is too late, for that thou art the
diuels, and hee hath good power presently to fetch <milestone n="69" unit="BMP"/> thee:</p><p>wherefore he hath sent me vnto thee, to tell thee, that seeing thou hast
sorrowed for that thou hast done, begin againe and write another writing with
thine owne blood, if not, then will I teare thee all to peeces.  Hereat Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> was sore afrayde, and sayd: My <name>Mephostophiles</name>, I will
write agayne what thou wilt: wherefore hee sate him downe, and</p><p>with his owne blood hee wrote as followeth: which writing was afterward sent
to a deare friend of the sayd Doctor <name>Faustus</name> being his kinsman.</p><p>

<!-- <link targets="chap48 aa23 aa25 bb28"> -->
</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="49" type="chapter" id="chap49">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus wrote the second time with his owne blood and gaue it to the Diuell.</hi> Chap. 49.</head>
<p>I Doctor <name>John Faustus</name>, acknowledge by this my deede and handwriting,
that sith my first writing, which is seuenteene yeares, that I haue right
willingly held, and haue been an vtter enemy vnto God and all men, the which I
once againe confirme, and giue fully &amp; wholly my selfe vnto the Diuel both
body and soule, euen vnto the great <name>Lucifer</name>: and that at the ende of
seuen yeares ensuing after the date of this letter, he shall haue to doe with
me according as it pleaseth him, either to lengthen or shorten my life as
liketh him: and herevpon I <seg id="n127">renounce</seg> <note target="n127" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'renonnce.'</note> all perswaders that seeke to withdrawe
mee from my purpose by the word of God, either ghostly or bodily.  And further,
I will neuer giue eare vnto any man, be he spirituall or temporall, that moueth
any matter for the saluation of my soule.  Of all this writing, and that
therein contained, be witnesse, my own bloud, the which with mine own hands I
haue begun, and ended.</p><p>
<hi rend="ital">Dated at Wittenberg the 25. of July</hi>.</p><p>And presently vpon the making of this Letter, he became so great an
enemie vnto the poore olde man, that he sought his life by all meanes possible;
but this godly man was strong in the holy Ghost, that he could not be
vanquished by any meanes: for about two dayes after that hee had exhorted
<name>Faustus</name>, as the poore man lay in his bed, sodainely there was a mightie
rumbling in the Chamber, the which hee was neuer wont to heare, &amp; he heard
as it had been the groning of a Sowe, which lasted long: whereupon the good
olde man began to iest, and mock, and saide: oh what Barbarian crie is this, oh
fayre Bird, what foule musick is this of a faire Angell, that could not tarrie
two dayes in his place': <milestone n="70" unit="BMP"/> beginnest <seg id="n128">thou</seg><note target="n128" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'thon.'</note> now to runne into a</p><p>
poore mans house, where thou hast no power, and wert not able to keepe thine
own two daies': With these and such like wordes the Spirit departed.  And when
hee came home <name>Faustus</name> asked him how hee had sped with the olde man: to
whome the Spirit answered, the olde man was <seg id="n129">harnessed</seg>,<note target="n129" type="gloss" anchored="yes">spiritually armed</note> and that hee could
not once lay holde vpon him: but he would not tell howe the olde man had mocked
him, for the diuels can neuer abide to heare of their fall. Thus doth God
defend the hearts of all honest Christians, that betake themselues vnder his
tuition.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="50" type="chapter" id="chap50">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus made a marriage betweene two louers.</hi> Chap. 50</head>
<p>IN the Citie of <name>Wittenberg</name> was a student, a gallant Gentleman, named
<name>N. N</name>.  This Gentleman was farre in loue with a Gentlewoman, fayre and
proper of personage.  This Gentlewoman had a Knight that was a suiter vnto her,
and many other Gentlemen, the which desired her in manage, but none could
obtaine her: So it was that this <name>N. N</name> was very well acquainted with
<name>Faustus</name>, and by that meanes became a suiter vnto him to assist him in
the matter, for he fell so farre in despayre with himselfe, that he pined away
to the skinne and bones.  But when he had opened the matter vnto Doctor
<name>Faustus</name>, he asked counsell of his Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name>, the
which tolde him what to doe.  Hereupon Doctor <name>Faustus</name> went home to the
Gentleman, and bade him be of good cheare, for he should haue his desire, for
he would helpe him to that hee wished for, and that this Gentlewoman should
loue none other but him onely: wherefore Doctor <name>Faustus</name> so changed the
minde of the Damsel by a practise he wrought, that she would doe no other thing
but thinke on him, whome before she had hated, neither cared she for any man
but him alone.  The deuice was thus, <name>Faustus</name> commaunded this Gentleman
that he should cloth himselfe in all his best apparel that he had and that he
should goe vnto this gentlewoman, and there to shew himselfe, giuing him also a
Ring, commanding him in any wise that he should daunce with her before he
departed. Wherefore he followed <name>Faustus</name> his counsaile, went to her, and
when they began to daunce</p><p>
they that were suiters began to take euery one his Lady in his hand, and this
good Gentleman tooke her, whom before had so disdained him, and in the daunce
hee thrust the Ring into her hand that Doctor <name>Faustus</name> had giuen him, the
which shee no sooner toucht, but she fell immediatly in loue with him,
beginning in the daunce to <milestone n="71" unit="BMP"/> smile, and many times to giue him wincks,
rouling her eyes, and in the end she asked him if he could loue her and make
her his wife; hee gladly answered, hee was content: and hereupon they
concluded, and were married, by the meanes and helpe of Doctor <name>Faustus</name>,
for which hee receiued a good reward of the Gentleman.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="51" type="chapter" id="chap51">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus led his friends into his Garden at Christmas, and shewed them many strange sights in his 19. yeare.</hi> Chap. 51.</head>
<p>IN December, about Christmas in the Citie of <name>Wittenberg</name>, were many young
Gentlewomen, the which were come out of the Countrey to make merry with their
friends and acquaintance: amongst whome, there were certaine that were well
acquainted with Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, wherefore they were often inuited as his
guests vnto him, and being with him on a certaine time after dinner, hee led
them into his Garden, where he shewed them all maner of flowers, <seg id="n130">and</seg> <note target="n130" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'aud.'</note> fresh
hearbs, Trees bearing fruit and blossomes of all sortes, insomuch that they
wondered to see that in his Garden should bee so pleasant a time as in the
middest of summer: and without in the streetes, and all ouer the Countrey, it
lay full of Snowe and yce.  Wherefore this was noted of them as a thing
miraculous, each one gathering and carrying away all such things as they best
liked, and so departed delighted with their sweete smelling flowers.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="52" type="chapter" id="chap52">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus gathered together a great armie of men in his extremitie agaynst a Knight that would haue injured him on his iourney.</hi> Chap. 52</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> trauelled towards <name>Eyszleben</name>, and when he was nigh
halfe the way, he espied seuen horsemen, and the

chiefe of them hee knew to be the knight to whome he had plaied a iest in the
Emperours Court, for he had set a huge payre of Harts hornes vpon his head: and
when the knight now saw that he had fit opportunitie to be reuenged of
<name>Faustus</name> he ran vpon him himselfe, &amp; those that were with him, to
mischiefe him, intending priuily to shoot at him:
which when Doctor <name>Faustus</name> espied, he vanished away into the wood which
was hard by them.  But when the Knight perceiued that he was vanished away, he
caused <milestone n="72" unit="BMP"/> his men to stand still, where as they remayned they heard all
manner of warlike instruments of musick, as Drummes, Flutes, Trumpets, and such
like, and a certaine troupe of horsemen running towards them.  Then they turned
another way, and there also were assaulted on the same side: then another way,
and yet they were freshly assaulted, so that which way soeuer they turned
themselues, hee was encountred: in so much that when the Knight perceiued that
he could escape no way, but that they his enemies layd on him which way soeuer
hee offered to flie, he tooke a good heart and ranne amongst the thickest, and
thought with himselfe better to die than to liue with so great an infamie.
Therefore being at handy-blowes with them hee demaunded the cause why they
should so vse them: but none of them would giue him answere, vntill Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> shewed himself vnto the Knight, where withall they inclosed him
round, and Doctor <name>Faustus</name> sayde vnto him, Sir, yeelde your weapon, and
yourselfe, otherwise it wcill goe hardly with you. The Knight that knew none
other hut that he was inuironed with an hoast of men, (where indeede they were
none other than Diuels) yeelded: then <name>Faustus</name> tooke away his sworde, his
piece, and horse, with all the rest of his companions.  And further hee said
vnto him; Sir, the chiefe General of our armie hath commaunded to deale with
you according to the law of Armes, you shall depart in peace whither you
please: and then he gaue the Knight an horse after the maner, and set him
theron, so he rode, the rest went on foote, vntill they came to their Inne,
where being alighted, his Page rode on his horse to the water, and presently
the horse vanyshed away, the Page being almost suncke and drowned, but he
escaped: and comming home, the Knight perceiued his Page so be myred &amp; on
foote, asked where his horse was become? Who answered that he was vanished
away: which when the Knight heard, he said, of a truth this is <name>Faustus</name>
his doing, for he serueth me now as he did before at the Court, only to
make me a skorne and a laughing stock.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="53" type="chapter" id="chap53">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus caused Mephostophiles to bring him seuen of the fayrest women that he could finde in all those countries he had traueiled in, in the 20. yeare.</hi> Chap. 53.</head>
<p>WHen Doctor <name>Faustus</name> called to <seg id="n131">minde</seg>,<note target="n131" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'miude.'</note> that his time from day to day drew
nigh, hee began to liue a swinish and Epicurish life, wherefore he commaunded
his Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name>, to bring him <milestone n="73" unit="BMP"/> seuen of the fayrest
women that he had seene in all the time of his trauel: which being brought,
first one, and then another, he lay with them all, insomuch that he liked them
so well, that he continued with them in all maner of bue, and made them to
trauell with him in all his iourneies.  These women were two <name>Netherlanders</name>,
one <name>Hungarian</name>, one <name>English</name>, two <name>Wallons</name>, one
<name>Francklander</name>: and with these sweete personages he continued long, yea
euen to his last ende.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="54" type="chapter" id="chap54">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus found a masse of money when hee had consumed 22. of his yeares.</hi> Chap. 54.</head>
<p>TO the ende that the Diuell would make <name>Faustus</name> his onely heire, he
shewed vnto him where he should goe and finde a mighty huge masse of money, and
that hee should haue it in an olde Chappell that was fallen downe, halfe a mile
distant from <name>Wittenberg</name>, there hee bade him to dig and he should finde
it, the which he did, and hauing digged reasonable deepe, he saw a mighty huge
serpent, the which lay on the treasure it selfe, the treasure it selfe lay like
an huge light burning: but D. <name>Faustus</name> charmed the serpent that he crept
into a hole, and when he digged deeper to get vp the treasure, he found nothing
but coles of fire: there also he heard and saw many that were tormented, yet
notwithstand

ing he brought away the coles, and when he was come home, it was al turned into
siluer and gold, as after his death was found by his seruant, the which was
almost about estimation, a thousand gilders.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="55" type="chapter" id="chap55">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus made the Spirit of fayre Helena of Greece his own Paramour and bedfellow in his 23. yeare.</hi> Chap. 55.</head>
<p>TO the ende that this miserable <name>Faustus</name> might fill the lust of his
flesh, and hue in all manner of voluptuous pleasures, it came in his minde
after he had slept his first sleepe, &amp; in the 23. yeare past of his time,
that he had a great desire to lie with fayre <name>Helena</name> of <name>Greece</name>,
especially her whom he had seene and shewed vnto the students of
<name>Wittenberg</name>, wherefore he called vnto him his Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name>,
comanding him to bring him the faire <name>Helena</name>, <seg id="n132">which</seg> <note target="n132" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'whic.'</note> he also did.
Wherupo he fel in loue with her, &amp; made her his common Concubine &amp;
bedfellow, for she was so beautifull and delightful a peece, that he could not
be one <milestone n="74" unit="BMP"/> houre from her, if hee should therefore haue suffered death,
shee had so stolne away his heart: and to his seeming, in time she was with
childe, and in the end brought him a man childe, whome <name>Faustus</name> named
<name>Iustus Faustus</name>: this childe tolde Doctor <name>Faustus</name> many things that
were to come, and what strange matters were done in forraine countries: but in
the end when <name>Faustus</name> lost his life, the mother and the childe vanished
away both together.

<!-- <link targets="chap55 aa24 bb29"> -->
</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="56" type="chapter" id="chap56">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus made his Will, in the which he named his seruant Wagner to be his heire.</hi> Chap. 56.</head>
<p>DOctor <name>Faustus</name> was now in his 24. and last yeare, and bee had a prety
stripling to his seruant, the which had studied also at the Vniuersitie of
<name>Wittenberg</name>: this youth was very well acquainted with his knaueries and
sorceries, so that hee was hated as well for his owne knaueries, as also for
his Masters: for no man would giue him entertainement into his seruice, because
of his vnhappines, but <name>Faustus</name>: this <name>Wagner</name> was so well beloued
with <name>Faustus</name>, that hee vsed him as his

sonne: for doo what hee would his master was alwayes therewith well content.
And when the time drewe nigh that <name>Faustus</name> should end, hee called vnto
him a Notary and certaine masters the which were his friends and often
conuersant with him, in whose presence he gaue this <name>Wagner</name> his house and
Garden.  Item, hee gaue him in ready money 1600. gilders. Item, a Farme.  Item,
a gold chayne, much plate, and other housholde stuffe.  This gaue he al to his
seruant, and the rest of his time he meant to spend in Innes and Students
company, drinking and eating, with other Iollitie: and thus hee finished his
Will for that time.</p><p>

<!-- <link targets="chap56 aa21 bb26 bb30"> -->
</p>
</div2>

<div2 n="57" type="chapter" id="chap57">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus fell in talke with his seruant touching his Testament, and the couenants thereof.</hi> Chap. 57.</head>
<p>NOw, when this Will was made, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> called vnto him his
seruant, saying: I haue thought vpon thee in my Testament, for that thou hast
beene a trusty seruant vnto me and a faithfull, and hast not opened my secrets:
and yet further (sayd he) aske of me before I die what thou wilt, and I will
giue it vnto thee.  His <milestone n="75" unit="BMP"/> <seg id="n133">seruant</seg> <note target="n133" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'seruaut.'</note> rashly answered, I pray you let mee
haue your cunning.  To which Doctor <name>Faustus</name> answered, I haue giuen thee
all my bookes, vpon this condition, that thou wouldst not let them bee common,
but vse them for thine owne pleasure, and studie carefully in them. And doest
thou also desire my cunning': That maiest thou peraduenture haue, if thou loue
and peruse my bookes well. Further (sayd Doctor <name>Faustus</name>) seeing that
thou desirest of me this request, I will resolue thee: my spirit
<name>Mephostophiles</name> his time is out with me, and I haue nought to commaund
him as touching thee, yet will I helpe thee to another, if thou like well
thereof.  And within three dayes after he called his seruant vnto him, saying:
art thou resolued': wouldst thou verily haue a Spirit': Then tell me in what
maner or forme thou wouldst haue him': To whome his seruant answered, that hee
would haue him in the forme of an Ape: whereupon presently appeared a Spirit
vnto him in maner and forme of an Ape, the which leaped about the house.  Then
sayd <name>Faustus</name>, see, there hast thou thy request, but yet he will not obey
thee

vntill I be dead, for when my Spirit <name>Mephostophiles</name> shall fetch me away,
then shal thy Spirit be bound vnto thee, if thou agree: and thy Spirit shalt
thou name <name>Akercocke</name>, for so is he called: but all this is vpon condition
that thou publish my cunning, and my merry conceits, with all that I haue done
(when I am dead) in an hystory: and if thou canst not remember all, thy Spirit
<name>Akercocke</name> will helpe thee: so shall the great actes that I haue done be
manifested vnto the world.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="58" type="chapter" id="chap58">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus hauing but one moneth of his appoynted time to come, fell to mourning and sorrowe with himselfe for his diuelish exercise.</hi> Chap. 58.</head>
<p>TIme ranne away with <name>Faustus</name>, as the houre glasse, for hee had but one
moneth to come of his 24. yeares, at the end whereof he had giuen himselfe to
the Diuell body and soule, as is before specified.  Here was the first token,
for he was like a taken murtherer or a theefe, the which findeth himselfe
guiltie in conscience before the ludge haue giuen sentence, fearing euery houre
to die: for hee was grieued, and waylaying spent the time, went talking to
himselfe, wringing of his hands, sobbing and sighing, hee fell away from flesh,
and was very leane, and <seg id="n134">kept</seg><note target="n134" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'kpt.'</note> himselfe close: neither could he abide to see
or heare of his <name>Mephistophiles</name> any more.</p><p>
<milestone n="76" unit="BMP"/> </p>
</div2>

<div2 n="59" type="chapter" id="chap59">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus complayned that hee should in his lusty time and youthful yeares die so miserably.</hi> Chap. 59.</head>
<p>THis sorrowfull time drawing neere so troubled Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, that he
began to write his minde, to the ende he might peruse it often and not forget
it and is in maner as followeth.</p><p>	Ah <name>Faustus</name>, thou sorrowful and wofull man, now must thou goe to the
damned company in vnquenchable fire, whereas thou mightest haue had the ioyfull
immortalitie of the soule, the which thou now hast lost.  Ah grosse
vnderstanding and wilfull will, what seazeth on my limmes other than a robbing
of my life': Bewayle with me my sound &amp; healthfull body,</p><p>
wit and soule, bewayle with me my sences, for you haue had your part and
pleasure as well as I.  Oh enuie and disdaine, how haue you crept both at once
into me, and now for your sakes I must suffer all these torments?  Ah whither
is pitie and mercy fled': Vpon what occasion hath heauen repayed me with this
reward by sufferance to suffer me to perish Wherefore was I created a man': The
punishment that I see prepared for me of my selfe now must I suffer. Ah
miserable wretch, there is nothing in this world to shew me comfort: then woe
is me, what helpeth my wayling.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="60" type="chapter" id="chap60">
<head><hi rend="ital">Another complaint of Doctor Faustus.</hi> Chap. 60.</head>
<p>OH poore, wofull and weary wretch: oh sorrowfull soule of <name>Faustus</name>, now
art thou in the number of the damned, for now must I waite for vnmeasurable
paynes of death, yea far more lamentable than euer yet any creature hath
suffered.  Ah senceles, wilful &amp; desperate forgetfulnesse!  O cursed and
vnstable life!  O blinde and carelesse wretch, that so hast abused thy body,
sence and soule!  O foolish pleasure, into what a weary labyrinth hast thou
brought mee, blinding mine eyes in the clearest day': Ah weake heart!  O
troubled soule, where is become thy knowledge to comfort thee': O pitifull
weariness! Oh desperate hope, now shall I neuer more be thought vpon!  Oh,
care vpon carefulnesse, and sorrowes on heapes: Ah grieuous paynes that pearce
my panting heart, whom is there now that can deliuer me': Would God that I knew
where to hide me, or into what place to creepe or flie. Ah, woe, woe is me, be
where I will, yet am I taken.  Herewith poore <milestone n="77" unit="BMP"/> <name>Faustus</name> was so
sorrowfully troubled, that he could not speake or vtter his minde any
further.</p><p></p>

</div2>

<div2 n="61" type="chapter" id="chap61">
<head><hi rend="ital">How Doctor Faustus bewayled to thinke on Hell, and of the miserable paynes
therein prouided for him.</hi> Chap. 61.</head>
<p>
NOw thou <name>Faustus</name>, damned wretch, howe happy wert thou if as an
vnreasonable beast thou mightest die without soule, so shouldest thou not feele
any more doubts': But nowe the diuell will take thee away both body and soule,
and set thee in an vnspeakable place of darkenesse: for although others soules
haue rest and peace, yet I poore damned wretch must suffer all manner of filthy
stench, paines, colde, hunger, thirst, heate, freezing, burning, hissing,
gnashing, and all the wrath and curse of God, yea all the creatures that God
hath created are enemies to mee.  And now too late I remember that my Spirit
<name>Mephostophiles</name> did once tell mee, there was a great difference amongst
the damned; for the greater the sinne, the greater the torment: for as the
twigges of the tree make greater flame than the trunke thereof, and yet the
trunke continueth longer in burning; euen so the more that a man is rooted in
sinne, the greater is his punishment.  Ah thou perpetuall damned wretch, now
art thou throwne into the euerlasting fiery lake that neuer shall be quenched,
there must I dwell in all manner of wayling, sorrow, misery, payne, torment,
griefe, howling sighing, sobbing, blubbering, running of eies, stinking at
nose, gnashing of teeth feare to the eares, horror to the conscience, and
shaking both of hand and foote. Ah that I could carry the heauens on my
shoulders, so that there were time at last to quit me of this euerlasting
damnation!  Oh who can deliuer me out of these fearful tormeting flames, ye
which I see prepared for me': Oh there is no helpe, nor any man that can
deliuer me, nor any wayling of sins can help me, neither is there rest to be
found for me day nor night. Ah wo is me, for there is no help for me, no
shield, no defence no comfort.  Where is my hold': knowledge dare I not trust:
and for a soule to God wards that haue I not, for I shame to speake vnto him:
if I doo, no answere shall be made me, but hee will hide his face from me, to
the end that I should not beholde the ioyes of the chosen. What meane I then to
complaine where no helpe is': No, I know no hope resteth in my gronings.  I
haue desired that it should bee so, and God hath sayd <name>Amen</name> to my
misdoings: for now I must haue shame to comfort me in my calamities.</p><p>

<!-- <link targets="chap59 chap60 chap61" id="xx26"> -->
<!-- <link targets="xx26 bb31"> -->

<milestone n="78" unit="BMP"/> </p>
</div2>

<div2 n="62" type="chapter" id="chap62">
<head><hi rend="ital">Here followeth the miserable and lamentable ende of Doctor Faustus, by the which all Christians may take an example and warning.</hi> Chap. 62.</head>
<p>IN the 24. yeare Doctor <name>Faustus</name> his time being come, his Spirit appeared
vnto him, giuing him his writing againe, and commaunding him to make
preparation, for that the diuel would fetch him agaynst a certaine time
appoynted.  D. <seg id="n135"><name>Faustus</name></seg><note target="n135" anchored="yes">B.M. has '<name>Fanstus</name>.'</note> mourned and sighed wonderfully, and neuer went
to bed, nor slept winke for sorrow.  Wherefore his Spirit appeared againe,
comforting him, and saying: My <name>Faustus</name>, be not thou so cowardly minded;
for although that thou losest thy body, it is not long vnto the day of
Iudgement, and thou must die at the last, although thou liue many thousand
yeares. The Turkes, the Iewes, &amp; many an vnchristian Emperour, are in the
same condemnation: therefore (my <name>Faustus</name>) be of good courage, and be
not discomforted, for the diuel hath promised that thou shalt not be in paines
as the rest of the damned are.  This and such like comfort he gaue him, but he
tolde him false, and agaynst the saying of the holy Scriptures.  

<seg id="c27">
Yet Doctor <name>Faustus</name> that had none other expectation but to pay his debts with his
owne skinne, went on the same day that his Spirit sayd the diuel would fetch
him, vnto his trusty and dearest beloued brethren and companions, as Masters,
and Batchelers of Arte, and other students more the which had often visited him
at his house in merriment: these he entreated that they would walke into the
Village called <name>Rimlich</name>, halfe a mile from <name>Wittenberg</name>, and that
they would there take with him for their repast part of a small banquet, the
which they all agreed vnto: so they went together, and there held their dinner
in a most sumptuous maner.  Doctor <name>Faustus</name> with them (dissemblingly) was
merry, but not from the heart: wherefore he <seg id="n135a">requested</seg><note target="n135a" anchored="yes">B.M. has the last e upside down.</note> them that they would
also take part of his rude supper: the which they agreed vnto: for (quoth hee)
I must tell you what is the <seg id="n135b">Victulers</seg> due:<note target="n135b" anchored="yes">In early use, one who provisioned a trading vessel in return for a share in the transaction was called a victualler.  The phrase here seems to mean, "I must tell you what I have done for which I must give the devil his due."</note> and when they sleeped (for
drinke was in their heads) then Doctor <name>Faustus</name> payed and discharged the
shot, and bound the students and the Masters to goe with him into another
roume, for he had many wonderfull matters to tell them: and when they were
entred the roume as he requested, Doctor <name>Faustus</name> sayd vnto them, as
hereafter followeth.
</seg></p>
<p>
<milestone n="81" unit="BMP"/> </p>
</div2>

<div2 n="63" type="chapter" id="chap63">
<head><hi rend="ital">An Oration of Faustus to the Students.</hi> Chap. 63.</head>
<p>MY trusty and welbeloued friends, the cause why I haue inuited you into this
place is this: Forasmuch as you haue knowne me this many yeares, in what maner
of life I haue liued, practising al maner of coniurations and wicked exercises,
the which I haue obtayned through the helpe of the diuel, into whose diuelish
fellowship they haue brought me, the which vse the like Arte and practise,
vrged by the detestable prouocation of my flesh, my stiffe necked and
rebellious will, with my filthy infernall thoughts, the which were euer before
me, pricking mee forward so earnestly, that I must perforce haue the consent of
the diuell to ayde me in my deuises. And to the end I might the better bring my
purpose to passe, to haue the Diuels ayd and furtherance, which I neuer haue
wanted in mine actions, I haue promised vnto him at the ende and accomplishing
of 24. yeares, both body and soule, to doe therewith at his pleasure: and this
day, this dismall day those 24. yeares are fully expired, for night beginning
my houre-glasse is at an end, the direfull finishing whereof I carefully
expect: for out of all doubt this night hee will fetch mee, to whome I haue
giuen my selfe in recompence of his seruice, both body and soule, and twice
confirmed writings with my proper blood.  Now haue I called you my welbeloued
Lords, friends, brethren, and fellowes, before that fatall houre to take my
friendly farewell, to the end that my departing may not hereafter be hidden
from you, beseeching you herewith courteous, and louing Lords and brethren, not
to take in euil part any thing done by mee, but with friendly commendations to
salute all my friends and companions wheresoeuer: desiring both you and them,
if euer I haue trespassed against your minds in any thing, that you would all
heartily forgiue me: and as for those lewd practises the which this full 24.
yeares I haue followed, you shall hereafter finde them in writing: and I
beseech you let this my lamentable ende to the residue of your liues bee a
sufficient warning, that you haue God alwayes before your eies, praying vnto
him that he would euer defend you from the temptation of the diuell, and all
his false deceipts, not falling altogether from God, as I wretched and vngodly
damned creature haue done, hauing denied and defied Baptisme, the Sacraments of
Christs body, God himselfe, all heauenly powers, and earthly men, yea, I haue
denied such a God, that desireth not to haue one lost.  Neither let the <milestone n="80" unit="BMP"/> euill fellowship of wicked companions misselead you as it hath done me:
visit earnestly and oft the Church, warre and striue continually agaynst the
Diuell with a good and stedfast beliefe on God, and Iesus Christ, and vse your
vocation in holiness.  Lastly, to knitte vp my troubled Oration, this is my
friendly request, that you would to rest, &amp; let nothing trouble you: also
if you chance to heare any noise, or rumbling about the house, be not therwith
afrayd, for there shal no euil happen vnto you: also I pray you arise not out
of your beds.  But aboue all things I intreate you, if you hereafter finde my
dead carkasse, conuay it vnto the earth, for I dye both a good and bad
Christian; a good Christian, for that I am heartely sorry, and in my heart
alwayes praye for mercy, that my soule may be deliuered: a bad Christian, for
that I know the Diuell will haue my bodie, and that would I willingly giue him
so that he would leaue my soule in quiet: wherefore I pray you that you would
depart to bed, and so I wish you a quiet night, which vnto me notwithstanding
will be horrible and fearefull.</p><p>	This Oration or declaration was made by Doctor <name>Faustus</name>, &amp; that with
a hearty and resolute minde, to the ende hee might not discomfort them: but
the Students wondered greatly thereat, that he was so blinded, for knauery,
coniuration, and such like foolish things, to giue his body and soule vnto the
diuell: for they loued him entirely, and neuer suspected any such thing before
he had opened his mind to them: wherefore one of the sayd vnto him; ah, friend
<name>Faustus</name>, what haue you done to conceale this matter so long from vs, we
would by the help of good Diuines, and the grace of God, haue brought you out
of this net, and haue torne you out of the bondage and chaynes of Sathan,
whereas nowe we feare it is too late, to the vtter ruine of your body and
soule?  Doctor <name>Faustus</name> answered, I durst neuer doo it, although I often
minded, to settle my selfe vnto godly people, to desire counsell and helpe, as
once mine olde neighbour counsailed mee, that I shoulde follow his learning,
and leaue all my coniurations, yet when I was minded to amend, and to followe
that good mans counsell, then came the Diuell and would haue had me away, as
this night he is like to doe, and sayd so soone as I turned againe to God, hee
would dispatch mee altogether.  Thus, euen thus, (good Gentlemen, and my deare
friends) was I inthralled in that Satanicall band, all good desires drowned,
all pietie banished, al purpose of amendmet vtterly exiled, by the tyranous
threatnings of my deadly enemy.  But when the Students heard his words, they
gaue him counsaile to doo naught else but call vpon God, desiring <milestone n="81" unit="BMP"/> him
for the loue of his sweete Sonne Iesus Christes sake, to haue mercy vpon him,
teaching him this forme of prayer.  O God bee mercifull vnto me, poore and
miserable sinner, and enter not into iudgement with me, for no flesh is able to
stand before thee.  Although, O Lord, I must leaue my sinfull body vnto the
Diuell, being by him deluded, yet thou in mercy mayest preserue my soule.</p><p>	This they repeated vnto him, yet it could take no holde, but euen as <name>Caine</name>
he also said his sinnes were greater than God was able to forgiue; for all
his thought was on his writing, he meant he had made it too filthy in writing
it with his owne blood. 

<!-- <link targets="c27 c27a" id="xx27"> -->
<!-- <link targets="xx27 aa26 bb32"> -->
<seg id="c28">
The Students &amp; the other that were there, when
they had prayed for him, they wept, and so went foorth, but <name>Faustus</name>
taryed in the hall: and when the Gentlemen were laid in bed, none of them
could sleepe, for that they attended to heare if they might be priuy of his
ende.  It happened between twelue and one a clock at midnight, there blewe a
mighty storme of winde against the house, as though it would haue blowne the
foundation thereof out of his place.  Hereupon the Students began to feare, and
got out of their beds, comforting one another, but they would not stirre out of
the chamber: and the Host of the house ran out of doores, thinking the house
would fall.  The Students lay neere vnto that hall wherein Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
lay, and they heard a mighty noyse and hissing, as if the hall had beene
full of Snakes and Adders: with that the hall doore flew open wherein Doctor
<name>Faustus</name> was, then he began to crie for helpe, saying: murther, murther,
but it came foorth with halfe a voyce hollowly: shortly after they heard him no
more.  But when it was day, the Students that had taken no rest that night,
arose and went into the hall in the which they left Doctor <name>Faustus</name>,
where notwithstanding they found no <name>Faustus</name>, but all the hall lay
besprinckled with blood, his braines cleauing to the wall: for the Diuel had
beaten him from one wall against another, <seg id="n136">in</seg><note target="n136" anchored="yes">B.M. has 'in in.'</note> one corner lay his eyes, in
another his teeth, a pitifull and fearefull sight to beholde.  Then began the
Students to bewayle and weepe for him, and sought for his body in many places:
lastly they came into the yarde where they found his bodie lying on the horse
dung, most monstrously torne, and fearefull to beholde, for his head and all
his ioynts were dasht in peeces.</seg></p>
<p>
<seg id="c28a">The forenamed Students and Masters that were at his death, haue obtayned so
much, that they buried him in the Village where he was so grieuously tormented.
After the which, they returned to <name>Wittenberg</name>, &amp; comming into
the house of <name>Faustus</name>, they found ye seruant of <name>Faustus</name> very <milestone n="80" unit="BMP"/> sad, vnto whom they opened all the mat[t]er, who tooke it exceeding
heauilie.  There found they also this history of Doctor <name>Faustus</name> noted,
and of him written as is before declared, all saue onely his ende, the which
was after by the students thereto annexed: further, what his seruant had noted
thereof, was made in another booke.  And you haue heard that he held by him in
his life the Spirit of fayre <name>Helena</name>, the which had by him one sonne, the
which he named <name>Iustus Faustus</name>, euen the same day of his death they
vanished away, both mother and sonne.  The house before was so darke, that
scarce any body could abide therein.  The same night Doctor <name>Faustus</name>
appeared vnto his seruant liuely, and shewed vnto him many secret things
the which hee had done and hidden in his life time.  Likewise there were
certaine which saw Doctor <name>Faustus</name> looke out of the window by night as
they passed by the house.
</seg></p>
<p>
<seg id="c28b">And thus ended the whole history of Doctor <name>Faustus</name> his coniuration, and
other actes that he did in his life; out of the which example euery Christian
may learne, but chiefly the stiffenecked and high minded may thereby learne to
feare God, and to be careful of their vocation, and to be at defiance with all
diuelish workes, as God hath most precisely forbidden, to the end we should not
inuite the diuell as a guest, nor giue
him place as that wicked <name>Faustus</name> hath done: for here we haue a feareful
example of his writing, promise, and end, that we may remember him: that we goe
not astray, but take God alwaies before our eies, to call alone vpon him, and
to honour him all the dayes of our life, with
heart and heartyprayer and with al our strength and soule to glorifie his holy
name, defying the Deuill and all his
 works, to the end we may remayne with Christ in all endlesse ioy: Amen, Amen,
that wish I vnto
euery Christian heart, and Gods name to
bee glorified.  Amen.

<foreign lang="la">FINIS</foreign>.

</seg>
<!-- <link targets="c28 c28a c28b" id="xx28"> -->
<!-- <link targets="xx28 aa27 bb33"> -->
</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body></text></TEI.2>
