<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dedication to Mary Countess of Pembroke</title>
<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
<author>Christopher Marlowe</author>
<editor role="translator">Mark Eccles</editor>
&responsibility;
&fund.Tufts;
</titleStmt>
<extent>about 700Kb</extent>
&Perseus.publish;
<sourceDesc><bibl></bibl></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
 <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2"> 
<state unit="line"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
	<state n="chunk" unit="dedication"/>
      </refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change><date>3/14/96</date>
<respStmt><name>Hilary Binda</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
<item>Mark up scanned text</item></change>
<change><date>9/1/97</date>
<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
<item>
$Log: marl.dedication.xml,v $
Revision 1.2  2004/04/22 14:20:32  cwulfman
*** empty log message ***

Revision 1.1  2004/04/22 13:55:23  cwulfman
Making xml files the canonical ones.

Revision 1.7  2003/07/01 22:14:53  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.6  2000/04/26 00:05:31  dasmith
Fixed fileDesc info. Cleaned up witList.

Revision 1.5  2000/02/22 22:16:14  amahoney
add refsdecls, for consistency

Revision 1.4  1999/09/01 17:15:33  dasmith
Fixed preamble and added encodingDesc.

Revision 1.3  1997/09/11 16:00:29  textgod
Updated for nsgmls.

Revision 1.2  1997/09/03 21:48:09  textgod
Fixed typos.

Revision 1.1  1997/09/01 19:43:34  textgod
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.

</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
      <div n="1" type="dedication">
<opener><salute>TO THE MOST ILLUSTRIOUS NOBLE LADY, 
<lb/>ADORNED WITH ALL GIFTS BOTH OF MIND 
<lb/>AND BODY, MARY COUNTESS OF PEMBROKE</salute></opener>

<p>Delia born of a laurel-crowned race, true sister of Sidney the bard of
<lb/>Apollo, fostering parent of letters, to whose immaculate embrace
<lb/>virtue, outraged by the assault of barbarism and ignorance, flieth for
<lb/>refuge, as once Philomela from the Thracian tyrant; Muse of the
<lb/>Poets of our time, and of all most happily burgeoning wits; descen-
<lb/>dant of the gods, who impartest now to my rude pen breathings of a
<lb/>lofty rage, whereby my poor self hath, methinks, power to surpass
<lb/>what my unripe talent is wont to bring forth: Deign to be patron to
<lb/>this posthumous Amyntas, as to thine adoptive son: the rather that
<lb/>his dying father had most humbly bequeathed to thee his keeping.
<lb/>And though thy glorious name is spread abroad not only among us
<lb/>but even among foreign nations, too far ever to be destroyed by the
<lb/>rusty antiquity of Time, or added to by the praise of mortals (for
<lb/>how can anything be greater than what is infinite?), yet, crowned as
<lb/>thou art by the songs of many as by a starry diadem Ariadne, scorn
<lb/>not this pure priest of Phoebus bestowing another star upon thy
<lb/>crown: but with that sincerity of mind which Jove the father of men
<lb/>and of gods hath linked as hereditary to thy noble family, receive
<lb/>and watch over him. So shall I, whose slender wealth is but the sea-
<lb/>shore myrtle of Venus, and Daphne's evergreen laurel, on the fore-
<lb/>most page of every poem invoke thee as Mistress of the Muses to my
<lb/>aid: to sum up all, thy virtue, which shall overcome virtue herself,
<lb/>shall likewise overcome even eternity.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most desirous to do thee honor,</salute> <signed>C.M.</signed>
</closer>
</div></body></text></TEI.2>
